<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://ac3lab.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://ac3lab.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2024-05-23T14:02:05+00:00</updated><id>https://ac3lab.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">blank</title><subtitle>Marrying academic rigor with practical applications to benefit sports </subtitle><entry><title type="html">In-Depth Analysis of Bayer Leverkusen - Past Seasons and Current Campaign</title><link href="https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2024/post_leverkusen_2_en/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="In-Depth Analysis of Bayer Leverkusen - Past Seasons and Current Campaign"/><published>2024-05-23T10:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-05-23T10:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2024/post_leverkusen_2_en</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2024/post_leverkusen_2_en/"><![CDATA[<hr/> <p align="justify"> Se quiser ler este texto em pt-br, <a href="https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2000/post_leverkusen_2_pt/"> clique aqui.</a> </p> <h2>Introduction</h2> <div style="text-align: justify"> Many aspects of Leverkusen have changed under Xabi Alonso. Some of the main changes have been the players and the way the squad has been managed. Therefore, in order to understand the success Leverkusen have enjoyed this season, it's important to analyze what happened to the squad before and after Xabi Alonso's arrival.<br/><br/> <h2>Players in the Squad</h2> One of the main changes made after the arrival of Xabi Alonso was the management of the players in the squad. To make this clearer, we analyze the players in the team over the last 3 seasons.<br/><br/> <h3>Season 2021/2022</h3> In 21/22, the team had a vast squad, with a total of 35 players and an average age of close to 24.5 years. In addition, the average value per player was around 13 million euros. In that season, the most estimated sector of the field on the market was the attack, with a value of approximately 170.70 million euros.<br/><br/> In 2021, Leverkusen hired a new coach, Swiss Gerardo Seone, who played his first game on August 7, 2021. Under the Swiss, Leverkusen played mostly in a 4-2-3-1 formation, very different from what happens today with Xabi Alonso. It's worth remembering that Xabi's style of play has already been discussed here on our blog!<br/><br/> It was in the 2021 season that the current seventh most valuable player in the world gained more prominence, being a player used frequently by Gerardo. In addition to the Leverkusen revelation, other players began to gain more prominence in the team too, such as striker Shick, who was the team's top scorer that season.<br/><br/> <h3>Season 2022/2023</h3> In 22/23, the squad didn't change much; it remained substantially the same as in 21/22. However, it was during this season that Xabi Alonso took over the team. To be more precise, Xabi took charge of Leverkusen on matchday 9 of the Bundesliga and matchday 4 of the Champions League.<br/><br/> Despite the few changes to the squad in general, Leverkusen sold some defenders and signed more midfielders. As a result, the most valued sector in 2022 was the midfield, which was valued at more than 185 million euros at the time.<br/><br/> After these small changes, the squad still had 35 players in it, the same number as in the 21/22 season, with the average age dropping slightly to 24.2 years. The average value of each player remained similar compared to 21/22.<br/><br/> <div style="width: 100%; margin: 0 auto; text-align: center;"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2024-05-23-post_leverkusen_2/player_squad.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <h3>Season 2023/2024 (current season)</h3> After the end of Xabi's first season at Leverkusen, the coach appeared to have more autonomy in assembling the squad for 23/24. The number of players has dropped considerably compared to previous years, and Leverkusen now have just 27 players, a reduction of 22%. At the moment, Leverkusen's average age is 24.8 and the average value of each player is 22 million euros. In other words, the average age has changed very little, but the value per player has increased by almost 70% compared to the 22/23 season.<br/><br/> However, even with the considerable reduction in the squad, Leverkusen have moved much more on the market than in recent seasons. In addition, the total value of the current squad has increased by 31% compared to last season. It is therefore essential to analyze Leverkusen's signings this season and how the players have increased in value since Xabi Alonso's arrival.<br/><br/> <h2>Hiring</h2> The main signings made after the arrival of Xabi Alonso were the transfer of midfielder Xhaka, who played for Arsenal, for 25 million euros; the arrival of striker Boniface, who played for Union Saint-Gilloise in Belgium; the transfer of winger Grimaldo, who played for Benfica, who arrived for free; and the arrival of goalkeeper Kovar, who was at Manchester United, who cost around 5 million euros. The one-off signings were extremely important for the Leverkusen team, with the five main players in the German team being Wirtz, Palacios, Xhaka, Grimaldo, Kovar, and Boniface.<br/><br/> Despite the signings, the players who were already at the club have improved incredibly. To analyze the growth of players, their market value is a very interesting parameter. In the graph below, you can see the players who have risen the most in value since Xabi Alonso's arrival. It's important to note that Boniface, acquired this season by Leverkusen, already has a market value almost double what he was paid. Boniface and Grimaldo, the latter of whom was acquired for free, show how well the signings have been executed, making the most of the opportunities on the market.<br/><br/> <div style="width: 100%; margin: 0 auto; text-align: center;"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2024-05-23-post_leverkusen_2/player_market.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> In terms of player valuations alone, the balance was positive and exceeded 90 million euros. The estimated value of the total squad is almost 595 million euros, of which only 80 million were invested this year. It's worth remembering that in 2023 many players were sold, loaned, or released by Leverkusen, and the devaluation of the squad due to these losses totals 119 million. As such, in addition to the amount invested, Xabi Alonso's work has been fundamental in valuing the players. Xabi qualified the players already in the squad, and Leverkusen took advantage of the opportunities of a very competitive market.<br/><br/> <h2>Team Performance</h2> Finally, it's interesting to compare the development of the team over the three seasons mentioned above. In 2021/2022 before Xabi Alonso, in 2022/2023 before and after the arrival of the Spanish coach, and the 2023/2024 season when Xabi had more autonomy in the formation of the squad.<br/><br/> <h3>Season 2021/2022</h3> In the 21/22 season, Leverkusen performed well in terms of results. Despite an early exit from the Europa League, beaten by Atalanta in the last 16, they finished 3rd in the Bundesliga and therefore qualified for the Champions League the following season. One of the reasons for the squad remaining very similar in the 22/23 season is precisely the good performance in 21/22.<br/><br/> In 21/22, Leverkusen conceded 47 goals and scored 80, with a good offensive record, averaging 2.4 goals per game in the Bundesliga. In addition, the German team's main players this season were Wirtz, Shick, and Demirbay.<br/><br/> <h3>Season 2022/2023</h3> The start of the 22/23 season was very different from what was imagined. With the squad maintained and, therefore, the project continuing, it was expected that the team would at least achieve a performance similar to that of the 21/22 season. However, Leverkusen got off to a terrible start and by the 9th matchday of the Bundesliga were in 15th place, close to the relegation zone. At the same time, on Matchday 3 of the Champions League, they were bottom of their group, which included Club Brugge, Porto, and Atlético de Madrid.<br/><br/> After poor results, Xabi Alonso was invited to take over the team on October 8, 2022. After the arrival of the new coach, Leverkusen finished 3rd in the Champions League group stage and qualified for the Europa League, only to fall to Roma in the semi-finals. At the end of the season, Leverkusen finished 6th in the Bundesliga and secured a place in the 2023/2024 Europa League.<br/><br/> Leverkusen's main players after Xabi Alonso took over were Wirtz, Demirbay, and Palácios. In other words, Leverkusen's highlights remained similar to the 2021 season, but Palácios was able to develop much more after the Spanish coach's arrival.<br/><br/> <h3>Season 2023/2024</h3> This season, Leverkusen need no introduction. They've won their first Bundesliga title in history and without losing a single game. Still in the Bundesliga, they've scored a total of 89 goals and conceded just 24, an average of 2.6 goals per game. Leverkusen have also conquered an average of 62% of possession per match in the Bundesliga.<br/><br/> Apart from all the prominence the team had in the Bundesliga, Leverkusen is in the final of the Europa League and is considered by many to be the favorite to win the title. The final will be played between the German club and Atalanta.<br/><br/> As for Leverkusen's highlights this season, the best players were Grimaldo, Wirtz, Palacios, Xhaka, Kovar, Hofmann, and Boniface. What's important to note is that the players signed were highlights of the team during the season, which demonstrates a clear efficiency when it comes to using players.<br/><br/> <h2>Conclusion</h2> Xabi Alonso's management has transformed Leverkusen into a highly competitive team, reflected by the unprecedented Bundesliga title win and the Europa League final. The reduction and qualification of the squad, with strategic signings and the valorization of the players already in the squad, significantly increased the team's market value. With an efficient style of play, Leverkusen not only improved their performance on the pitch, but also highlighted the ability of their players, such as Wirtz, Palacios, and new signings Xhaka, Grimaldo, Kovar, and Boniface, consolidating themselves as one of the strongest teams of the season.<br/><br/> Stay tuned to our social networks, as next week we'll be posting our final analysis of Xabi Alonso's brilliant season.<br/><br/> </div>]]></content><author><name>Ace Laboratory Football Team - Hugo Antunes</name></author><category term="Football;"/><category term="Analysis"/><category term="Football;"/><category term="Bundesliga;"/><category term="Analysis"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Se quiser ler este texto em pt-br, clique aqui.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">In-Depth Analysis of Bayer Leverkusen - Xabi Alonso’s Playing Style</title><link href="https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2024/post_leverkusen_1_en/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="In-Depth Analysis of Bayer Leverkusen - Xabi Alonso’s Playing Style"/><published>2024-05-20T10:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-05-20T10:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2024/post_leverkusen_1_en</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2024/post_leverkusen_1_en/"><![CDATA[<hr/> <p align="justify"> Se quiser ler este texto em pt-br, <a href="https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2000/post_leverkusen_1_pt/"> clique aqui.</a> </p> <h2>Introduction</h2> <div style="text-align: justify"> <div style="width: 90%; margin: 0 auto; text-align: center;"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2024-05-20-post_leverkusen_1/last_minute.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> There’s been one unbeaten team in all competitions for exactly one year, since May 2023. Champions of their national league, finalists in their country’s cup and in the UEFA competition. In moments when it seems like this team is finally going to lose, they come back with an unshakeable determination, score goals in added time and maintain their unbeaten streak and sequence in championships. How did a team that hadn't attracted attention in soccer for a few years manage to become a top power in European soccer, with the longest unbeaten streak in history? In this series of posts, ACE Laboratory will analyze and identify the playing style of Bayer Leverkusen and their coach Xabi Alonso, aiming to uncover the reasons behind the magnificent run the team has done in 2024.<br/><br/> <h2>What is Xabi Alonso’s playing style?</h2> Xabi Alonso, a former player who has won every possible title and is known for being extremely technical and analytical, worked with gigantic teams and excellent coaches like Mourinho, Guardiola, and Ancelotti. Each with their different styles, Xabi managed to absorb the best qualities from each, becoming a great communicator, strategist, and football enthusiast. After completing the UEFA course, he started in Real Madrid's U-14 team and soon moved to Real Sociedad B. There, technical skills and ball control were the focus, and the club was promoted to the second division for the first time in 60 years. From there, Bayer Leverkusen saw in Xabi someone who could save the team from the critical situation of relegation, and history began to be made. But how does Bayer Leverkusen play now, having been led by Alonso for over a year?<br/><br/> <h3>Bayer Leverkusen without possession</h3> In the defensive sector, Alonso's team applies high pressure during the opponent's build-up in a mid-block, forcing errors to regain possession. Depending on the match, the German champion can adopt two different formations while defending: a 5-2-2-1, pressing the opponent's build-up with five players, crowding the midfield, and forcing plays to the sides of the field where the wing-backs press and win the ball; or a 4-2-3-1, which allows for an easier transition out of defense after stealing the ball.<br/><br/> Additionally, Leverkusen employs counter-pressing, commonly known as Gegenpressing. Xabi needed only a few months to shape and solidify this defensive tactic, establishing one of the most robust defenses in the league. By the end of the Bundesliga, they had achieved nearly 54 recoveries per match using this tactical approach.<br/><br/> <div style="width: 90%; margin: 0 auto; text-align: center;"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2024-05-20-post_leverkusen_1/recoveries.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> The team also conceded the fewest goals in the entire Bundesliga, allowing only 24 goals, proving the efficiency of their playing style.<br/><br/> <div style="width: 90%; margin: 0 auto; text-align: center;"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2024-05-20-post_leverkusen_1/Goals_Against.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <h3>Bayer Leverkusen with possession</h3> Classified as a middle ground between Pep Guardiola's positional play and the relational play seen in Fernando Diniz's Fluminense, Xabi Alonso trains the team for a build-up that depends on the current formation on the field. The playing style, which involves many passing exchanges, is evident in the team's passing network, where we can see the formation of "triangles" that allow multiple options for a player to work the ball.<br/><br/> <div style="width: 90%; margin: 0 auto; text-align: center;"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2024-05-20-post_leverkusen_1/passing_networks.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> Often, the wing-back Grimaldo operates defensively on the left, leaving two central defenders and a right-back to create space on the field and allow for "third man combinations." In these combinations, two players (usually Xhaka and Palacios) quickly pass the ball between themselves to draw defenders, creating space for a third player (usually Wirtz) to receive the ball. This tactic is characteristic of the relational play style.<br/><br/> In that way, the wing-backs have a much more significant role in the game, both offensively and defensively, switching sides of the field while attacking and defending. This can be observed in the passing network from the match against Augsburg, where wing-back Frimpong appeared more advanced than any other Bayer player.<br/><br/> By employing this tactic, Xabi Alonso has maximized the individual technical skills of his wide players, such as Frimpong and Grimaldo, who have contributed to 39 goals in the Bundesliga. In other words, nearly half of the team's goals have come through these two players.<br/><br/> <div style="width: 90%; margin: 0 auto; text-align: center;"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2024-05-20-post_leverkusen_1/augsburg.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> The use of this tactic is evidenced by the number of passes made by Bayer, the highest in the Bundesliga in the 2023-24 season. Additionally, the four advanced players move a lot, preventing the opposing defenders from pushing up their defensive line.<br/><br/> <div style="width: 90%; margin: 0 auto; text-align: center;"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2024-05-20-post_leverkusen_1/Passes_per_match.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> However, it is also common to see the team building up play with three defenders, utilizing the flanks with advanced wing-backs (usually Grimaldo and Frimpong), midfielders and forwards giving closer non-positional options, through midfield with quick transitions to attack generally architected by Wirtz or with direct passes from the defense to the attack into the empty spaces created by the team’s movementation. This is exemplified by the high number of progressive passes per game.<br/><br/> <div style="width: 90%; margin: 0 auto; text-align: center;"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2024-05-20-post_leverkusen_1/progressive_passes.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> If the opponents remain too rigid centrally, the team starts forming narrow diamond patterns, allowing Bayer to continue doing their short and dynamic passes to reach the final third of the field. Another possibility is that if the opponents press Leverkusen's short passing exchanges, the ball is moved to the opposite flank, which will have plenty of free space.<br/><br/> Moreover, the German team doesn't rely solely on movement and masterful passing to score goals this season, since approximately 10% of all goals scored by Xabi Alonso's team have come from set-pieces. Additionally, goals from counter-attacks are also common for the German side when necessary.<br/><br/> <div style="width: 90%; margin: 0 auto; text-align: center;"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2024-05-20-post_leverkusen_1/dead_balls.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <h3>Final third of the field</h3> The final third of the German team's attack is almost unpredictable. The advance of the wing-backs through the flanks mixed with midfielders infiltrating the box, along with a bit of accurate long-range shooting, create Xabi Alonso's magical formula for the team's incredible effectiveness. Thus, a statistic that demonstrates the unpredictability of the team led by the Spanish maestro is the percentage of attacks from each offensive third of the field, with the left, middle, and right accounting for 33%, 34%, and 33% respectively.<br/><br/> Such offensive prowess not only leads to a flurry of goals and chances created for the German team but also contributes to the team's unbeaten streak, which, when being behind on the scoreboard, always finds a way, often through the tactics taught by Xabi Alonso, combined with a bit of luck, to score goals and maintain their unbeaten record intact for all season.<br/><br/> <div style="width: 90%; margin: 0 auto; text-align: center;"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2024-05-20-post_leverkusen_1/Goal_Creating_Actions.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> A common tactic is as follows: when reaching the final third of the field, the wing-backs advance and the team's formation shifts to a 3-2-5, with the central players pushing up to receive the ball and create more options for playmaking, thus creating a numerical advantage that makes the team unpredictable and overwhelms the opposing defense. During this advancement, other players move up to occupy the midfield. The team is so efficient that it ranks in the top 3 in chances created from open play, but in comparison, has few chances from set-pieces.<br/><br/> <div style="width: 90%; margin: 0 auto; text-align: center;"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2024-05-20-post_leverkusen_1/live_dead_balls.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <h3>Weakness</h3> Due to the relational play, if the team loses the ball in the attacking side and fails apply quick pressure, the opponent has a lot of space on the flanks of the field (where the full-backs should be), since the players concentrate in a compressed manner for effective passing combinations and triangles. However, if the midfielders in transition cover the flanks, the central area becomes weakened and opportunities arise for the opponent. The system relies entirely on the players' perfection and minimizing errors. An example of this was observed in the away game against Qarabag in the UEFA Europa League, where both goals conceded were due to possession losses and effective counter-attacks by the Azerbaijani team.<br/><br/> <div style="width: 90%; margin: 0 auto; text-align: center;"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2024-05-20-post_leverkusen_1/possession_lost.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> But, as we can see by the team’s results in the season and their goal difference stats, the risk is worth taking. <br/><br/> <div style="width: 90%; margin: 0 auto; text-align: center;"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2024-05-20-post_leverkusen_1/Goal_Difference.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <h2>Conclusion</h2> It is evident that Xabi Alonso has blended various influences and added his own product to create a team capable of an unbeaten performance in the Bundesliga. However, one of the key aspects of this team is the individuality of each player, who has fit into the Spanish coach's system while incorporating their own unique playing styles. When facing Xabi Alonso in tactical chess, one doesn't see his pieces as knights, towers, or pawns, but rather as twenty-four players with different characteristics that change the German team's playing style. These players are the reason behind the team's immense success this season and the singularity of this squad that has captivated the world. In the next post, we will analyze the evolution of these players and the team, leading to what is now known as the first team to win the first unbeaten Bundesliga title. </div>]]></content><author><name>Ace Laboratory Football Team - Caio Santos e Lucas Calmon</name></author><category term="Football;"/><category term="Analysis"/><category term="Football;"/><category term="Bundesliga;"/><category term="Analysis"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Se quiser ler este texto em pt-br, clique aqui.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Brasileirão 2024 - 5rd Round</title><link href="https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2024/post_brasileirao_5-en/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Brasileirão 2024 - 5rd Round"/><published>2024-05-06T12:30:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-05-06T12:30:00+00:00</updated><id>https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2024/post_brasileirao_5-en</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2024/post_brasileirao_5-en/"><![CDATA[<hr/> <p align="justify"> Se quiser ler este texto em pt-br, <a href="https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2000/post_brasileirao_5-pt/"> clique aqui.</a> </p> <h2>Introduction</h2> <div style="text-align: justify"> <p align="justify"> Round 5 of the Campeonato Brasileiro has come to an end, and it was a shorter one, with 3 games postponed. We'll continue our coverage of the top 4 teams in the round, analyzing the games of Athletico, Bahia, Botafogo and Atlético-MG. </p> </div> <h2>Botafogo x Bahia</h2> <div style="text-align: justify"> <div style="width: 80%; margin: 0 auto; text-align: center;"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2024-05-06-post_brasileirao_5/en/bot_bah.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <p align="justify"> At the Nilton Santos Stadium, Botafogo hosted Bahia in a very busy match. In the first half, both teams scored, despite a relative dominance by Bahia, who had the best chances of the match so far (xG of 1.75 against 0.22). However, we saw a very different second half, with Botafogo clearly dominating their opponents in almost every aspect (possession, chances created, shots on goal). Unfortunately for Botafogo, Bahia managed to get through the pressure without conceding, and in the 86th minute Rafael Ratão scored for the visitors, confirming an important away win. </p> </div> <h2>Athletico x Vasco</h2> <div style="text-align: justify"> <div style="width: 80%; margin: 0 auto; text-align: center;"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2024-05-06-post_brasileirao_5/en/cap_vas.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <p align="justify"> At the Ligga Arena, Athletico Paranaense hosted Vasco in an almost one-sided match. Furacão managed a simple victory, with only a goal scored by Erick in the first half. However, the sending off of Vasco midfielder Hugo Moura in the 16th minute was a determining factor in the match. In the first half, Athletico attacked more and accumulated 1.65 xG, while Vasco ended the first half with 0.0 expected goals. In the second half, despite being down a player, Vasco went on the attack and balanced the match. </p> </div> <h2>Fluminense x Atlético-MG</h2> <div style="text-align: justify"> <div style="width: 80%; margin: 0 auto; text-align: center;"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2024-05-06-post_brasileirao_5/en/flu_cam.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <p align="justify"> At the Kleber Andrade Stadium, Atlético-MG visited Fluminense, in a match marked by a heroic draw for the visiting team. Despite the balance during the first two thirds of the game, Fluminense were more effective than their opponents, scoring two goals and earning the chance to just manage the result they had built up. However, in the 73rd minute, the substitutions made by coach Gabriel Milito changed the course of the match and in just six minutes, Eduardo Vargas, coming off the bench, had already equalized for Galo. After the equalizer, Fluminense came under a bit of pressure, but the result held. </p> </div>]]></content><author><name>Ace Laboratory Football Team</name></author><category term="Football;"/><category term="Analysis"/><category term="Football;"/><category term="Brasileirao;"/><category term="Analysis"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Se quiser ler este texto em pt-br, clique aqui.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Rio Marathon 2023 – Exploratory with a bit of statistics and predictive estimation</title><link href="https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2024/post_marathon_en/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Rio Marathon 2023 – Exploratory with a bit of statistics and predictive estimation"/><published>2024-05-02T08:30:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-05-02T08:30:00+00:00</updated><id>https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2024/post_marathon_en</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2024/post_marathon_en/"><![CDATA[<p align="justify"> Se quiser ler este texto em pt-br, <a href="https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2000/post_marathon_pt/"> clique aqui.</a> </p> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2024-05-02-post_marathon/0.jpeg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <p align="justify"> Convenience, practicality, and health benefits are some of the reasons that make running an attractive, democratic, and popular sport. That's why street running has been gaining prominence worldwide, and events like marathons already attract thousands of athletes, whether elite or amateur. In Rio de Janeiro, for example, the 21st edition of the Marathon took place over the Corpus Christi holiday in 2023, and had over 40 thousands registrations (considering all the routes), which also economically boosted the city. </p> <p align="justify"> The 42k route, which passes through the city's main landmarks, crowned kenyan Josphat Kiprotich and ethiopian Zinash Debebe as the winners of the race, both from the elite male and female pelotons. Kiprotich finished the race in 2h13min29s – two seconds faster than the previous record, while Debebe completed it in 22h36min00s. </p> <p align="justify"> In just over a month, the city will host another edition of the event, and as a stimulus for preparation, we conducted a brief exploratory analysis - with a predictive touch - on the data from the 2023 general peloton results, so that we can reveal some insights about the race. Let's check it out! </p> <p>Exploratory</p> <p align="justify"> In total, informations from 5799 athletes from the general group was analyzed, with 30% being female. Among the registrants, when we look at the age groups, the age group with the highest concentration, both for men and women, is 40-44 years old. In the graph below, we can see how this frequency occurs in the different groups: </p> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2024-05-02-post_marathon/1.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <p align="justify"> When we look at athlete frequency from the perspective of performance, we see a higher concentration of men with a finishing time of 3,5-4 hours. For the female gender, the highest concentration is in the 4-4,5 hours range. Five women completed the race in less than 3 hours. </p> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2024-05-02-post_marathon/2.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <p align="justify"> The shortest female time was 2h55min04s, while the shortest male time was 2h28min33s. The longest times were 6h39min23s and 6h42min59s, respectively, noting that we are looking at net time (time between crossing the start and finish lines). In the graph below, we can see the time distributions by gender: </p> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2024-05-02-post_marathon/3.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <p align="justify"> It is also possible to view the distribution of the final time by age group and for each declared gender: </p> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2024-05-02-post_marathon/4.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2024-05-02-post_marathon/5.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <p align="justify"> For both genders, the age group that stands out for having the fastest athletes is the 30-34 age group. Additionally, the male group had 2 registered athletes over 80 years old, which increasingly shows that there is truly no age limit for sports. </p> <p>Performance prediction</p> <p align="justify"> Using as reference the article Prediction Marathon Using Artificial Intelligence [Lerebourg et al. 2023] and the article Pacing strategy of the finishers of the world marathon majors series [Kais et al. 2018], which assess the effect of variables such as gender and age on performance prediction using regression models, we also employed this information to train a multivariate regression model aiming to predict the finishing time of the race. </p> <p align="justify"> For this purpose, we used the python library <a href="https://www.statsmodels.org/stable/index.html">statsmodels</a>, after performing all the necessary data preprocessing and splitting it into training and testing sets. Below is the graph that compares the actual time versus what was predicted by the model: </p> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2024-05-02-post_marathon/6.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <p align="justify"> From the graph, one conclusion we can take is that the values predicted by the model don't follow the actual values as they increase. Additionally, evaluating the modeling statistics, the gender variable apparently doesn't have statistical significance in the prediction (p-value = 0.721). Therefore, there is a need to include other variables in the modeling. Some studies in the literature suggest the use of various information in prediction, such as anthropometric, physiological, biomechanical data, as well as training information like experience, step rhythm, and blood lactate concentration. </p> <p>Summary results:</p> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2024-05-02-post_marathon/7.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <p align="justify"> Finally, the residual distribution graph, since one of the premises for a good adjustment of a linear regression model is that the residuals are normally distributed: </p> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2024-05-02-post_marathon/8.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <p align="justify"> The distribution resembles a normal distribution, but with a slight positive skewness (left-skewed concentration). There are several tests we can perform to verify this, and some of them are already included in the summary table of results provided above. The <a href="https://docs.scipy.org/doc/scipy/reference/generated/scipy.stats.skew.html">Skewness</a>, for example, already indicates the non-normality and skewness of the error distribution (the closer to 0, the more "normal" the distribution is), and the <a href="https://docs.scipy.org/doc/scipy/reference/generated/scipy.stats.kurtosis.html">Kurtosis</a> as well, as it is associated with the flattening of the distribution (for values &gt; 3, the distribution is "higher" than the normal distribution). </p> <p align="justify"> In this case, it's important to stay vigilant in evaluating the confidence intervals, which could be incorrect. Furthermore, there are other assumptions for a good regression fit, such as a null expectation and independence of residuals, and homoscedasticity (constant variation of residuals), but as it's not the focus of this post, we'll save it for a future discussion. </p> <p>Discussion</p> <p align="justify"> In this post, we saw some descriptive statistics of the results from the 2023 Rio Marathon for the general group, visualizing how performance varies across different age groups and genders. With these data, we developed a simple performance prediction model, already raising the question of how challenging it can be to construct such a model with limited information. </p> <p align="justify"> Street running is a sport that has been growing rapidly, and the debate about which factors contributing to performance improvement is far from over. We hope to absorb and contribute more to this process over time. </p> <p align="justify"> We hope you enjoyed reading and any suggestions are welcome. </p> <p>References</p> <p>https://maratonadorio.com.br/<br/> https://www.folhavitoria.com.br/esportes/blogs/corridaderua/2023/08/17/estudo-realizado-na-maratona-do-rio-2023-comprova-o-sucesso-do-evento-deste-ano/<br/> Ülari K., et al. Pacing strategy of the finishers of the world marathon majors series. Institute of Sport Sciences and Physiotherapy, University of Tartu, Tartu, Estonia. 2018.<br/> Lerebourg, L. et al. Prediction Marathon Using Artificial Intelligence. Int J Sports Med, 2023, 44: 352–360.</p>]]></content><author><name>Ace Laboratory Running Team</name></author><category term="Running;"/><category term="Rio"/><category term="Marathon;"/><category term="Python;"/><category term="MachineLearning"/><category term="Running;"/><category term="Rio"/><category term="Marathon;"/><category term="Python;"/><category term="MachineLearning"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Analyzing data from the 2023 Rio Marathon results and developing a simple performance prediction model]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Brasileirão 2024 - 4rd Round</title><link href="https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2024/post_brasileirao_4-en/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Brasileirão 2024 - 4rd Round"/><published>2024-04-30T10:15:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-04-30T10:15:00+00:00</updated><id>https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2024/post_brasileirao_4-en</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2024/post_brasileirao_4-en/"><![CDATA[<hr/> <p align="justify"> Se quiser ler este texto em pt-br, <a href="https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2000/post_brasileirao_4-pt/"> clique aqui.</a> </p> <h2>Introduction</h2> <div style="text-align: justify"> <p align="justify"> Round 4 of the Campeonato Brasileiro 2024 has come to a close, in an exciting week with 4 games with 3 or more goals, Botafogo taking the lead in the competition with victory in the derby, Criciúma beating Vasco da Gama and a goalless draw in the derby between Palmeiras and São Paulo. We'll then analyze the games of Botafogo, Atlético-MG, Bragantino and Atlético-PR. </p> </div> <h2>Flamengo x Botafogo</h2> <div style="text-align: justify"> <div style="width: 80%; margin: 0 auto; text-align: center;"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2024-04-30-post_brasileirao_4/en/fla_bot.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <p align="justify"> At the Maracanã, Flamengo hosted Botafogo in a match marked by two completely opposite performances. Flamengo, despite having more possession, found it very difficult to finish their chances in a favorable way. This can be seen by comparing the number of shots (15) and shots on goal (0) by the rubro-negro team. On the other hand, Botafogo defended well without the ball and were much more efficient in attack, managing to have the best chances of the match and scoring two goals to claim another victory in the Brasileirão. </p> </div> <h2>Cuiabá vs Atlético-MG</h2> <div style="text-align: justify"> <div style="width: 80%; margin: 0 auto; text-align: center;"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2024-04-30-post_brasileirao_4/en/cui_cam.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <p align="justify"> At the Arena Pantanal, Cuiabá hosted Atlético-MG in a match that was dominated by their opponents. Gabriel Milito's team managed to turn the game's pace into goals in an extremely efficient manner and still not concede a goal. Despite scoring two goals from set pieces, scored by Gustavo Scarpa and Paulinho, Galo collected chances to increase the score away from home, accumulating a xG of 2.15. </p> </div> <h2>Fortaleza vs RB Bragantino</h2> <div style="text-align: justify"> <div style="width: 80%; margin: 0 auto; text-align: center;"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2024-04-30-post_brasileirao_4/en/for_rbb.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <p align="justify"> At the Castelão, Fortaleza and RB Bragantino played out an even contest, with both teams switching their moments of superiority. Despite the balance in possession and moments of pressure, Fortaleza managed to create more chances throughout the match, as shown by the almost constant increase in the tricolor's xG in the score line. </p> </div> <h2>Juventude vs Athletico</h2> <div style="text-align: justify"> <div style="width: 80%; margin: 0 auto; text-align: center;"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2024-04-30-post_brasileirao_4/en/juv_cap.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <p align="justify"> Finally, Athletico visited Juventude at the Alfredo Jaconi Stadium. Despite conceding an early goal, Athletico had the best chances, and even with a great performance from goalkeeper Gabriel Vasconcelos, they managed to tie the match. At the end of the game, Juventude applied great pressure on their opponents, taking 8 shots after 80 minutes of play, but were unable to change the outcome of the match. </p> </div>]]></content><author><name>Ace Laboratory Football Team</name></author><category term="Football;"/><category term="Analysis"/><category term="Football;"/><category term="Brasileirao;"/><category term="Analysis"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Se quiser ler este texto em pt-br, clique aqui.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Brasileirão 2024 - 3rd Round</title><link href="https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2024/post_brasileirao_3-en/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Brasileirão 2024 - 3rd Round"/><published>2024-04-23T15:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-04-23T15:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2024/post_brasileirao_3-en</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2024/post_brasileirao_3-en/"><![CDATA[<hr/> <p align="justify"> Se quiser ler este texto em pt-br, <a href="https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2000/post_brasileirao_3-pt/"> clique aqui.</a> </p> <h2>Introduction</h2> <div style="text-align: justify"> <p align="justify"> Last weekend (April 21st and 22nd), the 3rd round of the Brazilian Championship took place. After only 3 rounds, no team has a 100% record, proving that this is indeed one of the most fiercely contested tournaments in the world. Let's continue our coverage of the top 4 teams in the round, analyzing the matches of RB Bragantino, Flamengo, Botafogo, and Grêmio. </p> </div> <h2>RB Bragantino x Corinthians</h2> <div style="text-align: justify"> <div style="width: 80%; margin: 0 auto; text-align: center;"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2024-04-23-post_brasileirao_3/en/rbb_cor.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <p align="justify"> On Saturday, RB Bragantino and Corinthians faced off at the Nabi Abi Chedid Stadium. Massa Bruta managed to open the score in the 5th minute and maintained their lead throughout the match, benefiting from yet another lackluster performance by Corinthians, who, despite dominating possession for much of the game, failed to convert that dominance into clear goal-scoring opportunities. </p> </div> <h2>Palmeiras x Flamengo</h2> <div style="text-align: justify"> <div style="width: 80%; margin: 0 auto; text-align: center;"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2024-04-23-post_brasileirao_3/en/pal_fla.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <p align="justify"> At Allianz Parque, Palmeiras hosted Flamengo in a match that delivered less than expected, considering these are two of the top teams in Brazil. The game saw only 4 shots on target (1 for Palmeiras and 3 for Flamengo) and a modest xG (expected goals) of 0.4 for Verdão and 0.24 for the Rubro-Negro. </p> </div> <h2>Botafogo x Juventude </h2> <div style="text-align: justify"> <div style="width: 80%; margin: 0 auto; text-align: center;"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2024-04-23-post_brasileirao_3/en/bot_juv.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <p align="justify"> At Nilton Santos Stadium, Botafogo completely dominated Juventude. In addition to their convincing 5-1 victory, Botafogo scored more than double the expected goals for the match (2.38). However, Botafogo's defense has been one of the weaknesses of the squad, conceding 4 goals so far in the championship and allowing one goal to Juventude, who had less than 0.5 expected goals throughout the match. </p> </div> <h2>Grêmio x Cuiabá</h2> <div style="text-align: justify"> <div style="width: 80%; margin: 0 auto; text-align: center;"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2024-04-23-post_brasileirao_3/en/gre_cui.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <p align="justify"> At Arena Grêmio, the Tricolor Gaúcho faced Cuiabá and secured a narrow 1-0 victory. Despite the low-scoring affair, the game was highly eventful, with a total of 21 shots. The Dourado, despite not finding the back of the net, had a much higher xG than Grêmio, indicating efficiency in creation but also hinting at inefficiency in attack. Another statistic that highlights this is shot accuracy; Cuiabá attempted 14 shots, but only 3 were on target, while Grêmio had 7 shots, 4 of which were accurate. </p> </div>]]></content><author><name>Ace Laboratory Football Team</name></author><category term="Football;"/><category term="Analysis"/><category term="Football;"/><category term="Brasileirao;"/><category term="Analysis"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Se quiser ler este texto em pt-br, clique aqui.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Brasileirão 2024 - 2nd Round</title><link href="https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2024/post_brasileirao_2-en/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Brasileirão 2024 - 2nd Round"/><published>2024-04-15T15:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-04-15T15:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2024/post_brasileirao_2-en</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2024/post_brasileirao_2-en/"><![CDATA[<hr/> <p align="justify"> Se quiser ler este texto em pt-br, <a href="https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2000/post_brasileirao_2-pt/"> clique aqui.</a> </p> <h2>Introduction</h2> <div style="text-align: justify"> <p align="justify"> In a week with a double round that happened between 16/04 and 18/04, good games were played and the top 4 has changed considerably. For this round, we have Flamengo, Internacional, Juventude and Bragantino. </p> </div> <h2>Flamengo x São Paulo</h2> <div style="text-align: justify"> <div style="width: 80%; margin: 0 auto; text-align: center;"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2024-04-19-post_brasileirao_2/en/fla_sao.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <p align="justify"> On Wednesday, Flamengo and São Paulo faced each other at Maracanã in a rematch of Copa do Brasil’s 2023 final. This time around, the rubro-negro managed to maintain control during most of the game, only losing its grip after 70 minutes played, when the Tricolor finally got some chances and scored once with Ferreirinha. Besides Flamengo’s good performance, we can highlight Nico de La Cruz, who again showed he’s essential for the team in defense and playmaking. </p> </div> <h2>Palmeiras x Internacional</h2> <div style="text-align: justify"> <div style="width: 80%; margin: 0 auto; text-align: center;"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2024-04-19-post_brasileirao_2/en/pal_int.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <p align="justify"> At Barueri Arena, Internacional beat Palmeiras 1x0 with Wesley scoring. Palmeiras got a lot of game volume, but was inefficient when shooting, having lower than 17% shots hit (3 shots on goal with 18 total). On the other side, Internacional was way more efficient, though having lost a penalty kick, hitting higher xG than Palmeiras, even with few opportunities. </p> </div> <h2>Juventude x Corinthians </h2> <div style="text-align: justify"> <div style="width: 80%; margin: 0 auto; text-align: center;"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2024-04-19-post_brasileirao_2/en/juv_cor.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <p align="justify"> Juventude played Corinthians home at Alfredo Jaconi Stadium. Though having dominated for some time in the match, Timão’s low efficiency gave space for their opponent to grow in production. As result, Juventude took advantage of two bad moments of goalkeeper Cássio to open 2x0 in the first 15 minutes of second half, conquering their first win at Brasileirão. </p> </div> <h2>Red Bull Bragantino x Vasco</h2> <div style="text-align: justify"> <div style="width: 80%; margin: 0 auto; text-align: center;"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2024-04-19-post_brasileirao_2/en/rbr_vas.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <p align="justify"> Red Bull Bragantino faced Vasco in a very even match at Nabi Abi Chedid, winning 2x1 home. Bragantino’s goals were scored by Laquintana and Vitinha, while Vegetti lowered for the Gigante da Colina. RB Bragantino, though having won the match, had certain linearity in xGoals during the game. On the other side, Vasco lost at least one clear chance, losing the match even though they had more xG than their opponent. </p> </div>]]></content><author><name>Ace Laboratory Football Team</name></author><category term="Football;"/><category term="Analysis"/><category term="Football;"/><category term="Brasileirao;"/><category term="Analysis"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Se quiser ler este texto em pt-br, clique aqui.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Brasileirão 2024 - First Round</title><link href="https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2024/post_brasileirao_1-en/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Brasileirão 2024 - First Round"/><published>2024-04-15T11:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-04-15T11:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2024/post_brasileirao_1-en</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2024/post_brasileirao_1-en/"><![CDATA[<hr/> <p align="justify"> Se quiser ler este texto em pt-br, <a href="https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2000/post_brasileirao_1-pt/"> clique aqui.</a> </p> <h2>Introduction</h2> <div style="text-align: justify"> <p align="justify"> One of the most competitive leagues in the world, Brasileirão started this weekend (13/04). We at ACE Laboratory will, in every round, analyze the teams that find themselves in the top 4. For the first round, we brought the matches from Athletico-PR, Cruzeiro, Flamengo and Vasco. </p> </div> <h2>Athletico x Cuiabá</h2> <div style="text-align: justify"> <div style="width: 80%; margin: 0 auto; text-align: center;"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2024-04-15-post_brasileirao_1/en/cap_cui.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <p align="justify"> In the most unbalanced encounter of the 1st round, Athletico and Cuiabá faced each other at Ligga Arena. The “Furacão” had an impressive display, and we can see they dominated the match when we analyze that Cuiabá only shot once in 90 minutes. Offensively, Athletico was great, managing an easy win of 4x0. </p> </div> <h2>Cruzeiro x Botafogo</h2> <div style="text-align: justify"> <div style="width: 80%; margin: 0 auto; text-align: center;"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2024-04-15-post_brasileirao_1/en/cru_bot.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <p align="justify"> At the round’s most active match, Cruzeiro and Botafogo played a very interesting match for the supporters in Mineirão. Cruzeiro imposed their way of playing, which can be seen by analyzing the passing network and the number of shots (15). On the other side, Botafogo couldn’t have game volume, having only 6 shots. </p> </div> <h2>Atlético-GO x Flamengo </h2> <div style="text-align: justify"> <div style="width: 80%; margin: 0 auto; text-align: center;"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2024-04-15-post_brasileirao_1/en/fla_ago.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <p align="justify"> Sunday Atlético-GO and Flamengo faced each other at Estádio Serra Dourada. In a match full of controversies by the referees, we can still highlight the great performance by Atlético, who played with 10 men for the entire second half, and still managed to offer more danger than their opponent (shown by the greater xG during all 90 minutes, specially during the second half). Though the less than expected performance, Tite’s men managed to win by 2x1. </p> </div> <h2>Vasco x Grêmio</h2> <div style="text-align: justify"> <div style="width: 80%; margin: 0 auto; text-align: center;"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2024-04-15-post_brasileirao_1/en/vas_gre.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <p align="justify"> A balanced match between Vasco and Grêmio, the team from Rio won with their supporters in São Januário. An important highlight in this match is the difference between first and second halves. In the first 45 minutes, Vasco was the star, scoring two goals. While on the second half, Grêmio was way more offensive and had great chances of drawing the game. Looking at the xG timeline, it’s easy to see that Vasco’s attack kept almost linear during the match, while Grêmio was sharper in the last half. </p> </div>]]></content><author><name>Ace Laboratory Football Team</name></author><category term="Football;"/><category term="Analysis"/><category term="Football;"/><category term="Brasileirao;"/><category term="Analysis"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Se quiser ler este texto em pt-br, clique aqui.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Carioca Championship 2024 - Final - Second Leg</title><link href="https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2024/post_carioca_final2-en/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Carioca Championship 2024 - Final - Second Leg"/><published>2024-04-12T13:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-04-12T13:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2024/post_carioca_final2-en</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2024/post_carioca_final2-en/"><![CDATA[<hr/> <p align="justify"> Se quiser ler este texto em pt-br, <a href="https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2000/post_carioca_final2-pt/"> clique aqui.</a> </p> <h2>Introduction</h2> <div style="width: 55%; margin: 0 auto; text-align: center;"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2024-03-07-post_carioca_compilado/Carioca_2024_FERJ.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <div style="text-align: justify"> <p align="justify"> Last Sunday, Flamengo and Nova Iguaçu played the final match of the 2024 Carioca Championship. The result of 1x0 in favor of the team commanded by Tite only confirmed what was already expected and the rubro-negros are now state champions, thanks to a campaign marked by its defensive stability. So, let’s finish our coverage of Cariocão by talking about what we can analyze from the final’s statistics. </p> </div> <h2>Flamengo x Nova Iguaçu</h2> <div style="text-align: justify"> <h3>Match Analysis</h3> <div style="width: 80%; margin: 0 auto; text-align: center;"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2024-04-12-post_carioca_final2/en/game1.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <p align="justify"> Once more, Flamengo didn’t concede any goals during the match, equalizing Fluminense’s historic mark (in 1911) of just one goal conceded in the entire tournament. Repeating the script from the first leg, the rubro-negro’s defense prevented Nova Iguaçu from developing great chances, as they managed only 5 shots from inside the box and had a xG of just 0.7. </p> <p align="justify"> Although the Gávea team followed the high defensive standard shown throughout the competition, the attacking sector was way less objective than usual, with a xG of 1.64 and 10 shots from inside the box. Compared to the inspired performance of the attack in the first leg (xG of 3.35 and 16 shots inside the box), there was a considerable drop in performance, certainly associated with the interest in managing the advantage created in the first encounter. </p> <h3>Highlights</h3> <div style="width: 80%; margin: 0 auto; text-align: center;"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2024-04-12-post_carioca_final2/en/players1.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <p align="justify"> Despite a relatively uneventful game, there were players with performances worth highlighting. On Flamengo's side, defender Léo Pereira kept up his high standards and was instrumental in stopping the Baixada side's attack, with 4 tackles won and only 1 dribble conceded. It's also worth highlighting the player's role in creating plays, as he had 14 successful long balls (82% success rate). In addition to him, left winger Bruno Henrique came on in the second half and scored the winning goal for his team, with an impressive finish of just 0.05 xG. </p> <p align="justify"> For the team from Baixada, right-winger Xandinho put in a great attacking performance, with 5 shots, 100% of his dribbles correct and adding 0.60 xG to Nova Iguaçu's 0.70 total. Another highlight was goalkeeper Fabrício, who made 5 saves from inside the area. </p> </div> <h2>Final Remarks</h2> <div style="text-align: justify"> <p align="justify"> Finally, after three months of competition, the Carioca Championship is over. Looking at the tournament as a whole, we can see that the two finalists really were the great teams of the tournament. Flamengo, for their consistency and defensive solidity, and Nova Iguaçu, who stood up to the big teams in Rio de Janeiro with a much smaller budget, revealing very competent players and coaches. </p> </div>]]></content><author><name>Ace Laboratory Football Team</name></author><category term="Football;"/><category term="Analysis"/><category term="Football;"/><category term="Carioca;"/><category term="Analysis"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Se quiser ler este texto em pt-br, clique aqui.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Carioca Championship 2024 - Final - First Leg</title><link href="https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2024/post_carioca_final1-en/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Carioca Championship 2024 - Final - First Leg"/><published>2024-04-03T11:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-04-03T11:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2024/post_carioca_final1-en</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2024/post_carioca_final1-en/"><![CDATA[<hr/> <p align="justify"> Se quiser ler este texto em pt-br, <a href="https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2000/post_carioca_final1-pt/"> clique aqui.</a> </p> <h2>Introduction</h2> <div style="width: 55%; margin: 0 auto; text-align: center;"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2024-03-07-post_carioca_compilado/Carioca_2024_FERJ.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <div style="text-align: justify"> <p align="justify"> After waiting some time, last Saturday we had the first leg of the Campeonato Carioca 2024 final. The favorite Flamengo completely dominated the championship’s big surprise, Nova Iguaçu, winning 3x0 on the weekend. With this result, the team from Gávea is even closer to being the champions of Rio. Let’s analyze the data of those games and talk about what they can tell us of the game. </p> </div> <h2>Nova Iguaçu x Flamengo</h2> <div style="text-align: justify"> <h3>Match Analysis</h3> <div style="width: 80%; margin: 0 auto; text-align: center;"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2024-04-03-post_carioca_final1/en/game1.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <p align="justify"> Flamengo reached the amazing mark of 12 games without suffering a goal, the biggest sequence in the club’s history. Rubro-Negro’s great defense is shown in data by the low number of Nova Iguaçu’s shots from inside the zone (only 5) and by the even lower number of Expected Goals from the club from Baixada (0.59), which shows that only a small amount of shots meant danger to Agustín Rossi. While having a great defense, Flamengo also demonstrated great offensive plays, with 3.35 Expected Goals and 3 scored (2 for Pedro, and 1 own goal). </p> <p align="justify"> If on one side Nova Iguaçu’s attack wasn’t efficient, lots of shots were made, being comparable to both teams’ shots/minutes with the ball. But the Gigante da Baixada offered a small amount of risks and couldn’t impose their game style against Flamengo’s defense. The ball possession is one more thing that shows how the game was played, with 60% to the Rubro-Negro and 40% to the Gigante da Baixada. </p> <p align="justify"> In addition to the already good numbers, Flamengo made more than 75% of its shots from inside the opponent’s box. But it was evident that the goal difference could’ve been bigger, which makes it important to say that Flamengo has less goals than Expected Goals in the last two matches. On the second leg of the semifinal, Rubro-Negro’s attack didn’t reach expectations, and against Nova Iguaçu it wasn’t different. Considering the match’s one own goal, Flamengo just scored two times, with at least 3 being expected. </p> <h3>Highlights</h3> <div style="width: 80%; margin: 0 auto; text-align: center;"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2024-04-03-post_carioca_final1/en/players1.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <p align="justify"> Scoring two goals, we have to mention Pedro when talking about this match. In addition to his goals, he also had two key passes and four shots. In general, Flamengo’s left side played very well, Everton Cebolinha also did well, hitting 91% of his passes and 90% completed dribbles. While in defense goalkeeper Rossi had another great match, making 6 saves -2 from inside the zone- and having 100% accuracy on passes (23 passes and 4 long balls). </p> <p align="justify"> Besides having few opportunities, Nova Iguaçu’s attack can be highlighted through Bill. The attacker contributed alone to almost 40% of the team’s Expected Goals, plus 5 successful dribbles and 3 key passes. Another player that we should praise is Fabricio, the goalkeeper, making 6 saves and 4 from inside the zone. </p> </div> <h2>Final Remarks</h2> <div style="text-align: justify"> <p align="justify"> The first game of the Cariocão Final is gone. Flamengo has a big advantage, and it’s very hard, or even impossible for Nova Iguaçu to score 3 goals on the team that only suffered 1 in the entire Championship. But football is full of impossible events. </p> </div>]]></content><author><name>Ace Laboratory Football Team</name></author><category term="Football;"/><category term="Analysis"/><category term="Football;"/><category term="Carioca;"/><category term="Analysis"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Se quiser ler este texto em pt-br, clique aqui.]]></summary></entry></feed>