<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.4.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://ac3lab.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://ac3lab.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2025-10-17T23:40:49+00:00</updated><id>https://ac3lab.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">blank</title><subtitle>Marrying academic rigor with practical applications to benefit sports </subtitle><entry><title type="html">Fouls in Sports: Strategy, Safety and Game Control</title><link href="https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2025/post_faltas_en/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Fouls in Sports: Strategy, Safety and Game Control"/><published>2025-10-09T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-10-09T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2025/post_faltas_en</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2025/post_faltas_en/"><![CDATA[<hr/> <p align="justify"> Se quiser ler este texto em pt-br, <a href="https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2000/post_faltas_pt/"> clique aqui.</a> </p> <style>body{text-align:justify}</style> <h2><b>NBA</b></h2> <p>In NBA basketball, fouls play a fundamental role in the game’s dynamics and are divided into three main categories: personal foul, technical foul, and flagrant foul. Personal fouls generally occur in situations of illegal physical contact and, throughout the game, accumulate consequences: each player is eliminated after committing 6 personal fouls, and when a team reaches the fifth collective foul in the same quarter, the opponent automatically enters the bonus situation, receiving free throws on any new defensive foul. Technical fouls are called for unsportsmanlike conduct or behavioral violations, such as excessive complaining or delaying the game; their punishment is 1 free throw and ball possession for the opponent, and the player or coach who accumulates 2 technicals is automatically ejected. Finally, flagrant fouls, applied to contacts considered violent or excessive, result in 2 free throws and ball possession for the opponent, in addition to counting as a personal foul: at level 1 (Flagrant 1), the player is only ejected if he commits two; at level 2 (Flagrant 2), ejection is immediate.</p> <p>Free throws are an essential component of scoring and can reflect the offensive performance of players and teams throughout the regular season. In the last four seasons, the player with the highest points per game average also led in free throws made per game: <a href="https://www.nba.com/stats/players/traditional?Season=2024-25&amp;SeasonType=Regular%20Season&amp;dir=A&amp;sort=FTM">Joel Embiid was the leader in 2021-22, 2022-23 and 2023-24, while Shai Gilgeous-Alexander took that position in the 2024-25 season</a>. Additionally, in the 2024-25 season, of the 10 teams with the highest free throw differential — calculated as free throws made per game minus free throws made by the opponent — 8 qualified for the playoffs, evidencing that the ability to convert free throws is an important factor for both individual performance and collective team success.</p> <div style="display: flex; justify-content: center;"> <div> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2025-10-09-faltas/nba_ftm_difference.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" title="NBA Free Throw Difference" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <p>A peculiarity of fouls in basketball is that they can be strategically exploited, as in the case of Hack-a-Shaq, a tactic that emerged in 1978 and became popular when Don Nelson, coach of the Dallas Mavericks, applied it against Shaquille O’Neal, giving rise to the strategy’s name. The goal of Hack-a-Shaq consists of committing intentional fouls on an opposing player with low free throw efficiency, forcing them to shoot free throws instead of allowing normal offensive flow. Although Shaq is the most famous example, the strategy has been applied to other great players, such as Dennis Rodman, Ben Simmons and, in the recent playoffs, Mitchell Robinson, center for the New York Knicks, who converted only 45.2% of his free throws, well below the NBA average of 77.7% in the 2024-25 season.</p> <p>In the series between New York Knicks and Boston Celtics, won by the Knicks 4-2, center Mitchell Robinson became the central target of the intentional foul strategy. Despite his low free throw efficiency, Robinson recorded an offensive rating of 116 — a statistic that measures how many points a player generates for the team per 100 possessions. However, if he were forced to go to the free throw line on every possession, the Knicks would have an offensive rating of only 90.4 in the series, which shows how the strategy could, in theory, significantly reduce the team’s offensive efficiency. On the other hand, applying Hack-a-Shaq has trade-offs: besides eliminating transition attack opportunities, it forces defenders to accumulate fouls, running the risk of being eliminated when they reach the limit of six personal fouls. Even so, the Celtics coach took this tactic to the extreme, committing intentional fouls even before the team was in the bonus, just to reach the five collective fouls faster and force Robinson to go to the free throw line.</p> <p>In conclusion, fouls in NBA basketball go far beyond simple game interruptions: they shape strategies, define the pace of games and can be both a defensive resource and a weakness exploited by the opponent. Between the impact of personal fouls on bonus accumulation, the discipline required to avoid technical fouls and the severity of flagrant fouls, to the application of tactics like Hack-a-Shaq, it becomes clear how this element of the rules is central to the league’s identity. More than punishments, fouls represent strategic choices that directly influence the outcome of a season.</p> <h2><b>NFL</b></h2> <p>Fouls in the NFL, due to their intensity, have received numerous changes over time. The league, created in 1920, based its game on college football and maintained its initial rules for 12 years. It was a mix between Rugby and the American Football we know today. Due to evolution, it became necessary to create fouls and penalties for the game, to reduce recurring injuries and concussions in football. <a href="https://operations.nfl.com/updates/football-ops/concussions-decrease-to-historic-low-in-2024-nfl-season">According to data released by the league itself</a>, the number of concussions in 2024 decreased by about 17% compared to 2023 and 13% compared to the 2021-2023 period.</p> <div class="row"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2025-10-09-faltas/nfl_concussion.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" title="Number of NFL Concussions by Year" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <p>The image shows the number of concussions per year, including preseason and regular season.</p> <p>Today the NFL has 3 main types of fouls:</p> <ul> <li><b>Technical fouls:</b> Related to positioning, or illegal formation.</li> <li><b>Personal fouls:</b> Player behavior, illegal tackles (defensive play to try to take the ball and/or bring down the attacker) and dangerous actions.</li> <li><b>Procedural fouls:</b> False start (leaving before the ball), offside (being ahead of the ball line).</li> </ul> <p>Each type of these fouls has its specific markings and penalties:</p> <ul> <li> <b>Holding:</b> One of the most common infractions. It occurs when a player illegally holds an opponent to prevent their advance.<br/> <b>Penalty:</b> Loss of 10 yards for the offending team. </li> <br/> <li> <b>False start (illegal movement before the snap):</b> Occurs when an offensive player moves before the play begins, without the snap having been executed.<br/> <b>Penalty:</b> Loss of 5 yards. </li> <br/> <li> <b>Offside (across the line before the snap):</b> Happens when a defensive player crosses the line of scrimmage (the line that determines where the ball starts in the play) before the play begins.<br/> <b>Penalty:</b> Loss of 5 yards. </li> <br/> <li> <b>Pass interference (interference with the pass):</b> A foul committed when a player illegally prevents an opponent from completing or intercepting a pass.<br/> <b>Penalty:</b> Advance to the point where the foul occurred. </li> <br/> <li> <b>Roughing the passer (aggression against the quarterback):</b> Occurs when a defensive player hits the quarterback after throwing the ball in an unnecessary or dangerous manner.<br/> <b>Penalty:</b> 15-yard advance and automatic first down. </li> <br/> <li> <b>Targeting (targeting the head or neck):</b> One of the most serious infractions, happens when a player uses the helmet to hit the opponent's head or neck.<br/> <b>Penalty:</b> 15-yard advance and ejection of the offending player. </li> </ul> <p>Not all fouls will result in loss of yards, they can result in nullification/replay of the play, automatic first downs. Roughing the Passer and Targeting fouls are considered serious, and in addition to penalizing, they are reviewed by the league. These fouls have become much stricter, due to injuries and protection of the Quarterback (the passer, and generally, the team’s main player).</p> <p>A difference compared to other sports is how foul dynamics work: The team that suffered the foul chooses to accept or reject the foul. Let’s imagine the following scenario:</p> <p>Team A is on third down (third attempt to advance out of four total), needing 4 yards to achieve the necessary 10. The play begins and they manage to score a touchdown from that play, but there was a false start foul by team B. Team A has two options:</p> <p>Option A: Accept the foul. Since they accepted the foul, the penalty is applied relative to the line of scrimmage. Since they needed 4 yards for the first down and false start equals 5 yards, they automatically get the first down.</p> <p>Option B: Reject the foul. If they reject the foul, what counts is the play that occurred as a result, regardless of whether team A advanced or not. In this case, if they reject it, the score that counts is the touchdown, since that was the result of the play.</p> <p>Unlike tactical fouls made in football and basketball, American football does not have this type of foul, because of the nature of the sport; a more static and less fluid and continuous sport like football and basketball. However, fouls can cause psychological impacts on players and affect their performance on the field.</p> <p>NFL fouls were much less restrictive than they are today. As it was a sport with less equipment, fouls were much more violent than they are today, and this made the image that was propagated of the sport be that of a brutal and violent sport. Between 2015-2024, only 3 seasons have less than 200 injuries and concussions, including Preseason and Regular Season (2020, 2021 and 2024). The NFL today is protecting its players and athletes more, so that more people with college dreams and adults can play without having to worry about a permanent injury in the future, and so that spectators can be captivated, not by violence, but by the beauty of the sport.</p> <h2><b>FOOTBALL</b></h2> <p>In modern football, the line between a punishable infraction and a strategic play is becoming increasingly thin. Data and tactical analyses from different teams [Manchester City and the Art of the Tactical Foul] show that committing fouls is no longer necessarily a disadvantage. On the contrary, in many contexts, the calculated breaking of rules has become a valuable tool for controlling the game.</p> <p>A look at the Premier League shows exactly this: in recent years, there is no clear correlation between the number of fouls committed or suffered by a team and their success in the league table. The key, therefore, is not in quantity, but in the quality and context of each foul. <a href="https://www.premierleague.com/en/news/4187343">Arsenal is an emblematic case: frequently one of the teams that suffers the most fouls in the English Championship</a>, the London team has transformed this statistic into a weapon. With the expertise of set-piece coach Nico Jover, the team has become one of the most dangerous in the world in free kick situations, converting these interruptions into concrete goal opportunities.</p> <p>But this is far from unanimous, the golden rule, as midfielder Jack Grealish highlighted in an <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=EX_2r9-bAP0">interview</a>, is location. “If you suffer a foul here (in the central third of the opponent’s field), that’s fine, because it can be useful for the team, but if we’re in our own field, you want to try to stay on your feet”, explained the player. It is this logic that feeds the famous “tactical foul”, a play increasingly present in high-level football.</p> <p>Teams that abuse counter-attacks are constant targets of these strategic interruptions before midfield. The intention is clear: to break the offensive rhythm and prevent the construction of dangerous plays. <a href="https://blogarchive.statsbomb.com/articles/soccer/decision-making-and-expected-value/">Studies</a> further reinforce the advantage of committing fouls far from “danger zones” which, in most cases, are close to the final third of the field. Thus, the “faster” the foul is committed in counter-attack situations (where progress is made quickly on the field), the better.</p> <p>This dynamic creates a paradox within the four lines. The foul, which by definition punishes attitudes prohibited by the game, becomes a strategic component incorporated into the game. The result can be a “choppy match”, with frequent interruptions that benefit specific teams to the detriment of fluidity and spectacle. For players, the repetition of fouls also shapes perceptions. An athlete constantly interrupted may be unfairly labeled as a “diver”, when, in fact, their quality in retaining the ball and attracting marking makes them a frequent target.</p> <p>It is noted then that football becomes increasingly complex, where each foul is also a control tool, a defensive weapon and, for prepared teams, the starting point for a deadly attack. In the end, the limit of the rule becomes just the starting point for strategy.</p> <h2><b>CONCLUSION</b></h2> <p>In summary, the comparative analysis of fouls in the NBA, NFL and football reveals that, far beyond mere rule violations, they are strategic elements deeply integrated into each sport’s identity. In basketball and football, “more fluid” sports, fouls shape the pace and outcome of matches, being used in a calculated way in tactics such as the “tactical foul” or even “Hack-a-Shaq”. In the NFL, penalties have evolved to prioritize athlete safety, creating a complex system of choices that can alter the course of a match.</p> <p>Thus, it is perceived that foul rules transcend their original punitive function. They have become dynamic tools that teams master to gain competitive advantage. Whether to control the pace, exploit an opponent’s weakness or protect players, the strategic management of fouls is a reflection of the tactical sophistication and constant evolution that define high-performance sport today.</p>]]></content><author><name>Ace Laboratory Team - Gabriel Madruga, Antonio Magalhães e Miguel Angelo</name></author><category term="Sports;"/><category term="Analysis"/><category term="Basketball;"/><category term="NFL;"/><category term="Football;"/><category term="Analysis;"/><category term="Strategy"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A comparative analysis of fouls in the NBA, NFL and football, exploring how they evolved from simple rule violations to essential strategic tools]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Chelsea vs PSG: Blues Stun French Giants to Claim Club World Cup Crown</title><link href="https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2025/chelsea_psg_en/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Chelsea vs PSG: Blues Stun French Giants to Claim Club World Cup Crown"/><published>2025-07-14T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-07-14T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2025/chelsea_psg_en</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2025/chelsea_psg_en/"><![CDATA[<hr/> <p align="justify"> Se quiser ler este texto em português, <a href="https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2000/chelsea_psg_pt/"> clique aqui.</a> </p> <h2> <b> Introduction </b></h2> <div style="text-align: justify"> In the grand final of the first-ever FIFA Club World Cup under the new format, UEFA Champions League holders Paris Saint-Germain faced off against Chelsea, winners of the UEFA Conference League, in a showdown between two European powerhouses—both boasting impressive campaigns throughout the tournament. <br/><br/> Paris Saint-Germain arrived in the final with dominant numbers: five wins in six matches, including three emphatic 4–0 victories, showcasing the French side's formidable attacking prowess. Their only defeat came at the hands of Brazilian side Botafogo in the group stage. Even so, PSG's recent form in knockout games had been nothing short of extraordinary: in their last five elimination matches across all competitions, they secured five wins with a combined score of 18–0—a stat that speaks volumes. <br/><br/> Chelsea, on the other hand, also notched up five victories with just one loss, which also came against a Brazilian team—Flamengo. While their attack proved effective, the English side showed signs of defensive fragility, conceding five goals during the tournament—four more than PSG, who allowed only one. <br/><br/> According to projections from Opta Analyst, the French side entered the final as clear favorites, with a 64.4% chance of winning the world title compared to Chelsea's 35.6%. The match also made history as the first-ever final of a major men's football competition between clubs from England and France—an unprecedented European classic at the pinnacle of the sport. <br/><br/> Chelsea made a few changes to the side that faced Fluminense in the semifinals. The team lined up in a 4-2-3-1 formation, with Reece James starting in place of Nkunku, while Colwill returned to the lineup after serving a suspension. <br/><br/> Paris Saint-Germain, on the other hand, stuck with their trusted 4-3-3 formation, fielding the same starting eleven that delivered a dominant 4–0 victory over Real Madrid. <br/><br/> <h3> <b> Match Summary </b></h3> As expected from a final of this magnitude, the match kicked off at a frenetic pace. In the opening 10 minutes, Chelsea came out aggressively, catching PSG off guard with high pressure and intensity. During that stretch, the English side registered two shots, one of them a dangerous effort from Cole Palmer. That attempt had an expected goals (xG) value of 0.12, according to FotMob—a stat that estimates the likelihood of a goal based on the quality of the shot. <br/><br/> Palmer would return to the spotlight in the 22nd minute, this time finding the back of the net with a stunning goal. Remarkably, the xG for the shot was just 0.09, highlighting the difficulty of the finish and underlining the quality of the strike. <br/><br/> The young forward wasn't done. Cole Palmer, in inspired form, struck again in the 30th minute, doubling his tally and flipping the momentum of the match. With PSG initially seen as the heavy favorites, the tide had clearly turned. Within just 30 minutes, Palmer had taken three shots and scored two goals—a clinical performance on the biggest stage. <br/><br/> But Chelsea's dominance didn't stop there. In the 43rd minute, Brazilian forward João Pedro added a third, finishing a delicate chip over the goalkeeper after a perfectly timed assist from Cole Palmer. The strike had an xG on target (xGOT) value of 0.82—an advanced metric that goes beyond xG by evaluating the quality of the shot after it's been taken. The original xG for the chance was 0.49, making the leap in xGOT a testament to João Pedro's exceptional finish. <br/><br/> Despite trailing 3–0 at halftime, PSG actually dominated possession, holding 70% of the ball and completing an impressive 345 passes with 91% accuracy. Chelsea, by contrast, completed just 126 passes at a 79% rate. Yet, while the French side controlled the tempo, they struggled to create danger, managing only two shots—both saved by Robert Sánchez. Chelsea, meanwhile, thrived in transitional moments, recording six shots, three of which were on target—and all three ended up in the net. <br/><br/> The second half began with Chelsea not registering a single shot in the first 15 minutes, while the French side managed four attempts—three of them on target. A standout moment came in the 52nd minute, when Ousmane Dembélé took a shot from close range with an xG of 0.25. However, Chelsea goalkeeper Robert Sánchez, one of the match's standout performers, made a brilliant save to preserve the clean sheet. <br/><br/> In the 67th minute, João Pedro was subbed off for Liam Delap, who nearly made an immediate impact. Just one minute after coming on, he unleashed a powerful strike from long distance—an extremely difficult chance, with an xG of just 0.05 and an xGOT of 0.28. The shot was saved by Italian goalkeeper Gianluigi Donnarumma. <br/><br/> Later, in the 80th minute, Delap had an unbelievable opportunity to seal the game. Chelsea goalkeeper Robert Sánchez launched a long ball over the top, setting up Delap in a one-on-one situation with only the goalkeeper to beat. The chance had an expected goals value of 0.63. However, a poor finish from the young striker, combined with Donnarumma's excellent positioning, kept the scoreline at 3–0. <br/><br/> The match featured several heated moments between players from both sides. Tensions flared as early as the first half, notably between Fabián Ruiz and Cole Palmer. One of the most contentious matchups was between Chelsea left-back Marc Cucurella and PSG midfielder João Neves. In one incident, Neves was caught pulling Cucurella's hair—a gesture deemed violent conduct by the referee, who issued a straight red card to the Portuguese midfielder in the 85th minute. <br/><br/> PSG once again dominated possession in the second half, though slightly less than in the first. They controlled 62% of the ball and showed marked improvement in their attacking play, recording three times as many shots as they had in the first 45 minutes. Despite this surge, PSG failed to find the net, with all four of their shots on target saved by the outstanding Robert Sánchez. <br/><br/> The match ended in a stunning 3–0 win for Chelsea—an unexpected result considering their lower possession (34%) and significantly fewer completed passes (243 compared to PSG's 544). Despite seeing less of the ball, Chelsea proved more clinical in both attack and defense. <br/><br/> Chelsea goalkeeper Robert Sánchez was instrumental in the victory, saving all six of PSG's shots on target and providing security and confidence for his team throughout the match. <br/><br/> The clear man of the match was Cole Palmer. The midfielder was directly involved in all three of Chelsea's goals—scoring twice and assisting once. He completed 50% of his shots (2 on target from 4 attempts), had 48 touches, and lost the ball just once—highlighting his impeccable ball control. Palmer also led his team in successful dribbles, shots, and key passes, cementing his status as the key figure in Chelsea's triumph. <br/><br/> On PSG's side, João Neves stood out despite being sent off. The Portuguese midfielder completed 39 of 40 passes, won 12 of 15 ground duels, and led all players in defensive actions (tied with Gusto and Beraldo) and tackles. <br/><br/> <h3> <b> Tactical Analysis </b></h3> Although Chelsea began the match with high pressing, PSG's pressure throughout the game was relentless. The Parisian side forced 16 clearances from Chelsea, who cleverly relied on long balls to escape the pressure. This strategy paid off, as both of Chelsea's opening goals stemmed from direct long passes. <br/><br/> The first goal came from a long kick by goalkeeper Robert Sánchez—under pressure from Dembélé—finding Gusto on the right, who then assisted Palmer. The second goal followed a similar pattern, with center-back Colwill delivering a long ball to Palmer, who scored again. <br/><br/> The intensity of PSG's press is clearly visible in the PPDA (Passes Per Defensive Action) zone map. In this kind of visualization, the redder the zone, the higher the defensive pressure; the bluer, the lower. <br/><br/> <div class="row"> <div class="col-sm-10 offset-sm-1 mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2025-06-26-post_world_cup/final/ppda.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" title="PSG's PPDA by zone" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <center>PSG's PPDA by zone against Chelsea. <br/><br/></center> The image clearly shows that in three-quarters of the pitch, PSG allowed Chelsea very few passes before applying defensive pressure—a testament to how suffocating their pressing structure was. <br/><br/> With the ball, PSG displayed intriguing tactical variations. In buildup play, the center-backs were consistently supported by Vitinha, who led the match in touches (115) and line breaks completed (27). The midfielder completed 91 of the French team's 544 accurate passes, accounting for approximately 16.7% of the total—a clear indication of his influence on the game. This impact is further highlighted by the distance he covered during the match: a team-leading 11,879 meters. His mastery in controlling the pitch is evident, as shown by the heat map below. <br/><br/> <div class="row"> <div class="col-sm-10 offset-sm-1 mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2025-06-26-post_world_cup/final/mapa.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" title="Vitinha's heat map" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <center>Vitinha's heat map showing his extensive coverage and influence. <br/><br/></center> The full-backs were highly involved offensively—especially Hakimi on the right, who frequently operated as a winger. This movement often caused Doué, the original right winger, to drift into central areas. The image below illustrates this dynamic clearly. <br/><br/> <div class="row"> <div class="col-sm-10 offset-sm-1 mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2025-06-26-post_world_cup/final/campo1.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" title="Hakimi's offensive movement" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <center>Hakimi's offensive movement and Doué's central drift. <br/><br/></center> Another key tactical highlight was the role of Pedro Neto (highlighted in blue). Though a forward by trade, the Portuguese winger was essential in Chelsea's defensive scheme, frequently tracking back to contain Hakimi's overlapping runs and preventing PSG from creating numerical superiority down that flank. <br/><br/> Additionally, Chelsea's midfield showed a well-structured shape: Caicedo (central) and Reece James (right) held deeper positions, while Enzo Fernández (left) pushed higher up. The team's passing network diagram effectively illustrates this structure. <br/><br/> <div class="row"> <div class="col-sm-6 offset-sm-3 mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2025-06-26-post_world_cup/final/rede.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" title="Chelsea's passing network" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <center>Chelsea's passing network showing midfield structure. <br/><br/></center> The play below, which took place just minutes before the first goal, further highlights the positioning of the midfielders. Reece James, who typically operated as a right-back, is seen taking up a midfield role on the right side, while Enzo Fernández pushes forward, contributing more actively in the team's attacking phase. <br/><br/> <div class="row"> <div class="col-sm-10 offset-sm-1 mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2025-06-26-post_world_cup/final/campo2.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" title="Chelsea's midfield positioning" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <center>Chelsea's midfield positioning before the first goal. <br/><br/></center> <h2> <b> Conclusion </b></h2> Against all odds, Chelsea emerged as champions of the inaugural FIFA Club World Cup under the new format, defeating tournament favorites Paris Saint-Germain 3–0 in a final marked by efficiency, tactical discipline, and individual brilliance. <br/><br/> Despite entering the match with only a 35.6% chance of winning—according to Opta Analyst projections—Chelsea stunned the football world with a dominant first half, capitalizing on transitions and long passes to devastating effect. Cole Palmer's outstanding performance, with two goals and an assist, and Robert Sánchez's heroics in goal, were crucial in sealing the victory. <br/><br/> PSG, despite their strong campaign and statistical dominance in possession and passing, couldn't break through Chelsea's resilient defense. The Parisians will be left to reflect on missed chances and a red card that sealed their fate. <br/><br/> Chelsea's unexpected triumph reinforces the unpredictability of football and highlights the importance of strategy, efficiency, and seizing key moments. In this historic first edition of the revamped Club World Cup, the Blues stand alone at the top of the world. <br/><br/> </div>]]></content><author><name>Ace Laboratory Team - Brenno Santos, Antonio Magalhães</name></author><category term="Football;"/><category term="Analysis"/><category term="Football;"/><category term="Analysis;"/><category term="Club"/><category term="World"/><category term="Cup"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A tactical analysis of the historic Club World Cup final between Chelsea and Paris Saint-Germain, featuring an unexpected English triumph and tactical masterclass]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Fluminense vs Chelsea: Brazilian Underdogs’ Fairytale Run Ends in Semifinal</title><link href="https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2025/flu_chelsea_en/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Fluminense vs Chelsea: Brazilian Underdogs’ Fairytale Run Ends in Semifinal"/><published>2025-07-12T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-07-12T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2025/flu_chelsea_en</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2025/flu_chelsea_en/"><![CDATA[<hr/> <p align="justify"> Se quiser ler este texto em português, <a href="https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2000/flu_chelsea_pt/"> clique aqui.</a> </p> <h2> <b> Introduction </b></h2> <div style="text-align: justify"> Brazil's hopeful in the competition, Fluminense, keeps surprising everyone. After overcoming Inter Milan in the round of 16 with just a 15.4% chance of advancing, and then eliminating Al Hilal in the quarterfinals despite only a 40.2% probability, the Rio de Janeiro club has embraced the role of underdog — and their semifinal clash with powerhouse Chelsea was no exception. <br/><br/> According to Opta's supercomputer, Chelsea had an 81.3% chance of reaching the final, making the English side the overwhelming favorite. Still, Fluminense enters the semifinal unbeaten, with three wins and two draws, consistently defying expectations. <br/><br/> For this crucial match, Fluminense lines up in a 3-5-2 formation but will be without two key players due to suspension: center-back Freytes, a cornerstone of their defense, and midfielder Martinelli, who scored the opening goal against Al Hilal. Their replacements are center-back Thiago Santos and holding midfielder Hércules, who has scored twice in the last two games and steps in for Martinelli. <br/><br/> Chelsea, meanwhile, starts in a 4-2-3-1 setup. The main change is up front, where young striker Delap makes way for newly signed Brazilian forward João Pedro, who is still adjusting to the team. Another notable development is the return of elite midfielder Moisés Caicedo, back from suspension after missing the match against Palmeiras. <br/><br/> Also worth mentioning is the form of right winger Pedro Neto, who has played in four of Chelsea's five matches so far, scoring three goals and standing out as one of the team's top performers in this edition of the FIFA Club World Cup. <br/><br/> <h3> <b> Match Summary </b></h3> The opening 45 minutes were packed with intensity, marked by speed, emotion, and high stakes. Early on, former Fluminense striker João Pedro — now wearing Chelsea blue — opened the scoring with a stunning long-range strike. Remarkably, the shot had an expected goals (xG) value of just 0.04, underscoring its brilliance. <br/><br/> The first half featured 10 total shots: seven by Chelsea and three by Fluminense. One of the most dangerous moments came in the 26th minute, when Hércules found himself one-on-one with the goalkeeper. His shot, with a high xG of 0.39, was miraculously cleared off the line by left-back Marc Cucurella, in what proved to be a game-saving intervention. <br/><br/> Controversy flared when Fluminense was initially awarded a penalty for a handball by defender Chalobah. However, after a review, the referee overturned the call, ruling that the arm movement was natural. <br/><br/> Chelsea dominated the attacking momentum in the second half, especially in the opening 20 minutes, during which they held 68% possession. Although Fluminense gradually regained ground, the half ended with possession nearly even. Chelsea recorded 10 shots in the second half, while Fluminense managed 9 — four of which came during stoppage time, reflecting the English side's control, particularly early on. <br/><br/> The match concluded with a fairly balanced possession stat: 54% for Chelsea and 46% for Fluminense. The Brazilian side registered 12 total shots but struggled with efficiency, hitting the target only 3 times — a conversion rate of just 25%. Chelsea, on the other hand, demonstrated superior control throughout both halves, finishing with 17 shots and consistent dominance in possession and attacking play. <br/><br/> A standout performance came from Chelsea forward João Pedro, who — in a poetic twist — scored both goals against his former club. He was ruthlessly efficient, converting both of his two shots into goals. <br/><br/> An intriguing individual battle unfolded on the flank between Chelsea winger Pedro Neto and Fluminense right-back Guga. The Portuguese forward came out on top, completing 4 of 6 dribble attempts and winning 5 of 8 duels. Guga, by comparison, won only 3 of his contests. <br/><br/> <h3> <b> Tactical Analysis </b></h3> Fluminense repeated the formation used against Inter Milan and Al Hilal (3-5-2) and adopted a similar strategy: defending in a low block, without applying much high pressure, and looking to break forward in transition. Chelsea, on the other hand, took the opposite approach — pressing high in the attacking third and successfully winning the ball in dangerous areas, as seen in the build-up to their opening goal. <br/><br/> PPDA (Passes Allowed Per Defensive Action) maps clearly illustrate this contrast in approach. They show how Chelsea applied intense pressure in advanced zones, while Fluminense remained compact and deeper. On these maps, the redder a zone, the higher the pressure; the bluer, the lower. <br/><br/> <div class="row"> <div class="col-sm-10 offset-sm-1 mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2025-06-26-post_world_cup/semi/ppda_flu_chelsea.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" title="Comparação PPDA entre equipes" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <center>PPDA comparison showing defensive pressure zones for both teams. <br/><br/></center> At the 54-minute mark, with the score at 1–0, Fluminense coach Renato Gaúcho made a key tactical change. He replaced center-back Thiago Santos with winger Keno and switched to a 4-3-3 formation. The new front line featured Arias on the right, Cano through the middle, and Keno on the left. <br/><br/> In attack, Fluminense concentrated their efforts down the right flank, from where they delivered nine crosses — primarily through Guga and, later, Soteldo, who came on in the second half. Chelsea, meanwhile, focused more of their buildup down the left side, with Pedro Neto standing out as the team's most active crosser. <br/><br/> Chelsea's buildup play stood out for its structure and tactical variety. Left-back Cucurella dropped deeper to form a back three with the center-backs, while right-back Gusto pushed high up the pitch like a winger. This movement allowed Nkunku — nominally a forward — to shift centrally and join the midfield. <br/><br/> Nkunku thus formed a diamond in midfield alongside Enzo Fernández, Caicedo, and Palmer, with Caicedo as the deepest, Palmer in the advanced role, and Nkunku supporting both. On the left, Pedro Neto mirrored Gusto's wide role, while João Pedro stayed central as the striker. The image below helps illustrate this attacking dynamic. <br/><br/> <div class="row"> <div class="col-sm-10 offset-sm-1 mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2025-06-26-post_world_cup/semi/dynamic.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" title="Chelsea's attacking formation" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <center>Chelsea's attacking formation and Fluminense's defensive matchups. <br/><br/></center> This image also highlights some of Fluminense's individual defensive matchups in midfield. Nonato was tasked with tracking Caicedo, Hércules marked Enzo Fernández, and Bernal was responsible for Cole Palmer. These man-marking responsibilities are indicated by arrows in the image. <br/><br/> <h2> <b> Conclusion </b></h2> Despite their spirited performance, Fluminense's fairytale run in the FIFA Club World Cup came to an end. Chelsea, the favorites with an 81.3% chance of reaching the final according to Opta, ultimately lived up to expectations — advancing to the final, where they will face Paris Saint-Germain. <br/><br/> In a match filled with tactical battles and high-level execution, Chelsea's clinical edge made the difference. João Pedro, who began his career at Fluminense, played the role of heartbreaker by scoring both goals against his former club — a poetic twist that sealed the London side's path to the final. <br/><br/> Even in defeat, Fluminense can hold their heads high. After eliminating giants like Inter Milan and Al Hilal, the Brazilian side proved they belong on the world stage. With three wins, two draws, and just one loss — against one of the strongest squads in Europe — the underdog campaign of Fluminense will be remembered as one of the most surprising and admirable stories of the tournament. <br/><br/> </div>]]></content><author><name>Ace Laboratory Team - Brenno Santos, Antonio Magalhães</name></author><category term="Football;"/><category term="Analysis"/><category term="Football;"/><category term="Analysis;"/><category term="Club"/><category term="World"/><category term="Cup"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A tactical analysis of the FIFA Club World Cup semifinal between Fluminense and Chelsea, featuring the end of a remarkable underdog story]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Real Madrid vs PSG: French Dominance Secures Club World Cup Final Spot</title><link href="https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2025/real_psg_en/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Real Madrid vs PSG: French Dominance Secures Club World Cup Final Spot"/><published>2025-07-12T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-07-12T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2025/real_psg_en</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2025/real_psg_en/"><![CDATA[<hr/> <p align="justify"> Se quiser ler este texto em português, <a href="https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2000/real_psg_pt/"> clique aqui.</a> </p> <h2> <b> Introduction </b></h2> <div style="text-align: justify"> Real Madrid and Paris Saint-Germain played the match that defined the last finalist of the FIFA Club World Cup, and the reigning UEFA Champions League champion (and heavy favorite for today's game) emerged victorious with a 4-0 scoreline. The French team led by Luis Enrique once again proved to be the main European force and continues on the path towards the world championship. <br/><br/> Real Madrid came in a 4-3-2-1 formation (the same used against Borussia Dortmund), previously utilized by Xabi Alonso. In their lineup, the Spanish team combined young talents like García and Asencio with their more renowned players like Valverde and Vinicius Junior, a decision made mainly due to the high number of absences (Huijsen suspended; Endrick, Alaba and Mendy injured). <br/><br/> For their part, Paris Saint-Germain also repeated their 4-3-3 used against Bayern, with few direct substitutions from the last match; With Pacho suspended, Luis Enrique opted for Beraldo, and also brought back the attacking trio Kvaratskhelia, Dembélé and Barcola. Since all the team's players have good game awareness and can perform different functions, the coach can use his tactics with almost any combination of athletes. <br/><br/> <h3> <b> Match Summary </b></h3> Given the history, many analysts and predictions imagined a balanced game between the two teams. Opta's supercomputer, in its simulations, resulted in 47.4% chances of victory for the French team, and 27.3% for the Spanish team. However, these predictions and estimates fell apart very early; at 6 minutes of play, Fabián Ruiz opened the scoring for Paris Saint-Germain, and at 9 minutes, Dembélé changed the score again, opening 2-0 in less than 10 minutes. <br/><br/> PSG's aggressive DNA made the French team have 77% possession in the first half, suffocating Real Madrid, so the third goal seemed a matter of time, at 24 minutes Fabian Ruiz extended the score again. The Spanish team, nullified by Paris Saint-Germain, exchanged only 120 passes in the first half, against 402 from the French team. The ability to force their opponent's error is one of Luis Enrique's weapons (so much so that the first two goals come from Real Madrid's defensive errors), and this allows the Parisian midfield to play with freedom and reign over their opponents. <br/><br/> In the second half, the French team was slightly less dominant than in the first; PSG slowed down a bit (already concerned about the players' conditioning in a possible final), but without losing their defensive and offensive superiority, winning possession 59% to 41% and their duels 53% to 47%. This reduction in the pace of play allowed Real Madrid to propose a bit more and risk offensive plays in greater quantity. <br/><br/> Despite this, at 87 minutes, with Gonçalo Ramos coming off the bench in place of Dembélé (change made at 59 minutes of play), closed the account for the Paris team, scoring another goal and leaving the final score at 4-0. Even having more actions in the second half, the Spanish team could not capitalize on their chances in offensive plays on Donnarumma's goal, and ended the game without a goal. <br/><br/> This game shows a lot how the French team has adopted their coach's ideals and manages to apply them against any team; their aggressiveness, pressure and intensity consolidate them more and more as the main force in football, the Parisian team's dream for the last decades. The final against Chelsea could transform this dream of players, coaching staff, and most importantly: the fan's dream, into reality. <br/><br/> If on one hand we had a great offensive performance, we also had a great defensive performance by Paris Saint-Germain. Defensively, they had an 85% tackle rate (13) and a total of 57 ball recoveries, something that shows the great resilience of their players, led by Marquinhos, the team's captain. <br/><br/> <h3> <b> Tactical Analysis </b></h3> PSG demonstrated absolute tactical superiority, controlling all aspects of the game from the start. The French team's 4-3-3 formation allowed for high and constant pressure, suffocating Real Madrid and preventing the Spanish team from establishing their game. <br/><br/> PSG's ability to force defensive errors was fundamental to the result. The first two goals came from Real Madrid errors, demonstrating the effectiveness of French pressure and the defensive fragility of the Spanish team without some of their starters. <br/><br/> Real Madrid, despite trying to reorganize in the second half, could not overcome PSG's technical and physical superiority. The absence of important players like Endrick, Alaba and Mendy was felt, especially in build-up play and defense. <br/><br/> PSG's tactical flexibility, with players capable of performing multiple functions, allowed Luis Enrique to maintain the intensity and quality of the game even with substitutions. <br/><br/> <h2> <b> Conclusion </b></h2> Luis Enrique's squad, which once again lived up to the European champion title by dispatching the Merengue team without much difficulty, now faces Chelsea in the Club World Cup final. Although many believe the French team is the clear favorite for the title, Enzo Maresca's team also aims to take the trophy to London and promises to give PSG a hard time. <br/><br/> Finally, we can expect an exciting final game in this edition of the Club World Cup. Taking into account the teams' track record in the competition, it can be said that the chance of seeing many goals in this match is high. It remains to be seen whether the English squad, which has been strengthening in recent weeks, will be able to stop this Parisian locomotive that has been running over practically everyone who crosses its path for months. <br/><br/> </div>]]></content><author><name>Ace Laboratory Team - Gabriel Madruga, Miguel Angelo</name></author><category term="Football;"/><category term="Analysis"/><category term="Football;"/><category term="Analysis;"/><category term="Club"/><category term="World"/><category term="Cup"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A tactical analysis of the Club World Cup semifinal between Real Madrid and Paris Saint-Germain, featuring absolute French dominance]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Fluminense vs Al Hilal: Brazilian Resilience Meets Saudi Power in Quarterfinal Showdown</title><link href="https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2025/alhilal_flu_en/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Fluminense vs Al Hilal: Brazilian Resilience Meets Saudi Power in Quarterfinal Showdown"/><published>2025-07-07T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-07-07T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2025/alhilal_flu_en</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2025/alhilal_flu_en/"><![CDATA[<hr/> <p align="justify"> Se quiser ler este texto em português, <a href="https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2000/alhilal_flu_pt/"> clique aqui.</a> </p> <h2> <b> Introduction </b></h2> <div style="text-align: justify"> Fluminense and Al Hilal faced off in the quarterfinals of the FIFA Club World Cup in a highly anticipated matchup. Both teams reached this stage by overcoming heavyweight opponents in the Round of 16 — defying expectations. The Brazilian side pulled off a major upset by eliminating Inter Milan, runners-up of the 2024/25 UEFA Champions League, while the Saudi club knocked out the mighty Manchester City. <br/><br/> Still, according to Opta Analyst projections, Al Hilal were the favorites to reach the semifinals, with a 59.8% chance of advancing. <br/><br/> The starting lineups reflected each team's strategic intentions. Fluminense lined up in a 3-5-2, with Cano and Jhon Arias forming the attacking duo. The only change from the side that beat Inter was the inclusion of left-back Fuentes, replacing the suspended Renê. Meanwhile, Al Hilal fielded the same XI that started against City, but this time arranged in a 5-3-2 formation — reminiscent of the tactical setup Simone Inzaghi used at Inter Milan, his previous club. <br/><br/> <h3> <b> Match Summary </b></h3> The first half was tightly contested and offered few clear chances. Al Hilal had 52% possession compared to Fluminense's 48%, and both sides registered three shots each, with only one on target for either team. The Brazilian side opened the scoring through a beautiful strike from Martinelli, capitalizing on a poorly cleared ball by João Cancelo. Al Hilal's best chance came from a set piece, as Koulibaly's header forced an excellent save from Fábio, preserving the 1-0 lead. <br/><br/> The game was heavily concentrated in midfield, with 56% of all passes occurring in the central third. Al Hilal had the edge in duels, winning 61% of them. On the negative side, Arias had a quiet first half — losing 11 of his 12 duels and giving the ball away 11 times in 29 possessions. The strikers were largely uninvolved: Marcos Leonardo and Cano had only 12 and 10 touches, respectively — only slightly more than goalkeeper Fábio, who had 8. <br/><br/> Defensively, left wing-back Al-Harbi stood out for Al Hilal, leading the first half in tackles and interceptions. <br/><br/> In the second half, Al Hilal pressed higher up the pitch and found the equalizer early. After another set piece and a Koulibaly header, the ball fell to Marcos Leonardo, who slotted it home. Despite the goal, the Saudi team continued pushing forward but struggled to break down Fluminense's compact defense. Al Hilal took 12 shots in the second half — four times more than in the first — but only three hit the target. <br/><br/> They finished the half with 65% possession and earned 10 corner kicks, compared to just one for Fluminense. Still, the Brazilian side proved more dangerous. One of their two shots on target in the second half found the back of the net — Hércules scored to restore the lead. Fluminense had another golden opportunity after a poor pass by Renan Lodi left Cano one-on-one with goalkeeper Bounou, but the Al Hilal keeper came out on top. <br/><br/> In the closing minutes, Al Hilal pushed for an equalizer, bringing on striker Hamdallah in place of midfielder Kanno. However, they couldn't find the breakthrough, and Fluminense secured a spot in the semifinals. <br/><br/> Defensively, Fluminense put in a rock-solid performance. Center-back Ignácio was the standout, leading the game in defensive actions (16), clearances (9), and blocked shots (3). Right-back Samuel Xavier also impressed — he led the match in interceptions (3) and assisted the game-winning goal. <br/><br/> Despite the loss, Koulibaly had an excellent game for Al Hilal. The defender won 10 of his 11 duels, provided the assist for their goal, and led the match in tackles with 5. <br/><br/> <h3> <b> Tactical Analysis </b></h3> When Fluminense had possession, their buildup started with the three center-backs, while wing-backs Samuel Xavier and Fuentes pushed high to align with the forward pair in the central channel. Meanwhile, Al Hilal, in their defensive phase, avoided high pressing and maintained five players in their back line, with their wing-backs closely marking Fluminense's wide players. The image below helps illustrate this tactical structure. <br/><br/> <div class="row"> <div class="col-sm-10 offset-sm-1 mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2025-06-26-post_world_cup/quartas/alhilalflu1.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" title="Fluminense's attacking formation" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <center>Fluminense's attacking formation and movement patterns. <br/><br/></center> Similarly, when Al Hilal had the ball, they also relied on a back three for their buildup, pushing their wing-backs high up the pitch — a strategy quite similar to Fluminense's. However, the Brazilian side defended differently. Left midfielder Nonato joined Cano and Arias to form a front line of three, while Bernal and Martinelli (replaced by Hércules in the second half) sat deeper in midfield. Additionally, Fluminense's wing-backs were tasked with marking their Saudi counterparts, and the three center-backs tracked the attacking duo of Marcos Leonardo and Malcom. The following image illustrates this defensive setup. <br/><br/> <div class="row"> <div class="col-sm-10 offset-sm-1 mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2025-06-26-post_world_cup/quartas/alhilalflu2.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" title="Al Hilal's attacking formation" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <center>Al Hilal's attacking formation and Fluminense's defensive setup. <br/><br/></center> Regarding Al Hilal's buildup play, it's important to highlight Rúben Neves (marked in blue in the image), who is originally a midfielder but has been deployed as a center-back since the Round of 16 match against Manchester City. He was the team's primary distributor, leading the game in passes with 71 (92% accuracy) and topping the chart for line-breaking passes with 25 successful out of 36 attempts. <br/><br/> Neither team opted for high pressing. Instead, both chose to defend in mid-to-low blocks, aiming to reduce space and limit counterattacking opportunities. This is reflected in the PPDA (Passes Allowed per Defensive Action) zone maps for each team, which show that most of the pressing occurred in their own defensive thirds. On the map, red zones indicate higher pressing intensity, while blue zones indicate lower pressure. <br/><br/> <div class="row"> <div class="col-sm-10 offset-sm-1 mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2025-06-26-post_world_cup/quartas/alhilalflu3.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" title="PPDA comparison between teams" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <center>PPDA comparison showing defensive pressure zones for both teams. <br/><br/></center> <h2> <b> Conclusion </b></h2> Fluminense defeated Al Hilal in the first-ever meeting between the two sides, securing a place in the FIFA Club World Cup semifinals. Once again, the Brazilian team showed defensive resilience and attacking efficiency, earning another win against a favored opponent. <br/><br/> It was their second consecutive victory as underdogs — first against Inter Milan, now against Al Hilal — underscoring the strength of their collective play, tactical discipline, and competitive maturity under coach Renato Gaúcho. <br/><br/> In the semifinals, Fluminense will face Chelsea, who have already eliminated Benfica and Palmeiras. It will be another major challenge against top European competition, but based on their campaign so far, Fluminense have proven they are ready to compete with the best in the world. <br/><br/> </div>]]></content><author><name>Ace Laboratory Team - Antonio Magalhães</name></author><category term="Football;"/><category term="Analysis"/><category term="Football;"/><category term="Analysis;"/><category term="Club"/><category term="World"/><category term="Cup"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A tactical analysis of the FIFA Club World Cup quarterfinal clash between Fluminense and Al Hilal, featuring defensive masterclass and strategic battles]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Heartbreak and Heroics: Palmeiras Faces Chelsea in a Quarterfinal Thriller</title><link href="https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2025/chelsea_palmeiras_en/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Heartbreak and Heroics: Palmeiras Faces Chelsea in a Quarterfinal Thriller"/><published>2025-07-07T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-07-07T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2025/chelsea_palmeiras_en</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2025/chelsea_palmeiras_en/"><![CDATA[<hr/> <p align="justify"> Se quiser ler este texto em português, <a href="https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2000/chelsea_palmeiras_pt/"> clique aqui.</a> </p> <h2> <b> Introduction </b></h2> <div style="text-align: justify"> In the FIFA Club World Cup quarterfinals, Palmeiras and Chelsea face off to continue in the tournament. Their last meeting was in the 2021 Club World Cup final, where Chelsea won 2–1 in extra time. <br/><br/> According to Opta Analyst, Palmeiras had a low chance of winning, with a 15.4% probability of victory, 20.1% chance of a draw, and a 64.5% chance of defeat. Among the 8 teams qualified so far, Palmeiras had the lowest probability of reaching the semifinals, at just 25.50%. <br/><br/> Palmeiras lined up in a 4-2-3-1 formation, similar to the setup used in their match against Botafogo. However, in this clash against the English side, the team had two crucial absences due to suspensions: Piquerez and Gustavo Gómez, both key players who had been instrumental in Palmeiras' Club World Cup campaign. They were replaced by Vanderlan and Micael. <br/><br/> Chelsea also had a major absence in their squad — Ecuadorian midfielder Moisés Caicedo was suspended for the quarterfinals. As a result, the team started with Andrey Santos in his place. Chelsea also used a 4-2-3-1 formation, similar to the one used in their round of 16 match against Benfica, but with some changes, including fullback Reece James and midfielder Lavia. <br/><br/> <h3> <b> Match Summary </b></h3> The first half was marked by greater offensive threat from Chelsea. With 68% possession, 9 shots, and 1 goal, the English side clearly dominated the first 45 minutes. Until the 40th minute, the Brazilian team had no shots at all, highlighting their lack of offensive efficiency during that period. By halftime, Palmeiras had only two shots, with just one on target. During this half, English player Cole Palmer — who scored the goal — had more shots than the entire Palmeiras team, being a key offensive pillar for Chelsea in that stretch. <br/><br/> Palmeiras began to improve after the 30-minute mark, gradually attempting to enhance their attacking performance, which was reflected in the attacking momentum graph — previously showing near-total dominance by Chelsea. <br/><br/> In the second half, at the 53rd minute, 18-year-old Estevão scored the equalizer for Palmeiras. The second half began much more balanced, with Palmeiras having 46% possession in the first 15 minutes and two shots — equaling their total from the entire first half. <br/><br/> The final 45 minutes saw both teams score again, each adding one more goal. Possession in the second half was more balanced, with Palmeiras at 44% versus Chelsea's 56%, and a high number of total shots — 15 combined, with 5 from Palmeiras and 10 from Chelsea. <br/><br/> Despite Palmeiras managing to create a few more chances as the match went on, Chelsea had the overall better performance, securing the victory. In total, Chelsea had 19 shots, 6 of which were on target, achieving a slightly higher shot conversion rate than Palmeiras — 31.6% compared to Palmeiras' 28.6%. <br/><br/> A negative highlight for Palmeiras was Vanderlan, who, possibly feeling the pressure of replacing first-choice left-back Piquerez, had a poor performance. He completed only 63% of his passes, won just 2 out of 7 duels (28.6%), and lost possession 15 times out of 44 touches — clearly showing how much the suspended starter was missed. The image below, which shows Palmeiras' crosses, highlights the poor performance on the left flank, with none of the left-side crosses being completed. <br/><br/> <div class="row"> <div class="col-sm-10 offset-sm-1 mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2025-06-26-post_world_cup/quartas/CrossPalmeirasChelsea.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" title="Palmeiras' crosses against Chelsea" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <center>Palmeiras' crosses against Chelsea, showing poor performance on the left flank. <br/><br/></center> To compensate for the two suspended Palmeiras players, Bruno Fuchs — who had already performed well against Botafogo — played a crucial role in keeping the team in the game. He led all players in defensive actions with 18, far ahead of second-place Marc Cucurella with 8. Bruno was also the leader in clearances, interceptions, and tackles, and did not suffer a single successful dribble against him. <br/><br/> In this impressive Chelsea victory, one of the most important players was the outstanding Marc Cucurella. He had a pass accuracy of 96% and delivered an exceptional defensive performance. Notably, he was responsible for blocking all three of Palmeiras' blocked shots — showing that he excels at his duties both offensively and defensively. <br/><br/> <h3> <b> Tactical Analysis </b></h3> Chelsea's tactical approach was characterized by their ability to control possession and create attacking opportunities through structured build-up play. The English side's 4-2-3-1 formation allowed them to maintain numerical superiority in midfield while providing width through their full-backs. <br/><br/> The absence of Moisés Caicedo was well-managed by Chelsea's coaching staff, with Andrey Santos stepping in seamlessly to maintain the team's defensive balance. This adaptability showcased Chelsea's squad depth and tactical flexibility. <br/><br/> Palmeiras, despite missing key defensive players, attempted to maintain their attacking identity while adapting to Chelsea's superior technical quality. The Brazilian side's 4-2-3-1 formation was designed to provide defensive solidity while creating opportunities through quick transitions. <br/><br/> However, the absence of Piquerez and Gustavo Gómez proved crucial, particularly in defensive transitions and attacking support from the flanks. Vanderlan's struggles on the left side significantly impacted Palmeiras' ability to create width and maintain attacking momentum. <br/><br/> <h2> <b> Conclusion </b></h2> In a high-level clash marked by tactical contrasts and individual performances, Chelsea ultimately proved superior to Palmeiras, securing a deserved victory in the FIFA Club World Cup quarterfinals. Despite Palmeiras' effort to adjust and respond in the second half — particularly through the brilliance of young Estevão and the defensive leadership of Bruno Fuchs — the absence of key players like Piquerez and Gustavo Gómez left noticeable gaps in both defensive stability and offensive support. <br/><br/> Chelsea dominated the first half with possession, precision, and an organized attacking structure, driven largely by Cole Palmer and Marc Cucurella. The English side's ability to control the game through positioning, pressing, and fluid movement exposed Palmeiras' struggles to build and progress the ball. <br/><br/> While Palmeiras improved in the second half, showing more offensive intent and better balance, their overall inefficiency in the final third and individual underperformances — especially from Vanderlan — hindered a full comeback. Chelsea's depth, tactical consistency, and high execution level across all phases of play ensured their progression to the semifinals. <br/><br/> Chelsea came out on top in this match, as predicted by Opta's probabilities, and now moves forward in the tournament with a 36.25% chance of winning the championship. Their next challenge will be against Fluminense, who arrive in great form after impressive victories over Internazionale — last season's Champions League runners-up — and Al-Hilal, the undefeated champions of the 2023/2024 Saudi Pro League. <br/><br/> In summary, it was a match that showcased the importance of tactical discipline, squad depth, and composure under pressure — areas where Chelsea held the advantage and converted it into a hard-fought, yet clear, win. <br/><br/> </div>]]></content><author><name>Ace Laboratory Team - Brenno Santos</name></author><category term="Football;"/><category term="Analysis"/><category term="Football;"/><category term="Analysis;"/><category term="Club"/><category term="World"/><category term="Cup"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A tactical analysis of the FIFA Club World Cup quarterfinal clash between Palmeiras and Chelsea, featuring strategic battles and individual performances]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Real Madrid vs Borussia Dortmund: A Champions League Rematch on the World Stage</title><link href="https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2025/real_borussia_en/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Real Madrid vs Borussia Dortmund: A Champions League Rematch on the World Stage"/><published>2025-07-07T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-07-07T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2025/real_borussia_en</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2025/real_borussia_en/"><![CDATA[<hr/> <p align="justify"> If you want to read this text in Portuguese, <a href="https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2000/real_borussia_pt/"> click here.</a> </p> <h2> <b> Introduction </b></h2> <div style="text-align: justify"> The clash between Real Madrid and Borussia Dortmund marked the end of the quarterfinal stage of the FIFA Club World Cup, with the Spanish giants emerging victorious. This highly anticipated match drew extra attention, as it was a rematch of the 2023/24 UEFA Champions League final — a game Real Madrid won. Dortmund came into this fixture eager for revenge and with much to prove. <br/><br/> Real Madrid lined up in a 4-3-1-2 formation, despite missing key players such as Eduardo Camavinga and Ferland Mendy due to injury. Still, the squad showcased its impressive depth, featuring rising talents like Gonzalo, who had already made a mark in earlier Club World Cup matches, and the promising Arda Güler, a creative force steadily earning his place in Madrid's setup. <br/><br/> Borussia Dortmund, on the other hand, opted for a 3-4-1-2 formation. One of the emotional subplots was Jobe Bellingham taking the field without his brother Jude, who was suspended due to yellow card accumulation. Jobe had been performing well throughout the tournament. Up front, Serhou Guirassy, one of the competition's top scorers with three goals in four matches, carried Dortmund's hopes. Aware of the challenge, even he admitted before the game: "It's going to be a tough match." <br/><br/> According to Opta Analyst, Real Madrid entered the match with a 59.7% chance of advancing to the semifinals, while Borussia Dortmund had a 40.3% chance. These odds reflected Madrid's status as one of the tournament favorites to lift the trophy. <br/><br/> <h3> <b> Match Summary </b></h3> Before the 35-minute mark in the first half, Real Madrid's probability of advancing to the semifinals skyrocketed from 59.7% to 91.9%, thanks to two early goals from their rising stars — Gonzalo in the 10th minute and Fran García in the 20th. <br/><br/> Despite Borussia Dortmund having the edge in possession (58%) compared to Madrid's 42% in the first half, the Spanish side delivered a much more efficient and dangerous performance. They registered 8 total shots, with 4 on target, resulting in a 50% shot accuracy. After the second goal, Madrid pulled back slightly, allowing Dortmund to regain more control of the ball, but without creating significant danger. <br/><br/> In the second half, Madrid reasserted dominance, holding 57% of possession and recording 7 shots, 4 of which were on target. Despite the continued pressure, no goals came until stoppage time. Then, the game took a dramatic turn. <br/><br/> At 92 minutes, Borussia Dortmund capitalized on a defensive lapse and scored their first goal, narrowing the gap to 2–1. But Madrid responded almost immediately, with a third goal at the 94th minute, restoring their two-goal cushion. Dortmund, needing two more goals to equalize and force extra time, surged forward in desperation and won a penalty. Guirassy converted from the spot, making it 3–2 in the 98th minute — despite only 5 minutes of stoppage time being initially added. <br/><br/> The game continued for one final, dramatic opportunity. In the dying seconds, midfielder Marcel Sabitzer unleashed a powerful strike that was brilliantly saved by the Madrid goalkeeper. The shot had an xGOT (Expected Goals on Target) value of 0.70, indicating a high probability of scoring based on shot placement and trajectory — a near-equalizer denied only by a moment of goalkeeping brilliance. <br/><br/> In the end, despite Real Madrid's victory, the match was highly competitive. Madrid held 49% possession to Dortmund's 51%, and both teams produced a high volume of chances — 15 shots for Madrid, 12 for Dortmund. Madrid, however, showed superior finishing efficiency, with a 53.3% shot accuracy (8 out of 15), underlining their clinical edge in front of goal. <br/><br/> Another crucial factor in Madrid's win was their strong defensive performance. The back four combined for 16 tackles and 22 defensive actions, a testament to their resilience and discipline under pressure. <br/><br/> The undisputed standout of the match was Arda Güler, Real Madrid's brilliant 20-year-old prospect, who once again showcased why he is considered one of the most promising young talents in world football. Güler delivered a masterclass performance, registering two assists and playing a key role in orchestrating Madrid's attacking transitions. <br/><br/> Operating primarily as an advanced playmaker behind the two forwards, Arda Güler demonstrated exceptional vision, composure, and technical ability. He maintained an outstanding pass accuracy of 96%, completing nearly every pass he attempted — a remarkable feat in such a high-stakes, fast-paced match. Over the course of the game, he recorded 78 touches, a clear sign of his influence and involvement in Real Madrid's build-up play. <br/><br/> Just as impressive was his ball security. Güler lost possession only four times throughout the entire match, a testament to his intelligence on the ball and ability to navigate through pressure from the Dortmund midfield. Whether finding space between the lines, delivering sharp through balls, or contributing defensively when needed, he played with a maturity far beyond his age. <br/><br/> This performance adds to a growing list of impressive displays by Güler in the Club World Cup, further strengthening his case to become a regular starter in Carlo Ancelotti's squad. With key injuries in the team, Güler seized his opportunity and turned the spotlight onto himself — not just as a future star, but as a player ready to make a difference in the present. <br/><br/> <h3> <b> Tactical Analysis </b></h3> Real Madrid's tactical approach was characterized by their ability to adapt to the absence of key players while maintaining their attacking identity. The 4-3-1-2 formation allowed them to create numerical superiority in midfield while providing multiple attacking options through the central areas. <br/><br/> The absence of Camavinga and Mendy was well-managed through tactical adjustments and the impressive performances of their replacements. This adaptability showcased Madrid's squad depth and the quality of their youth development system. <br/><br/> Borussia Dortmund's 3-4-1-2 formation was designed to provide defensive solidity while creating attacking opportunities through the flanks and central areas. However, their inability to convert possession into clear-cut chances in the first half proved costly, despite their numerical advantage in midfield. <br/><br/> The dramatic finish highlighted both teams' fighting spirit and tactical flexibility. Dortmund's late surge demonstrated their ability to adapt under pressure, while Madrid's resilience showed their experience in managing high-stakes situations. <br/><br/> <h2> <b> Conclusion </b></h2> Real Madrid emerged victorious in a thrilling, high-scoring quarterfinal, a match that not only highlighted their resilience but also showcased the depth and brilliance of their rising stars. Despite missing key players due to injuries, the Spanish giants delivered a confident and commanding performance, proving once again why they are one of the most successful clubs in world football. <br/><br/> With that win, Real Madrid now advances to the semifinals, where they will face their most challenging opponent yet — Paris Saint-Germain, the reigning UEFA Champions League titleholders. It's a clash worthy of a final, featuring two European powerhouses filled with elite talent and global stars. <br/><br/> However, according to Opta Analyst, PSG enters the match as the favorite, with a 58.1% probability of reaching the final of the inaugural FIFA Club World Cup in its new format. Real Madrid, while not the statistical favorite in this semifinal, still carries the weight of experience, tradition, and individual brilliance — factors that often defy the odds. <br/><br/> Despite being the underdog in this particular matchup, Real Madrid holds a 24.67% chance of winning the entire tournament, according to Opta projections. This figure places them among the top contenders and reflects the competitive nature of the remaining teams. Given their form, mentality, and historical pedigree, it would be unwise to count Madrid out. <br/><br/> As they prepare for a blockbuster semifinal, Real Madrid will be banking on the momentum gained in the quarterfinals, the growth of their young stars, and the leadership of their seasoned veterans. The road ahead is difficult — but if there's one team that knows how to navigate elite competitions, it's Real Madrid! <br/><br/> </div>]]></content><author><name>Ace Laboratory Team - Brenno Santos</name></author><category term="Football;"/><category term="Analysis"/><category term="Football;"/><category term="Analysis;"/><category term="Club"/><category term="World"/><category term="Cup"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A tactical analysis of the FIFA Club World Cup quarterfinal clash between Real Madrid and Borussia Dortmund, featuring a dramatic Champions League rematch]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Palmeiras vs Botafogo: A Tactical Battle in the Club World Cup Round of 16</title><link href="https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2025/botafogo_palmeiras_en/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Palmeiras vs Botafogo: A Tactical Battle in the Club World Cup Round of 16"/><published>2025-07-02T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-07-02T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2025/botafogo_palmeiras_en</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2025/botafogo_palmeiras_en/"><![CDATA[<hr/> <p align="justify"> Se quiser ler este texto em português, <a href="https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2000/botafogo_palmeiras_pt/"> clique aqui.</a> </p> <h2> <b> Introduction </b></h2> <div style="text-align: justify"> The clash between Brazilian clubs Botafogo and Palmeiras extended their growing rivalry onto the international stage, as they met once again in the Round of 16 of the 2025 FIFA Club World Cup. The two sides previously faced off in the 2024 Copa Libertadores Round of 16 and battled for the title in the Brasileirão Série A — with Botafogo emerging victorious in both competitions. <br/><br/> In the Club World Cup group stage, Palmeiras topped Group A with one win and two draws. Botafogo finished second in Group B, recording two victories — including an impressive win over UEFA Champions League winners PSG — and one loss. <br/><br/> Despite Botafogo's recent dominance in the head-to-head record — three wins and two draws in their last five meetings — Palmeiras entered the knockout stage as slight favorites. According to Opta Analyst, Palmeiras had a 52.4% chance of winning in regular time, compared to 23.8% for Botafogo, with the probability of a draw also at 23.8%. The overall chances of advancing to the quarterfinals were more balanced: 55.6% for Palmeiras and 44.4% for Botafogo. <br/><br/> In the end, Palmeiras secured a 1–0 win in the Round of 16 match, with substitute Paulinho scoring the decisive goal in the first half of extra time. <br/><br/> Tactically, Botafogo stuck with the 4-3-3 formation that was used against PSG and Atlético de Madrid, with Danilo Barbosa stepping in for the suspended Gregore. Palmeiras deployed a 4-2-3-1 system and made several notable changes to their starting lineup. Academy product Allan started on the right wing, while rising star Estevão featured on the left. In defense, Bruno Fuchs replaced the injured Murilo, and Maurício took over for Veiga in midfield. <br/><br/> <h3> <b> Match Summary </b></h3> The first half ended with a clear offensive advantage for the São Paulo team. By the 30-minute mark, the Rio de Janeiro side had yet to attempt a single shot, while their opponents had already registered five. By halftime, the São Paulo club had taken seven shots with an expected goals (xG) value of 0.51, compared to just two shots and 0.07 xG for Botafogo. Despite this disparity, possession remained fairly balanced — 51% for Palmeiras and 49% for Botafogo. However, none of the nine total shots hit the target, highlighting the lack of efficiency from both sides in front of goal. <br/><br/> In the second half, possession remained nearly even — 52% for Botafogo and 48% for Palmeiras — but the São Paulo team continued to threaten more consistently. They registered nine shots to the opponent's two, including three on target versus just one. The xG numbers reflected this attacking edge: 0.64 to just 0.06. Goalkeeper John stood out in this period, making three crucial saves to keep Botafogo in the game. Another stat that underscored Palmeiras' dominance was corner kicks: they took 13 in regular time, compared to just two for Botafogo. <br/><br/> With the match still goalless after 90 minutes, extra time began at a high tempo. Substitutions brought new energy to the field — most notably Paulinho, who scored the decisive goal in the first half of extra time. During those 15 minutes, Palmeiras stayed on the front foot, producing two shots on target and converting one. <br/><br/> In the second half of extra time, already ahead, Palmeiras adopted a more defensive posture, particularly after replacing forward Paulinho with center-back Micael. They had only 26% possession in that stretch, focusing on protecting the lead. Meanwhile, Botafogo pushed forward aggressively. In those final 15 minutes alone, the Rio side recorded 10 shots — more than in the entire 90 minutes plus the first extra-time period combined. That final stretch generated 0.75 xG, accounting for 68.2% of their total expected goals for the entire match. <br/><br/> After 120 minutes, Palmeiras secured their place in the quarterfinals with a stronger overall performance: 19 total shots, five on target, 47% possession, and approximately 83% passing accuracy. <br/><br/> A standout performer for Palmeiras was Richard Ríos, who delivered a high-quality display over the full 120 minutes to help secure the win. He provided an assist and led his team in tackles (4), duels won (10), and distance covered (13,4 km). His performance was well-rounded, contributing both offensively and defensively, and he played a key role in the team's success. <br/><br/> The image below shows the attacking momentum of the match, highlighting Palmeiras' superiority, with most of the opportunities and greater attacking efficiency, despite the overall statistical balance in the game. It also shows Botafogo dominating the second half of extra time, with 10 attempts compared to none from the team from São Paulo. <br/><br/> <div class="row"> <div class="col-sm-10 offset-sm-1 mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2025-06-26-post_world_cup/oitavas/pressure_map.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" title="Attacking momentum of the match" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <center>Attacking momentum of the match between Palmeiras and Botafogo. <br/><br/></center> <h3> <b> Tactical Analysis </b></h3> In addition to repeating the same formation used against the European sides (PSG and Atlético de Madrid), Botafogo also stuck to the same strategy: applying pressure in their own defensive half and relying on counterattacks. <br/><br/> When in possession — and not attacking in transition — head coach Renato Paiva's approach was clear: the wingers, Artur and Savarino, moved into central areas to create space for overlapping full-backs Vitinho and Alex Telles, while Igor Jesus stayed as the central reference up front. This dynamic can be seen in the image below. <br/><br/> <div class="row"> <div class="col-sm-10 offset-sm-1 mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2025-06-26-post_world_cup/oitavas/formation2.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" title="Botafogo's tactical formation" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <center>Botafogo's tactical formation and movement patterns. <br/><br/></center> Although he had been performing well in the tournament, forward Savarino stood out for the wrong reasons in this match. He completed only 75% of his passes, lost all 5 duels he contested, and gave away possession 10 times out of 27 touches. <br/><br/> Additionally, Botafogo focused more of their attacks down the right flank. Vitinho and Artur were the players with the most passing offers, with 74 and 60 respectively. The team's passing map helps illustrate this scenario. <br/><br/> <div class="row"> <div class="col-sm-6 offset-sm-3 mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2025-06-26-post_world_cup/oitavas/passing_map_botafogo.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" title="Botafogo's passing network" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <center>Botafogo's passing network against Palmeiras. <br/><br/></center> Palmeiras set up in a 4-2-3-1 formation but employed an intelligent defensive tactic by shifting into a 5-4-1 variation, as shown in the image below. This adjustment proved highly effective against Botafogo's attack — particularly since, as mentioned earlier, the team focused heavily on attacking down the flanks. The compact defensive shape effectively neutralized those wide advances. <br/><br/> <div class="row"> <div class="col-sm-10 offset-sm-1 mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2025-06-26-post_world_cup/oitavas/formation1.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" title="Palmeiras' defensive formation" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <center>Palmeiras' defensive formation and tactical adjustments. <br/><br/></center> Palmeiras' exceptional defensive performance is evidenced by Igor Jesus' high offensive movement — 29 runs in behind — yet without any effective finishing. Palmeiras' PPDA (passes per defensive action) reflects a low-block defense, with lower values closer to the box, as shown in the image below: the more red, the lower the index (in other words, more pressure), and the more blue, the higher the index and lower the pressure. <br/><br/> <div class="row"> <div class="col-sm-10 offset-sm-1 mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2025-06-26-post_world_cup/oitavas/ppda_palmeiras.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" title="Palmeiras' PPDA by zone" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <center>Palmeiras' PPDA by zone against Botafogo. <br/><br/></center> One of the key positive defensive standouts was left-back Joaquín Piquerez, who played a vital role in executing this system. In addition to maintaining strong positioning and discipline on his side of the field, Piquerez led the team in defensive actions (10) and clearances (5), showing great awareness and composure throughout the match. His contribution was crucial in absorbing the pressure during Botafogo's most aggressive phases and helped Palmeiras maintain their structure even as the match became more intense. <br/><br/> <h2> <b> Conclusion </b></h2> The match between Palmeiras and Botafogo showcased not only the intensity of a growing rivalry but also the tactical maturity and adaptability of both teams. While Botafogo stayed true to its counterattacking identity and maintained structural consistency throughout the tournament, Palmeiras demonstrated greater flexibility — both in formation and in in-game adjustments — which ultimately made the difference. <br/><br/> Statistically and tactically, Palmeiras managed to control key areas of the pitch, especially in defense, where their shape and discipline effectively neutralized Botafogo's strengths. The transition from a 4-2-3-1 to a 5-4-1 in defensive phases proved decisive, as did individual performances like that of Joaquín Piquerez and Richard Ríos, who embodied the balance between defensive solidity and offensive support. <br/><br/> In a match defined by fine margins and intense strategic battles, Palmeiras' ability to adapt and capitalize on moments of opportunity, such as the goal in extra time, underlined the team's competitive edge — not just in terms of talent, but in execution and game management. The result was not only a deserved qualification but also a performance that reflects the evolution of Brazilian clubs on the international stage. <br/><br/> Having secured a spot in the quarterfinals, Palmeiras now faces a high-stakes encounter with Chelsea — the same opponent they battled in the 2022 Club World Cup final. The matchup not only revives recent history but also adds another chapter to Palmeiras' pursuit of the long-awaited dream of eternal glory on the world stage. <br/><br/> </div>]]></content><author><name>Ace Laboratory Team - Brenno Santos, Antonio Magalhães</name></author><category term="Football;"/><category term="Analysis"/><category term="Football;"/><category term="Analysis;"/><category term="Club"/><category term="World"/><category term="Cup"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A thrilling tactical showdown between Brazilian giants Palmeiras and Botafogo in the Club World Cup Round of 16, featuring intense extra-time drama and strategic masterclass]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Flamengo vs Bayern: An Analysis of Errors and Tactical Differences</title><link href="https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2025/flamengo_bayern_en/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Flamengo vs Bayern: An Analysis of Errors and Tactical Differences"/><published>2025-07-02T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-07-02T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2025/flamengo_bayern_en</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2025/flamengo_bayern_en/"><![CDATA[<hr/> <p align="justify"> Se quiser ler a versão em português, <a href="https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2000/flamengo_bayern_pt/"> clique aqui.</a> </p> <h2> <b> Introduction </b></h2> <div style="text-align: justify"> This past Sunday, 06/29, Flamengo and Bayern Munich faced off in a match between the cream of what South American football can offer (and possibly the best team on the continent) against a team from the highest tier of European football (which wasn't the best of the last season) in a game marked by several things, but mainly by the number of errors on the part of the Rio team that led to the Bavarian team's goals, which raises the question: were these failures just demerits of the red-and-black team? <br/><br/> <h3> <b> Match Summary </b></h3> Even before the ball rolled, there was already a debate about the lineup made by Filipe Luís, for including Arrascaeta, the team's top scorer of the season, but who doesn't usually impose as much physical vigor when marking pressure or when serving as a speed escape valve for the attack, roles that would be better performed by another athlete, such as Bruno Henrique, the striker who came on in place of the Uruguayan in the group stage match against Chelsea and changed the course of the match. However, whatever the Brazilian coach's thinking was, it was completely influenced by what happened in the early minutes of the game. <br/><br/> The pace of the game, the strategy, and the level of pressure that would be felt throughout the 90 minutes were severely influenced when at 3 minutes and 45 seconds, the Argentine goalkeeper Rossi kicked a ball at Pulgar, which ended up resulting in a corner kick (by the referee's understanding) that generated a second one, from which came the first goal of the match, an own goal. This change in the score so quickly would already be enough to change the entire match planning, but the blitz imposed by Bayern was still in full force when the French defender Upamecano came up from the German defensive line to contest a pass received by Arrascaeta, which succeeded in Harry Kane's fatal finish, extending the score. <br/><br/> After this disastrous sequence of events, the Rio team managed to have more possession and try to put their game idea into practice, leading to their first goal play, resulting from a deflected cross into the penalty area with a Gerson finish, which made the Bavarian imposition return with full force. <br/><br/> <div class="row"> <div class="col-sm-10 offset-sm-1 mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2025-06-26-post_world_cup/oitavas/fla_bayern.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" title="Momento ofensivo da partida" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <center>Offensive moment of the match between Flamengo and Bayern. <br/><br/></center> As we can observe in the attacking third actions chart, this pattern repeated itself in the interval between the third and fourth goals of the Europeans, giving the impression that the German team "took their foot off" after making the result more comfortable, leaving more possession and space for the Brazilian team to work the plays, which resulted in a second goal after the Uruguayan midfielder's cross hit Olise's open hand inside the area, generating a penalty converted with precision by Jorginho. This pattern repeated itself after this reduction in the score advantage, with the pace being imposed by Bayern and with pressure on a ball exit where Luiz Araújo tried to dribble near the defensive penalty area, turning into a precise shot from the English striker. <br/><br/> This norm in the game dynamics can help explain the fact that at the end of the match some data showed a Flamengo equivalent or superior to Bayern (such as a minimal advantage in possession, a greater number of shots, xG), although the Rio team was not very close to equalizing the score (the closest chance came from an Arrascaeta header at 6 minutes of play), the eye test points to the contrary, a Bayern that dictated the pace when the advantage decreased and that didn't take as many risks. <br/><br/> <h3> <b> Tactical Analysis </b></h3> Regarding the question of errors, forced or not, they can be contextualized, in part, by the difference in quality between the two teams in various aspects, but mainly in the effectiveness of pressure and efficiency in punishing the opposing team's errors, and one of the justifications for these issues can be, besides the quality of the players on the field, due to the history of German teams having this historical habit of pressing high, after all, gegenpressing comes from there. <br/><br/> The concept of marking by pressing in attack is not something that was created recently, but this style of football, especially in the context of German football, is attributed to German coach Ralf Rangnick, who influenced modern generations of German coaches, such as Jurgen Klopp, Thomas Tuchel, and Julian Nagelsmann. Additionally, the German league is known for the high level of athleticism imposed by the players, fundamental factors for teams like Klopp's Borussia or Hansi Flick's Bayern Munich to establish their game plans brutally, having vigor to move up the marking line, attack spaces quickly, etc. <br/><br/> This very high-pressure football, combined with the high marking line, has been in the club's DNA for a long time, and besides being very well refined by recent coaches, such as Nagelsmann and Hansi Flick, they are put into practice by Kompany, the current coach, while the ephemerality of Brazilian coaches' work combined with the lack of conviction in fixed game styles for clubs, makes it difficult for the work to be much refined here, and for there to be an exploited sequence even with coach changes. <br/><br/> <h2> <b> Conclusion </b></h2> In the end, the Brazilian team did what they could, especially given the circumstances, and lost in a dignified manner, and although they were far from making a head-to-head match, it doesn't mean that the defeat was a disgrace or something of the sort, and this defeat cannot shake the structures of both the squad and the entire football department because the season is only at its halfway point, with the most decisive matches for national competitions and the Copa Libertadores very close. <br/><br/> The match between Flamengo and Bayern demonstrated not only the technical difference between the teams, but also the importance of tactical consistency and efficient pressure in modern football. While Bayern showed its tradition of high pressure and finishing efficiency, Flamengo revealed fragilities that need to be worked on to compete at the highest international level. <br/><br/> The defeat, although heavy on the scoreboard, serves as valuable learning for the development of Brazilian football, showing that tactical evolution and methodological consistency are fundamental for success in the international scenario. <br/><br/> </div>]]></content><author><name>Ace Laboratory Team - João Victor Gadelha</name></author><category term="Football;"/><category term="Analysis"/><category term="Football;"/><category term="Analysis;"/><category term="Club"/><category term="World"/><category term="Cup"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[How Flamengo's errors and Bayern's pressure defined the result in the Club World Cup Round of 16]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Fluminense vs Inter: A Victory that Surprised Everyone</title><link href="https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2025/fluminense_inter_en/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Fluminense vs Inter: A Victory that Surprised Everyone"/><published>2025-07-02T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-07-02T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2025/fluminense_inter_en</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2025/fluminense_inter_en/"><![CDATA[<hr/> <p align="justify"> Se quiser ler este texto em português, <a href="https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2000/fluminense_inter_pt/"> clique aqui.</a> </p> <h2> <b> Introduction </b></h2> <div style="text-align: justify"> In our last post about Fluminense after the group stage, we stated: "the Flu had both defensive failures and wasted goal opportunities, which should be crucial points for improvement in the next game". In this knockout match against Inter Milan, it seems the tricolor understood the message. <br/><br/> Renato Gaúcho bet on a different formation, with a 3-5-2. In the first minute of the match, Fluminense's high pressing was already causing discomfort for goalkeeper Sommer, who shares a ball with Germán Cano. A few minutes later, after a series of passes, Fluminense overloaded Inter with four players inside the penalty area, setting up a cross for Cano, who, free, becomes lethal again and scores the first goal of the match, putting Fluminense in an excellent position. <br/><br/> <h3> <b> Match Summary </b></h3> After the goal, Fluminense didn't panic. The Italian team kept the ball at their feet, ending the first half with 66% possession, but without causing major problems for the tricolor, who intercepted their shots very well, both in defense and in goalkeeper Fábio's hands. Additionally, Renato's team was the one that came closest to the second goal still in the first half, with a wasted chance from Samuel Xavier after an impressive play by Arias. This play, along with Ignácio's disallowed goal, demonstrates that, despite having less possession, Fluminense definitely didn't back down from the game. <br/><br/> Accumulating only half the number of passes from Inter at the end of the first half (126 to 250), it was the Rio team that showed more sharpness, ending the first half with 5 shots against Inter's 5. Dimarco, who wears number 32, was responsible for three of them. See the possession from Inter's passing network: <br/><br/> <div class="row"> <div class="col-sm-6 offset-sm-3 mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2025-06-26-post_world_cup/oitavas/rede_inter.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" title="Inter's passing network" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <center>Inter Milan's passing network against Fluminense. <br/><br/></center> In the second half, Fluminense continued in this style — Renato, in fact, ended the game with a substitution to spare. Inter, however, showed they wanted the game, making changes that had an effect: from the 60th minute onwards, the team brought much danger to Fluminense, shooting an incredible 10 times. The tricolor fan certainly held their breath seeing the three great chances created by Inter, one wasted by de Vrij, another from Lautaro that stopped in Fábio, and one more from Lautaro in the same minute that hit the post. These three shots alone add up to 0.52 xG. <br/><br/> Who closed the tricolor's house was the match's star, Ignácio, who won 10 of the 15 duels he contested. This pressure suffered can be observed from Fluminense's PPDA (Passes per Defensive Action) chart: <br/><br/> <div class="row"> <div class="col-sm-10 offset-sm-1 mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2025-06-26-post_world_cup/oitavas/ppda_flu.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" title="Fluminense's PPDA" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <center>Fluminense's PPDA by zone against Inter. <br/><br/></center> <h3> <b> Tactical Analysis </b></h3> Renato Gaúcho's tactical change to 3-5-2 was fundamental for Fluminense's success. This formation allowed greater control of the midfield and better defensive coverage, especially against Inter's technical quality. <br/><br/> Fluminense's defensive system worked exceptionally well, with the three defenders providing extra security and the full-backs offering offensive width when necessary. The high pressing at the beginning of the match caught Inter by surprise and resulted in Cano's early goal. <br/><br/> Ignácio's performance was particularly notable. The player not only won most of the duels but was also crucial in defensive organization and offensive transition. His versatility allowed Fluminense to maintain tactical structure even under intense pressure from Inter in the second half. <br/><br/> <h2> <b> Conclusion </b></h2> However, qualification was destined for the Warriors team, who killed the game at Hércules' feet in stoppage time, to confirm an extremely conscious and deserved victory. <br/><br/> Fluminense demonstrated significant tactical evolution compared to previous games. The change to 3-5-2, combined with a more aggressive approach at the beginning of the match, was fundamental to neutralizing Inter's quality. The team showed maturity in managing the result, even under intense pressure in the second half. <br/><br/> After this victory, fans may have been excited about the possibility of revenge against Manchester City. However, the Club World Cup has shown that it never tires of surprising, and Fluminense now has a match scheduled against Al-Hilal for Friday, which will very likely be their biggest challenge so far. <br/><br/> The performance against Inter demonstrates that Fluminense is growing in the tournament and could be a surprise in the next phases. The combination of defensive solidity, offensive efficiency, and tactical adaptability makes the tricolor a fearsome opponent for any team. <br/><br/> </div>]]></content><author><name>Ace Laboratory Team</name></author><category term="Football;"/><category term="Analysis"/><category term="Football;"/><category term="Analysis;"/><category term="Club"/><category term="World"/><category term="Cup"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[How Renato Gaúcho surprised Inter with tactical change and Fluminense secured qualification in the Round of 16]]></summary></entry></feed>