<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.4.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://ac3lab.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://ac3lab.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2025-05-21T14:08:37+00:00</updated><id>https://ac3lab.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">blank</title><subtitle>Marrying academic rigor with practical applications to benefit sports </subtitle><entry><title type="html">Predicting Match Results in Football - Part 3</title><link href="https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2025/post_poisson_3_en/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Predicting Match Results in Football - Part 3"/><published>2025-05-16T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-05-16T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2025/post_poisson_3_en</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2025/post_poisson_3_en/"><![CDATA[<hr/> <p align="justify"> Se quiser ler este texto em pt-br, <a href="https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2000/post_poisson_3_pt/"> clique aqui.</a> </p> <h2> <b> Introduction </b></h2> <div style="text-align: justify"> In this final post of the Results Prediction series, we’ll introduce the Poisson Distribution. This time, we’ll do something a bit different: we’ll explain what the Poisson Distribution is and walk through the step-by-step process of predicting the final score of a match. <br/><br/> <h3> <b> The Poisson Distribution </b> </h3> The Poisson distribution is a discrete probability distribution that expresses the probability of a given number of events occurring in a fixed interval of time or space. It assumes these events occur with a known average rate and independently of the time since the last event. <br/><br/> <div style="width: 100%; margin: 0 auto; text-align: center;"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2025-05-16-post_poisson_3/image1.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <center>The Poisson distribution formula. <br/><br/></center> The left side of the Poisson distribution formula, P(X = k), represents the probability of exactly k events occurring in a fixed interval. Here, X is the number of events, and k is the specific number we’re interested in. <br/><br/> The numerator on the right-hand side, e<sup>-λ</sup> λ<sup>k</sup>, has two components. λ<sup>k</sup> reflects the likelihood of k events happening based on the average rate λ. The e<sup>-λ</sup> accounts for the randomness of the events, ensuring that the probability decreases as the number of events deviates from the expected rate. <br/><br/> The denominator on the right-hand side, k!, adjusts for the number of ways the k events can occur. The factorial notation calculates the number of possible arrangements, ensuring that the probability accounts for the fact that the order of events doesn’t matter. <br/><br/> <h3> <b> How to Use It in Football </b> </h3> First of all, we need to clarify something: there are several goal prediction models using the Poisson distribution, but we’re going to use the simplest one, which considers only the historical match data of the two teams. More complex models can account for other variables such as pitch quality, head-to-head records, and more. <br/><br/> To begin, we need to decide which matches we want to predict. For this post, we’ll try to predict the number of goals in a Fla-Flu derby (with Fluminense as the home team) in 2023, using data from both teams from the 2022 Brasileirão season. <br/><br/> <h3> <b> Preparing the Table </b> </h3> We used the results of all matches from the 2022 Brasileirão, sourced from the FBREF website. The data includes various pieces of information, but we only used the match results. For the next steps, we had to split the data into “Home Team,” “Away Team,” “Home Goals,” and “Away Goals.” <br/><br/> <h3> <b> Calculating Offensive and Defensive Strength </b> </h3> To predict the number of goals for a team, we first need to calculate the Offensive Strength and Defensive Strength of the teams in the Brasileirão, based on last season. <br/><br/> The Offensive Strength is the average number of goals scored by each team, both at home and away. The formula is: <br/><br/> <ul> <li>Total goals scored at home / number of games</li> <li>Total goals scored away / number of games</li> </ul> <br/><br/> In the 2022 Brasileirão season, there were 534 home goals and 371 away goals. Divided by the number of games (380), we get the average goals scored at home as 1.405, and the average goals scored away as 0.976.<br/><br/> The Defensive Strength is the average number of goals conceded by each team — which is essentially the inverse of Offensive Strength, since the number of goals scored by the home team equals the number of goals conceded by the away team. Thus, the average goals conceded at home is 0.976, and the average goals conceded away is 1.405. <br/><br/> Now we can use these league averages to calculate the strengths of the specific teams we want to analyze. <br/><br/> <h3> <b> Predicting Fluminense’s Goals </b> </h3> To calculate Fluminense’s Offensive Strength, we take the number of home goals scored by Fluminense in the 2022 season (39) and divide it by the number of home games (19) = 2.052. Then we divide this value by the league’s average home goals (1.405), giving us an Offensive Strength of 1.460.<br/><br/> Next, we calculate Flamengo’s Defensive Strength to predict how many goals Fluminense might score. We take the number of away goals conceded by Flamengo (24) and divide it by their number of away games (19) = 1.263. Then divide this by the average away goals conceded in the league (1.405), yielding a Defensive Strength of 0.898.<br/><br/> Now we can compute the expected number of goals for Fluminense by multiplying: Fluminense’s Offensive Strength (1.460) × Flamengo’s Defensive Strength (0.898) × Average Home Goals (1.405)<br/><br/> <b>1.460 × 0.898 × 1.405 = 1.845 </b> <br/><br/> <h3> <b> Predicting Flamengo’s Goals </b> </h3> To calculate the number of goals Flamengo might score, we use the same formulas, but replace the average home goals with average away goals.<br/><br/> <ul> <li>Flamengo’s Offensive Strength: (23/19) / 0.976 = 1.239</li> <li>Fluminense’s Defensive Strength: (20/19) / 0.976 = 1.078</li> </ul> <br/><br/> Now, multiply these values with the average away goals: <br/><br/> <b>1.239 × 1.078 × 0.976 = 1.305 </b> <h3> <b> Using the Poisson Distribution </b> </h3> Since no match ends in a score of 1.845 to 1.305, we use these values with the Poisson Distribution to spread 100% of the probability across possible goal outcomes for each team. We want to estimate the chance of each team scoring a specific number of goals (in our case, 0 to 5) — the number of occurrences of the event — using the expected goals (1.845 for Flu, 1.305 for Fla) - the expected occurencies. <br/><br/> We can do this easily in Python using the command:<br/><br/> <figure class="highlight"><pre><code class="language-python" data-lang="python"><table class="rouge-table"><tbody><tr><td class="gutter gl"><pre class="lineno">1
</pre></td><td class="code"><pre><span class="n">poisson</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">pmf</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">NumberOfOccurrences</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">ExpectedOccurrences</span><span class="p">)</span>
</pre></td></tr></tbody></table></code></pre></figure> <br/><br/> Calculating this 6 times for each team, we get the following vectors: <table> <thead> <tr> <th style="color: white;">Goals</th> <th style="color: white;">Fluminense</th> <th style="color: white;">Flamengo</th> </tr> </thead> <tbody> <tr> <td style="color: white;">0 goals</td> <td style="color: white;">15.80%</td> <td style="color: white;">27.11%</td> </tr> <tr> <td style="color: white;">1 goal</td> <td style="color: white;">29.15%</td> <td style="color: white;">35.39%</td> </tr> <tr> <td style="color: white;">2 goals</td> <td style="color: white;">26.90%</td> <td style="color: white;">23.09%</td> </tr> <tr> <td style="color: white;">3 goals</td> <td style="color: white;">16.54%</td> <td style="color: white;">10.05%</td> </tr> <tr> <td style="color: white;">4 goals</td> <td style="color: white;">7.63%</td> <td style="color: white;">3.28%</td> </tr> <tr> <td style="color: white;">5 goals</td> <td style="color: white;">2.82%</td> <td style="color: white;">0.86%</td> </tr> </tbody> </table> Since these results are independent, the most likely result of the match is 1-1, as both teams are most likely to score 1 goal. Multiplying the probabilities of each team scoring 1 goal gives the probability of a 1-1 draw: <br/><br/> <b>0.2915 × 0.3539 = 0.1031</b><br/><br/> Using the np.outer command with these two vectors, we can generate the full probability matrix of all possible score combinations.<br/><br/> <div style="width: 100%; margin: 0 auto; text-align: center;"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2025-05-16-post_poisson_3/image2.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <center>By summing the probabilities: Above the diagonal (Fluminense wins): 48.96% <br/> On the diagonal (Draw): 22.75% <br/> Below the diagonal (Flamengo wins): 26.91% <br/><br/></center> <h2> <b> Conclusion </b> </h2> <div style="width: 100%; margin: 0 auto; text-align: center;"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2025-05-16-post_poisson_3/image3.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <center>In total, we had 3 draws, 2 wins for Flamengo, and 1 win for Fluminense. When Fluminense played at home, there were two draws and one win for Fluminense. <br/><br/></center> From this result, we can compare it with the first encounter between the teams in 2023, which took place in the final round of the Taça Guanabara and ended in a 2-1 win for Fluminense. That result was the second most likely according to our model, indicating that the match followed the expected trend based on the teams’ offensive and defensive performance from the previous season. <br/><br/> Moreover, we didn’t use data from earlier 2023 Campeonato Carioca matches, which could provide more up-to-date offensive and defensive strength values — and thus a different probability distribution. <br/><br/> With this analysis, we wrap up our series of posts, where we’ve explored some predictive models applied to football and how we can use them to better understand the sport. <div> </div></div>]]></content><author><name>Ace Laboratory Football Team - Lucas Calmon, Pedro Carvalho</name></author><category term="Football;"/><category term="Analysis"/><category term="Football;"/><category term="Analysis"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Predicting Match Results in Football - Part 2</title><link href="https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2025/post-value-market_2_ing/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Predicting Match Results in Football - Part 2"/><published>2025-04-15T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-04-15T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2025/post-value-market_2_ing</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2025/post-value-market_2_ing/"><![CDATA[<p align="justify"> Se quiser ler este texto em pt-br, <a href="https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2025/post-value_market_2_pt/"> clique aqui.</a> <h2> <b> Introduction </b> </h2> <div style="text-align: justify"> In this post, we will present another method for predicting victory. This time, we will use the market value of the teams as the main variable, which corresponds to the sum of the individual market values of all players on the team. We will explore how this metric can influence the performance of clubs and their chances of winning a match. </div> <h3> <b> Context </b> </h3> <div style="text-align: justify"> Money plays a significant role in modern football. With the transfer market becoming increasingly inflated, it is necessary to spend more money in the transfer windows to maintain competitiveness in the top leagues. The professionalization of the sport has also had a great influence on increasing the cost of maintaining a team, as more expenses are now needed for infrastructure and creating a quality environment to stay ahead of the competition. In fact, studies in the Premier League and Championship (2011-2020) have shown a correlation between a team's payroll and the position the team achieves in the table (Soccernomics, Simon Kuper and Stefan Szymanski). Money drives football. Therefore, we will use the market value of the clubs in the Brazilian league to try to predict the final result of the matches. <div style="width: 100%; margin: 0 auto; text-align: center;"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2025-04-15-post-value-market-2/img1.jpeg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <h3> <b> Method </b> </h3> <h4><b>Data</b></h4> <div style="text-align: justify"> We will use data from the 2023 season. <b></b> The dataset has two main parts: <ul> <br/> <li>The match data: information such as the home team, away team, result, match date, and odds for victory (home, draw, away), extracted from the <a href="https://football-data.co.uk/">Football-data</a> website and the Pinnacle betting house.</li> <li>The market value of the teams in the Brazilian league 2023, sourced from <a href="https://www.transfermarkt.com.br">Transfermarkt</a>.</li> </ul> Let’s take a look at our match dataset. It has about 19 fields, but only the following are relevant to us: <div style="width: 80%; margin: 0 auto; text-align: center;"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2025-04-15-post-value-market-2/img2.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <b>Legend:</b> home: Home team; away: Away team; res: Match result; oddHome: Home team's chance of victory; oddDraw: Chance of a draw; oddAway: Away team's chance of victory. <br/><br/> We will transform the odds into probabilities. To do this, we don't simply use the formula (1/odds), because the sum of the probabilities would exceed 1. This excess represents the bookmaker's margin, so we normalize the probabilities to correct it. <div style="width: 80%; margin: 0 auto; text-align: center;"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2025-04-15-post-value-market-2/img3.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> Now let's take a look at the market value data: <div style="width: 50%; margin: 0 auto; text-align: center;"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2025-04-15-post-value-market-2/img4.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <div style="text-align: justify"> The column <code>TFM_Value</code> contains the market value in millions of euros. For example, Palmeiras' market value is 138.4 million euros. These values represent the market values of the clubs as of July 20, 2024. <b></b> We have merged the two datasets, adding the market value columns for the home team (<code>tmH</code>) and the away team (<code>tmA</code>). <div style="width: 100%; margin: 0 auto; text-align: center;"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2025-04-15-post-value-market-2/img5.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> The variable we will use to predict the results is the ratio between <code>tmH</code> (home team's market value) and <code>tmA</code> (away team's market value). More specifically, the <b>logarithm</b> of this ratio. The reason we use the log is that the distribution of the ratio between <code>tmH</code> and <code>tmA</code> is skewed to the right. Applying the log function makes the distribution symmetrical, which improves performance. The image below helps to visualize this. <div style="width: 80%; margin: 0 auto; text-align: center;"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2025-04-15-post-value-market-2/img6.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div style="width: 80%; margin: 0 auto; text-align: center;"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2025-04-15-post-value-market-2/img7.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> So, the <code>logTmRatio</code> will be the variable we will use to predict the results. In other words, our independent variable. <div style="text-align: justify"> We encoded the <code>res</code> column as: <ul> <li>0: Home team victory</li> <li>1: Draw</li> <li>2: Away team victory</li> </ul> This new column will be called <code>winValue</code>. <div style="width: 80%; margin: 0 auto; text-align: center;"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2025-04-15-post-value-market-2/img8.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <h3><b>Model</b></h3> <div style="text-align: justify"> We will use an <b>Ordinal Logistic Regression</b> model, which is a technique used to model the relationship between an ordinal response variable (i.e., categories with order) and one or more predictor variables. In our case, the ordinal response variable is <code>winValue</code> and the predictor variable will be <code>logTmRatio</code>. The model involves determining the \( \alpha_1 \), which is the point that separates the home team victory from the draw or away team victory. In other words, if a point falls before \( \alpha_1 \), the model will predict a home team victory, and if it falls after \( \alpha_1 \), it will predict a draw or away team victory. The \( \alpha_2 \) is the point that separates the draw from the away team victory. The \( \beta \) indicates how the predictor variable, in our case the market value ratio, influences the result. For better visualization of this explanation, observe the graph below, where \( \alpha_1 \) is represented by \( \theta_1 \): <div style="width: 80%; margin: 0 auto; text-align: center;"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2025-04-15-post-value-market-2/img9.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> We used an Ordinal Logistic Regression model, which relates an ordinal response variable (<code>winValue</code>) to a continuous predictor (<code>logTmRatio</code>). The model finds two cutoff points: <ul> <li><b>\( \alpha_1 \)</b>: separates home team victory from draw or away team victory</li> <li><b>\( \alpha_2 \)</b>: separates draw from away team victory</li> <li><b>\( \beta \)</b>: tells us how this ratio influences the result of The coefficient of <code>logTmRatio</code></li> </ul> Now that we understand the model, let's prepare its training. The training dataset consists of the first 200 games of the season, and the remaining 180 games will be used as the test dataset. <div style="width: 80%; margin: 0 auto; text-align: center;"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2025-04-15-post-value-market-2/img10.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <b>Model coefficients:</b><br/> \(\beta \): -0.6309<br/> \( \alpha_1 \): -0.1519<br/> \( \alpha_2 \): 0.0533 </div> <h4><b>Probability Calculation</b></h4> <div style="text-align: justify"> From these coefficients, we calculate: <ul> <li><b>Ph (home team victory)</b>: \( \frac{1}{1 + e^{-( \alpha_1 - βx)}} \)</li> <li><b>Pd (draw)</b>: \( \frac{1}{1 + e^{-( \alpha_2 - βx)}} - Ph \)</li> <li><b>Pv (away team victory)</b>: \( 1 - Ph - Pd \)</li> </ul> <div style="width: 100%; margin: 0 auto; text-align: center;"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2025-04-15-post-value-market-2/img11.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> Let's add columns to compare the prediction results from Pinnacle and what we found. <div style="width: 100%; margin: 0 auto; text-align: center;"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2025-04-15-post-value-market-2/img12.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <h3> <b> Evaluation </b> </h3> <div style="text-align: justify"> Remember that we used the first 200 games to train our model, so we will compare the prediction results from our test set. <div style="width: 100%; margin: 0 auto; text-align: center;"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2025-04-15-post-value-market-2/img13.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> The most important value for us is highlighted: the average accuracy of results from both the bookmaker and our model. Notice that they are close, and even the bookmaker had less than 50% accuracy. One important thing to consider when analyzing these data is the size of the training set, which only had 200 matches, and we achieved a result of a 0.03 difference from the bookmaker. Let’s create two cross tables to better understand in which types of games our model is most likely to make errors and succeed. <div style="width: 40%; margin: 0 auto; text-align: center;"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2025-04-15-post-value-market-2/img14.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> Notice that in the draw column, our model did not predict draws, which is due to the fact that the market value ratio between two teams has a very low probability of resulting in a draw, since it is expected that the market values of the teams would need to be close to each other. <div style="width: 40%; margin: 0 auto; text-align: center;"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2025-04-15-post-value-market-2/img15.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> The numbers are quite scattered, but we can see that our model performs better than Pinnacle in predicting away team victories, while Pinnacle has most of its correct predictions in home team victories. </div> <h2> <b> Conclusion </b> </h2> <div style="text-align: justify"> In the next post, we will discuss the prediction of results based on the Poisson distribution, a well-known distribution used to predict rare events. Stay tuned to our social media to not miss any updates from the blog! </div> </p>]]></content><author><name>Ace Laboratory Football Team - Lucas Calmon, Pedro Carvalho</name></author><category term="Football;"/><category term="Analysis"/><category term="Football;"/><category term="Analysis"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Prevendo Resultados no Futebol - Parte 2</title><link href="https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2025/post-value_market_2_pt/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Prevendo Resultados no Futebol - Parte 2"/><published>2025-04-15T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-04-15T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2025/post-value_market_2_pt</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2025/post-value_market_2_pt/"><![CDATA[<h2> <b> Introdução </b> </h2> <div style="text-align: justify"> Neste post, vamos apresentar mais um método para previsão de vitória. Desta vez, utilizaremos como variável principal o valor de mercado dos times, que corresponde à soma dos valores de mercado individuais de todos os jogadores da equipe. Vamos explorar como essa métrica pode influenciar o desempenho dos clubes e sua chance de vencer uma partida. </div> <h3> <b> Contextualização </b> </h3> <div style="text-align: justify"> O dinheiro tem um grande papel no futebol moderno. Com o mercado de transferências cada vez mais inflacionado, mostra-se necessário gastar cada vez mais dinheiro nas janelas de transferências para manter a competitividade nas maiores ligas. A exponente profissionalização do esporte também possui grande influência no encarecimento do custo de manter um time, visto que atualmente são necessários mais gastos em estrutura e um ambiente de qualidade para se manter na frente dos demais. Inclusive, estudos na Premier League e Championship (2011-2020) mostraram que existe uma correlação entre a folha salarial de um time e a posição que esse time alcança na tabela (Soccernomics, Simon Kuper e Stefan Szymansk). O dinheiro move o futebol. Por isso, vamos utilizar o valor de mercado dos clubes do Brasileirão para tentar prever o resultado final das partidas. <div style="width: 100%; margin: 0 auto; text-align: center;"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2025-04-15-post-value-market-2/img1.jpeg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <h3> <b> Método </b> </h3> <h4><b>Dados</b></h4> <div style="text-align: justify"> Nós iremos usar os dados da temporada 2023. <b></b> O dataset tem duas partes principais: <ul> <br/> <li>Os dados das partidas: informações como time da casa, time visitante, resultado, data da partida e odds de vitória (casa, empate, visitante), extraídas do site <a href="(https://football-data.co.uk/)">Footbal-data</a> e da casa de apostas Pinnacle.</li> <li>O valor de mercado dos times do Brasileirão 2023, retirados do site <a href="(https://www.transfermarkt.com.br)">Transfermarkt</a>.</li> </ul> Vamos agora dar uma olhada no nosso dataset das partidas. Ele possui cerca de 19 campos, mas só os seguintes nos interessam: <div style="width: 80%; margin: 0 auto; text-align: center;"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2025-04-15-post-value-market-2/img2.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <b>Legenda:</b> home: Time mandante; away: Time visitante; res: Resultado da partida; oddHome: Chance da vitória do time mandante; oddDraw: Chance do empate; oddAway: Chance da vitória do time visitante. <br/><br/> Iremos transformar odds em probabilidades. Para isso, não utilizamos apenas a fórmula (1/odds), pois a soma das probabilidades seria maior que 1. Esse excesso representa a margem de lucro das casas de apostas, então normalizamos as probabilidades para corrigi-la. <div style="width: 80%; margin: 0 auto; text-align: center;"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2025-04-15-post-value-market-2/img3.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <p>Vamos observar os dados de valor de mercado agora:</p> <div style="width: 50%; margin: 0 auto; text-align: center;"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2025-04-15-post-value-market-2/img4.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <div style="text-align: justify"> A coluna <code>TFM_Value</code> contém o valor de mercado em milhões de euros. Por exemplo, o valor de mercado do Palmeiras é de 138,4 milhões de euros. Esses dados representam os valores de mercado dos clubes no dia 20 de Julho de 2024. <b></b> Unimos os dois datasets, adicionando as colunas de valor de mercado do time da casa (<code>tmH</code>) e do visitante (<code>tmA</code>). <div style="width: 80%; margin: 0 auto; text-align: center;"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2025-04-15-post-value-market-2/img5.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> A variável que vamos utilizar para realizar a previsão de resultados é a razão entre o <code>tmH</code> (valor de mercado do time da casa) e <code>tmA</code> (valor de mercado do time da visitante). Mais especificamente o <b>logaritmo</b> dessa razão. O motivo de utilizarmos o log é pelo fato de que a distribuição da razão entre <code>tmH</code> e <code>tmA</code> estar inclinada para a direita. A aplicação da função log leva a uma distribuição simétrica, o que melhora a performance. A imagem abaixo ajudam a visualizar isso. <div style="width: 80%; margin: 0 auto; text-align: center;"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2025-04-15-post-value-market-2/img6.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div style="width: 80%; margin: 0 auto; text-align: center;"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2025-04-15-post-value-market-2/img7.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <p>Então o <code>logTmRatio</code> será a variável que iremos utilizar para a previsão de resultados. Em outras palavras, a nossa variável independente.</p> <div style="text-align: justify"> Codificamos a coluna <code>res</code> com: <ul> <li>0: vitória do time da casa</li> <li>1: empate</li> <li>2: vitória do time visitante</li> </ul> Essa nova coluna será chamada de <code>winValue</code>. <div style="width: 80%; margin: 0 auto; text-align: center;"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2025-04-15-post-value-market-2/img8.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <h3><b>Modelo</b></h3> <div style="text-align: justify"> Nós iremos usar um modelo de <b>Regressão Logística Ordinal</b> que consiste em uma técnica utilizada para modelar a relação entre uma variável de resposta ordinal, ou seja categorias que possuem ordem, e uma ou mais variáveis preditoras. No nosso caso, a variável de resposta ordinal é o <code>winValue</code> e a variável preditora será o <code>logTmRatio</code>. O modelo consiste em descobrirmos o \( \alpha_1 \) que é o ponto que divide a vitória do mandante e empate ou vitória do visitante, ou seja, se um ponto cair antes de \( \alpha_1 \), o modelo preverá a vitória do mandante e se cair após \( \alpha_1 \), preverá o empate ou vitória do visitante. Já o \( \alpha_2 \) é o ponto que divide o empate e a vitória do visitante. O \( \beta \) indica como a variável preditiva, no nosso caso a razão do valor de mercado, influencia no resultado. Para uma melhor visualização dessa explicação, basta observar o gráfico abaixo, no qual o \( \alpha_1 \) é representado por \( \theta_1 \): <div style="width: 80%; margin: 0 auto; text-align: center;"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2025-04-15-post-value-market-2/img9.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> Usamos um modelo de Regressão Logística Ordinal, que relaciona uma variável resposta ordinal (<code>winValue</code>) a uma preditora contínua (<code>logTmRatio</code>). O modelo encontra dois pontos de corte: <ul> <li><b>\( \alpha_1 \)</b>: separa vitória do mandante de empate ou vitória do visitante</li> <li><b>\( \alpha_2 \)</b>: separa empate de vitória do visitante</li> <li><b>\( \beta \)</b>: nos diz como essa razão influencia o resultado do coeficiente de <code>logTmRatio</code></li> </ul> Agora que entendemos sobre o modelo, vamos preparar o seu treinamento. O dataset de treino consiste nos primeiros 200 jogos da temporada e os 180 jogos restantes serão usados como dataset de teste. <div style="width: 80%; margin: 0 auto; text-align: center;"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2025-04-15-post-value-market-2/img10.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <b>Coeficientes do modelo:</b><br/> \(\beta \): -0.6309<br/> \( \alpha_1 \): -0.1519<br/> \( \alpha_2 \): 0.0533 </div> <h4><b>Cálculo das probabilidades</b></h4> <div style="text-align: justify"> A partir desses coeficientes, calculamos: <ul> <li><b>Ph (vitória do mandante)</b>: \( \frac{1}{1 + e^{-( \alpha_1 - βx)}} \)</li> <li><b>Pd (empate)</b>: \( \frac{1}{1 + e^{-( \alpha_2 - βx)}} - Ph \)</li> <li><b>Pv (vitória do visitante)</b>: \( 1 - Ph - Pd \)</li> </ul> <div style="width: 100%; margin: 0 auto; text-align: center;"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2025-04-15-post-value-market-2/img11.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> Vamos adicionar colunas que compare os resultados de previsão da Pinnacle e o que encontramos. <div style="width: 100%; margin: 0 auto; text-align: center;"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2025-04-15-post-value-market-2/img12.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <h3> <b> Avaliação </b> </h3> <div style="text-align: justify"> Lembrando que utilizamos os primeiros 200 jogos para treinar o nosso modelo, por isso vamos comparar os resultados de previsão do nosso conjunto de teste. <div style="width: 100%; margin: 0 auto; text-align: center;"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2025-04-15-post-value-market-2/img13.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> O valor que mais nos interessa está destacado que é a média de acertos de resultados da casa de apostas e do nosso modelo. Repare que são valores próximos e até mesmo a casa de apostas teve menos de 50% de acerto. Uma coisa importante para se considerar ao analisar esses dados é o tamanho do conjunto de treino que só teve 200 partidas e obtivemos um resultado de 0.03 de diferença para a casa de aposta. Vamos fazer duas tabelas cruzadas para entendermos melhor em quais tipos de jogos nosso modelo mais erra e acerta. <div style="width: 40%; margin: 0 auto; text-align: center;"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2025-04-15-post-value-market-2/img14.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> Note que na coluna de empates o nosso modelo não previu empates, isso é causado pelo fato de que a razão entre o valor de mercado de dois times têm uma probabilidade muito baixa de se relacionar com empate, já que se imagina que os valores de mercados do times teriam que ser próximos entre si. <div style="width: 40%; margin: 0 auto; text-align: center;"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2025-04-15-post-value-market-2/img15.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> Os números estão bem dispersos, mas percebesse que o nosso modelo acerta mais do que o Pinnacle no quesito vitória do visitante, enquanto a Pinnacle tem a maioria dos seus acertos nas vitórias dos times da casa. </div> <h2> <b> Conclusão </b> </h2> <div style="text-align: justify"> No próximo post, abordaremos a previsão de resultados com base na distribuição de Poisson, uma famosa distribuição usada para prever eventos raros. Fique atento às nossas redes sociais para não perder nenhuma novidade do blog! </div>]]></content><author><name>Ace Laboratory Football Team - Lucas Calmon, Pedro Carvalho</name></author><category term="Football;"/><category term="Analysis"/><category term="Football;"/><category term="Analysis"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Introdução Neste post, vamos apresentar mais um método para previsão de vitória. Desta vez, utilizaremos como variável principal o valor de mercado dos times, que corresponde à soma dos valores de mercado individuais de todos os jogadores da equipe. Vamos explorar como essa métrica pode influenciar o desempenho dos clubes e sua chance de vencer uma partida.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Predicting Match Results in Football - Part 1</title><link href="https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2025/post_pitagorica_1_en/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Predicting Match Results in Football - Part 1"/><published>2025-02-12T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-02-12T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2025/post_pitagorica_1_en</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2025/post_pitagorica_1_en/"><![CDATA[<hr/> <p align="justify"> Se quiser ler este texto em pt-br, <a href="https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2000/post_pitagorica_1_pt/"> clique aqui.</a> </p> <h2> <b> Introduction </b></h2> <div style="text-align: justify"> In this series of posts, we will explore some methods to predict football clubs' winning percentage. In this first post, we will discuss two statistics: the winning percentage and a variation of it called the Pythagorean expectation. The data used will be from the latest seasons of major European leagues (23-24) and the Brazilian league (24), extracted from the FBREF website. <br/><br/> <h3> <b> What is the Pythagorean Expectation? </b> </h3> The Pythagorean expectation is an analytical formula initially used in baseball. It was created by Bill James, a renowned statistician and pioneer in sports data analysis, who wrote dozens of books studying baseball through statistics to determine why teams win or lose. This formula aims to estimate the percentage of games a team should have won based on the number of runs they scored and allowed. In football, the equivalent would be goals scored and goals conceded. <br/><br/> <div style="width: 100%; margin: 0 auto; text-align: center;"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2025-02-12-post_pitagorica_1/image1.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <center>The name of the statistic comes from the similarity of its formula to the Pythagorean theorem. <br/><br/></center> Comparing a team's winning percentage with its Pythagorean expectation can help evaluate which teams are performing above expectations and which are underperforming. <br/><br/> <h3> <b> The Research </b> </h3> The data used consists of a table with all match results from each league's season, collected from <a href="https://fbref.com/pt/comps/24/cronograma/Serie-A-Resultados-e-Calendarios">FBREF</a>. <br/><br/> <h3> <b> Data Preparation and Defining Percentages </b> </h3> After extracting the data and performing basic table cleaning, the result is a DataFrame in the following format. A season consists of 380 matches, and to calculate the winning percentage and the Pythagorean expectation, we need the following information: the match result determines the team's winning percentage, while goals scored and conceded define the Pythagorean expectation. <br/><br/> <div style="width: 100%; margin: 0 auto; text-align: center;"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2025-02-12-post_pitagorica_1/image2.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <center>This is the way the data is extracted from FBREF. <br/><br/></center> We separated each team's goals and determined the winner of each match. This allows us to calculate the winning percentage—where a win is worth 1, a draw is worth 0.5, and a loss is worth 0. The sum of these values is then divided by the number of games played (<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Winning_percentage">Wikipedia</a>). <br/><br/> After adjusting the table and calculating the teams' winning percentages, we split the data into the First Half and Second Half of the season, meaning before and after matchday 20. The table for the First Half of the season looks like this: <br/><br/> <div style="width: 100%; margin: 0 auto; text-align: center;"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2025-02-12-post_pitagorica_1/image3.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <center> G: Number of matches played; W: Win value, used for calculating the winning percentage; GF: Goals scored; GA: Goals conceded; wpc: Winning percentage <br/><br/></center> To finalize our table, we calculate the Pythagorean expectation and merge the First and Second Half tables according to each team. <br/><br/> <div style="width: 100%; margin: 0 auto; text-align: center;"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2025-02-12-post_pitagorica_1/image4.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <center> Values with <b>x</b> refer to the First Half, and values with <b>y</b> refer to the Second Half. <br/><br/></center> Code for Calculating wpc and pyth: <br/> <br/> <figure class="highlight"><pre><code class="language-python" data-lang="python"><table class="rouge-table"><tbody><tr><td class="gutter gl"><pre class="lineno">1
2
</pre></td><td class="code"><pre><span class="n">PrimeiroTurno</span><span class="p">[</span><span class="sh">'</span><span class="s">win_percentage</span><span class="sh">'</span><span class="p">]</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">PrimeiroTurno</span><span class="p">[</span><span class="sh">'</span><span class="s">W</span><span class="sh">'</span><span class="p">]</span> <span class="o">/</span> <span class="n">PrimeiroTurno</span><span class="p">[</span><span class="sh">'</span><span class="s">G</span><span class="sh">'</span><span class="p">]</span>  <span class="c1"># win percentage - (Win Value) / (Games Played)
</span><span class="n">PrimeiroTurno</span><span class="p">[</span><span class="sh">'</span><span class="s">pythagorean</span><span class="sh">'</span><span class="p">]</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">PrimeiroTurno</span><span class="p">[</span><span class="sh">'</span><span class="s">GF</span><span class="sh">'</span><span class="p">]</span><span class="o">**</span><span class="mi">2</span> <span class="o">/</span> <span class="p">(</span><span class="n">PrimeiroTurno</span><span class="p">[</span><span class="sh">'</span><span class="s">GF</span><span class="sh">'</span><span class="p">]</span><span class="o">**</span><span class="mi">2</span> <span class="o">+</span> <span class="n">PrimeiroTurno</span><span class="p">[</span><span class="sh">'</span><span class="s">GA</span><span class="sh">'</span><span class="p">]</span><span class="o">**</span><span class="mi">2</span><span class="p">)</span>  <span class="c1"># pythagorean expectation - (Goals For)^2 / ((Goals For)^2 + (Goals Against)^2)</span>
</pre></td></tr></tbody></table></code></pre></figure> <br/><br/> <h3> <b> Discussing Regression Graphs and Correlation </b></h3> As seen in the image below, the Pythagorean expectation in the first half of the Premier League is strongly related to the winning percentage, as expected. <br/><br/> <div style="width: 100%; margin: 0 auto; text-align: center;"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2025-02-12-post_pitagorica_1/image5.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <center> The relationship between <b>pythagorean_x</b> and <b>win_percentage_x</b> in the First Half is represented in the graph. The line represents a linear regression fitted to the data, showing the relationship between the two variables. <br/><br/></center> But what we really want to know is: which of these statistics has a stronger relationship with a team’s winning percentage at the end of the season? To analyze this, we can generate a correlation table comparing these statistics between the First Half and Second Half of the season. <br/><br/> <div style="width: 100%; margin: 0 auto; text-align: center;"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2025-02-12-post_pitagorica_1/image6.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <center> Premier League correlation table. <br/><br/></center> As seen in the highlighted values, <b>pythagorean_x</b> has a stronger correlation with <b>win_percentage_y</b> (0.80) than <b>win_percentage_x</b> with <b>win_percentage_y</b> (0.75). While this difference is small, it suggests that the Pythagorean expectation has slightly better predictive power than the winning percentage. This is the result for the Premier League. What about other leagues? <br/><br/> <h4> <b> Bundesliga </b></h4> <div style="width: 100%; margin: 0 auto; text-align: center;"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2025-02-12-post_pitagorica_1/image7.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <center> Bundesliga correlation table. <br/><br/></center> <h4> <b> La Liga </b></h4> <div style="width: 100%; margin: 0 auto; text-align: center;"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2025-02-12-post_pitagorica_1/image8.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <center> La Liga correlation table. <br/><br/></center> <h4> <b> Serie A </b></h4> <div style="width: 100%; margin: 0 auto; text-align: center;"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2025-02-12-post_pitagorica_1/image9.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <center> Serie A correlation table. <br/><br/></center> <h4> <b> Ligue One </b></h4> <div style="width: 100%; margin: 0 auto; text-align: center;"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2025-02-12-post_pitagorica_1/image10.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <center> Ligue One correlation table. <br/><br/></center> As observed, in the German, Spanish, and Italian leagues, the values are slightly lower, but the Pythagorean expectation still has better predictive power than the winning percentage. In the French league, despite the correlation between First Half and Second Half results being below 50%, the Pythagorean expectation still outperforms the winning percentage. So far, everything aligns with expectations. However, things get interesting when we analyze the Brazilian league. <br/><br/> <h4> <b> Brasileirão </b></h4> <div style="width: 100%; margin: 0 auto; text-align: center;"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2025-02-12-post_pitagorica_1/image11.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <center> Brasileirão correlation table. <br/><br/></center> In the Brazilian league, not only do First Half values have less than 30% correlation with Second Half results, but the winning percentage also has a <b>higher correlation</b> than the Pythagorean expectation! This is the only one of the six leagues studied where this phenomenon occurs. <br/><br/> <h2> <b> Conclusion </b></h2> Based on the experiment’s results, we decided to analyze how much team performance fluctuates between the two halves of the season, depending on the league, to better understand the most ‘unpredictable’ leagues. To do this, we calculated the mean and median of this variation across all studied leagues. The <b>Brasileirão stood out as the competition with the highest fluctuation between halves</b>, surpassing European leagues. Surprisingly, La Liga showed a relatively high variation for European standards. <br/><br/> <table> <thead> <tr> <th style="color: white;">Leagues</th> <th style="color: white;">Median Performance Difference</th> <th style="color: white;">Mean Performance Difference</th> </tr> </thead> <tbody> <tr> <td style="color: white;">Premier League</td> <td style="color: white;">20.78%</td> <td style="color: white;">27.13%</td> </tr> <tr> <td style="color: white;">La Liga</td> <td style="color: white;">21.64%</td> <td style="color: white;">36.83%</td> </tr> <tr> <td style="color: white;">Ligue 1</td> <td style="color: white;">23.25%</td> <td style="color: white;">32.35%</td> </tr> <tr> <td style="color: white;">Série A</td> <td style="color: white;">18.61%</td> <td style="color: white;">27.39%</td> </tr> <tr> <td style="color: white;">Bundesliga</td> <td style="color: white;">21.30%</td> <td style="color: white;">26.35%</td> </tr> <tr> <td style="color: white;">Brasileirão</td> <td style="color: white;">32.14%</td> <td style="color: white;">38.76%</td> </tr> </tbody> </table> <br/><br/> <h4>Performance Difference Calculation:</h4> \[ \left( \frac{\text{Second Half Performance}}{\text{First Half Performance}} - 1 \right) \times 100\% \] <div style="width: 100%; margin: 0 auto; text-align: center;"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2025-02-12-post_pitagorica_1/image12.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <center> variation in Brazilian clubs’ performances between the First and Second Halves of the Brasileirão. <br/><br/></center> The graph above illustrates the high variation in Brazilian clubs’ performances between the First and Second Halves of the Brasileirão. Teams like Vitória, Grêmio, Fluminense, and Corinthians had poor results in the first half but above-average performances in the second half. Meanwhile, Atlético Mineiro, Cruzeiro, and Bahia performed well in the first half but declined in the second. Why does this happen? <br/><br/> We can speculate on some possible reasons, such as increased investment over time, frequent coaching changes, or fan pressure after poor results, which forces club management to invest more in reinforcements. However, determining the real cause would require a more in-depth study on the subject. <br/><br/> In the next post, we will discuss predicting outcomes based on the clubs' market value, which will be our primary variable. Stay tuned to our social media channels so you don't miss any updates from the blog! <br/> <br/> <div> </div></div>]]></content><author><name>Ace Laboratory Football Team - Lucas Calmon, Pedro Carvalho</name></author><category term="Football;"/><category term="Analysis"/><category term="Football;"/><category term="Analysis"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">São Garrafa Niterói 2024 – Analyzing 10 different runners</title><link href="https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2025/post_sao_garrafa_en/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="São Garrafa Niterói 2024 – Analyzing 10 different runners"/><published>2025-01-26T11:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-01-26T11:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2025/post_sao_garrafa_en</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2025/post_sao_garrafa_en/"><![CDATA[<p align="justify"> Se quiser ler este texto em pt-br, <a href="https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2000/post_sao_garrafa_pt/"> clique aqui.</a> </p> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2025-01-28-post_sao_garrafa/imagem_0.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <p align="justify"> On December 15 2024, the last edition of São Garrafa, a very traditional race in the city of Niterói (RJ). The event featured 5km and 15km routes and is renowned for the significant challenges in the longer-distance course: nearly 4km of uphill segments, with certain points becoming quite steep. </p> <p align="justify"> A total of 1.973 runners completed the race, with 1.010 in the 5km course and 963 in the 15km course. Here's an interesting detail: in the shorter distance, the majority of participants were women (around 63%), while in the longer distance, the majority were men, with women accounting for 38% of the participants. </p> <p align="justify"> As it is well known that weather conditions can directly impact athletes performance, it's worth noting that the race started at 6:30am and that during the event, the sky was heavily overcast, with occasional drizzle. According to some participants, the early start time combined with the weather conditions contributed positively to their performance on the course, as December tends to be very hot in Niterói. </p> <p>Let’s dive into the analysis!</p> <p align="justify"> The goal of this post is to analyze the performance of some participants to shed light on and validate certain hypotheses that we already know from other studies and related work. </p> <p align="justify"> Ten athletes who participated in the race and used the <a href="https://www.strava.com/">Strava</a> app provided consent to participate in the analysis and shared the race data collected by the app. This dataset includes information such as speed, distance, compass, and more. Additionally, the volunteer runners completed a brief questionnaire containing details about their training, race preparation, and experience. </p> <p>In general, regarding the participants:</p> <ul> <li>All of them had a habit of running and practicing other exercises;</li> <li>Only 4 had previously run the race course;</li> <li>9 out of the 10 participants prepared for the race in a more comprehensive manner.</li> </ul> <h2>Exploratory</h2> <p align="justify"> The data extracted from Strava and provided by the participants were imported into Python for a more detailed exploratory analysis. It is important to note that we removed 2 runners from the analysis due to inconsistent data — most likely caused by GPS data capture failures during the race. </p> <p align="justify"> In the chart below, you can visualize the performance of each participant (average pace) by distance covered: </p> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2025-01-28-post_sao_garrafa/imagem_2.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <p align="justify"> Right from the start, runners 1, 5, 6, and 10 stand out for maintaining a low pace throughout the entire course — around 4'30" on average. Coincidence? Probably not, as these were the 4 runners who had trained on the race course before the event. To simplify the understanding from here on, we will refer to this group as the "course-savvy runners". This point highlights just how crucial preparation and knowledge of the course are before taking on a challenging race. </p> <p align="justify"> Notice that between kilometers 5 and 8, all athletes showed a decrease in their speeds (increase in pace). This is exactly the part of the course with a very steep uphill, where it is quite difficult to maintain the pace. Here, a statistical test was conducted to compare the pace of the course-savvy runners with those who were not familiar with the course, and it can be stated that there is a statistically significant difference (p-value &lt; 0.05) in the speeds of these two groups at this segment of the course. </p> <p align="justify"> In this other chart, it's also possible to visualize the performance of each participant, but now by race time. Once again, the course-savvy runners stand out for, unsurprisingly, being the ones to finish the race the fastest. </p> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2025-01-28-post_sao_garrafa/imagem_1.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <p align="justify"> In general, the course-savvy runners were at a walking speed (established here as 5 km/h) less frequently compared to the non-savvy runners. Another point that reinforces the idea that "more trained" athletes naturally perform better is their experience time. The course-savvy runners have an average of 5 years of running experience each, while the non-savvy runners have an average of 1 year. </p> <p align="justify"> It was also possible to compare performance by elevation range (in meters), as shown in the chart below. Runners 1 and 5 stand out for their minimal pace fluctuations as the elevation level increases, demonstrating their ability to maintain a nearly constant pace, as shown above. A previous study delves deeper into this point, suggesting that more experienced runners show fewer fluctuations in their speed series, meaning fewer abrupt changes. The full article can be found <a href="https://sol.sbc.org.br/index.php/sbbd/article/view/30754">here</a>! </p> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2025-01-28-post_sao_garrafa/imagem_3.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <h2>Discussion</h2> <p align="justify"> By analyzing the performance of the runners monitored by Strava, along with the information on preparation and experience in the sport, it was possible to validate some ideas already raised by other studies in a real race scenario: preparation and training are strongly correlated with good performance. </p> <p align="justify"> According to the analysis, the course-savvy runners had better results, maintaining a more consistent pace throughout the race compared to the others. It is likely that their prior knowledge of the course allowed these runners to better adapt to the challenges. It is important to mention that there are other variables not considered in this analysis, such as nutrition, injury history, age, body anatomy, among others, which, according to the literature, also influence the results. </p> <p align="justify"> Our goal was to illustrate in a real case how some of these variables are connected and to raise the challenge for future work considering other influencing factors for performance evaluation—and even prediction. </p> <p>Any suggestions are welcome!</p> <h2>References</h2> <p>https://neorace.com.br/resultados/g-live.html?f=2024%2Fdez%2Fsgf%2Fsgf.clax</p> <p>TITO, Nathália; PAIXÃO, Balthazar; TAVARES, Lucas G.; OGASAWARA, Eduardo; AMORIM, Glauco F.. Diferenciando Perfis de Corredores por Meio de Pontos de Mudança nos Treinos. In: SIMPÓSIO BRASILEIRO DE BANCO DE DADOS (SBBD), 2024, Florianópolis/SC. Porto Alegre: Sociedade Brasileira de Computação. p. 834-840.</p>]]></content><author><name>Ace Laboratory Football Team - Nathália Tito</name></author><category term="Running;"/><category term="São"/><category term="Garrafa;"/><category term="Python;"/><category term="Analytics;"/><category term="Statistics"/><category term="Running;"/><category term="São"/><category term="Garrafa;"/><category term="Python;"/><category term="Analytics;"/><category term="Statistics"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Analyzing the performance of 10 different runners from São Garrafa 2024]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Analyzing Brazilian Football Signings in 2024 - Offensive Sector: Part 2</title><link href="https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2024/post_contratacoes_2_en/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Analyzing Brazilian Football Signings in 2024 - Offensive Sector: Part 2"/><published>2024-12-16T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-12-16T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2024/post_contratacoes_2_en</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2024/post_contratacoes_2_en/"><![CDATA[<hr/> <p align="justify"> Se quiser ler este texto em pt-br, <a href="https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2000/post_contratacoes_2_pt/"> clique aqui.</a> </p> <h2> <b> Introduction </b></h2> <div style="text-align: justify"> In the latest post in our series on the Brazilian league's attacking signings, we'll be bringing you some new analysis of the players, as well as showing the updated graphs seen in the previous post. This time, we'll be using data that takes into account all 38 rounds of the championship (in the first post, the championship was still in its 29th round). <br/><br/> It's worth noting that we'll continue to focus our analysis on the players selected using the criteria explained in the <a href="https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2024/post_contratacoes_1_en/"> last post</a>: <b> Luiz Henrique </b> (Botafogo), <b> Felipe Anderson </b> (Palmeiras), <b> Gustavo Scarpa </b> (Atlético-MG), <b> Breno Lopes </b> (Fortaleza), <b> André Silva </b> (São Paulo), <b> Everton Ribeiro </b> (Bahia), <b> Gabriel Veron </b> (Cruzeiro), <b> David </b> (Vasco), <b> Soteldo </b> (Grêmio), <b> Wesley </b> (Internacional), <b> Rodrigo Garro </b> (Corinthians), <b> Yannick Bolasie </b> (Criciúma), <b> Lucas Barbosa </b> (Juventude) and <b> Gonzalo Mastriani </b> (Athletico). <br/><br/> In addition, we decided to include and focus the analysis on three more players who stood out during the year and fit the criteria used: <b> Alerrandro </b> (Vitória), <b> Memphis Depay </b> (Corinthians) and <b> Kevin Serna </b> (Fluminense). Finally, the players used for comparison will also be the same as in the last post and will be represented in yellow, while the signings will be represented in blue. <br/><br/> <h3> <b> Decisive goals and assists </b> </h3> To begin with, let's try to quantify the decision-making power of these players. To do this, we'll use the decisive goal participations metric, which counts <b> goals or assists that happened while the game was tied or while the player's team was losing by one goal </b>. <br/><br/> In the following graph, the red bar represents the number of decisive goal participations, while the blue bubble represents the number of total participations. <br/><br/> <div style="width: 100%; margin: 0 auto; text-align: center;"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2024-12-16-post_contratacoes_2/decisiveGoalsAssists.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <center>Graph 1. Decisive goal participations in red, and total goal participations in blue <br/><br/></center> - One player stands out in a very negative way: <b> Felipe Anderson </b> (Palmeiras). Especially for a player who came straight from one of Europe's big five leagues, a single decisive goal in 14 minutes can be considered a disappointing result. <br/><br/> - <b> Alerrandro </b> was one of the highlights of the Brasileirão. As well as being top scorer (tied with Corinthians' <b> Yuri Alberto </b>), he was extremely decisive for Vitória (especially in the final stretch, when he scored 8 decisive goals in the last 9 rounds), who finished in 11th place. <br/><br/> If we also take into account the number of minutes played, dividing the number of participations in goals by the number of games (90 minutes), the ranking changes shape a little, leaving room for new observations: <br/><br/> <div style="width: 100%; margin: 0 auto; text-align: center;"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2024-12-16-post_contratacoes_2/decisivePer90.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <center> Graph 2. Decisive participations in goals per 90 minutes in red, and total participations in goals per 90 minutes in blue <br/><br/></center> - From this graph, you can see the impact of <b> Memphis Depay </b>, from Corinthians, much more clearly. He was the signing with the most decisive appearances per game, as well as having an impressive 0.9 goals per game. It's worth noting that, after round 27 (<b> Memphis </b>' debut), Corinthians had won 28 out of a possible 33 points (84% points!). <br/><br/> - Even taking into account the ratio of decisive goals to minutes on the field, <b> Alerrandro </b> (24!) continues to lead the statistics among the selected signings, scoring approximately 1 decisive goal every two matches. <br/><br/> - Another player worth mentioning is <b> Kevin Serna </b>, from Fluminense. The Colombian arrived in the mid-year transfer window and was essential to his team's escape from relegation, scoring an average of one decisive goal every two matches. It's also worth mentioning that all of the Colombian's goal participations were decisive. <br/><br/> <h3> <b> General Analysis </b> </h3> In the graphs below, we have used the same model used in the first part of the series of posts. However, we've updated the data and also added the other players who fit the criteria to be selected (<b> Alerrandro </b>, <b> Memphis Depay </b> and <b> Kevin Serna </b>). <br/><br/> <div style="width: 100%; margin: 0 auto; text-align: center;"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2024-12-16-post_contratacoes_2/totalShotsper90_vs_xGper90.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <center> Graph 3. Total Shots per 90 minutes x Expected Goals per 90 minutes <br/><br/></center> - <b> Memphis Depay </b> is one of the players with the most shots per game in the league. However, it's interesting to note that this high number of shots is not reflected in expected goals. One interpretation is that <b> Memphis </b>, being a player with well above-average technical quality, attempts a lot of shots from outside the box or in difficult conditions, thus not accumulating a high number of expected goals. <br/><br/> - On the other hand, <b> Alerrandro </b> accumulates an average of expected goals per game very similar to <b> Memphis Depay </b>, even though he shoots considerably less, indicating less risk-taking and opting to shoot only when he is in clearer scoring conditions. In addition to this difference in characteristics, the positioning of the players on the pitch also influences this different behavior: <b> Alerrandro </b> is a center forward by trade, while <b> Memphis </b> is a second striker, forming attacking duos. <br/><br/> <div style="width: 100%; margin: 0 auto; text-align: center;"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2024-12-16-post_contratacoes_2/xg_vs_goals.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <center> Graph 4. Goals per 90 minutes vs. Expected Goals per 90 minutes <br/><br/></center> - Once again, we have to mention <b> Memphis Depay </b> as an individual highlight. Among the players considered (minutes equivalent to at least 8 games), <b> Memphis </b> was the second player with the most goals per game (as a matter of curiosity, the first was <b> Eduardo Vargas </b>, from Atlético-MG). However, it's not just the number of goals per game that's impressive, but also the player's efficiency. <b> Memphis </b> had 0.44 expected goals/game and 0.79 goals/game (almost double!). <br/><br/> - <b> André Silva </b>, from São Paulo, also deserves a mention. Despite initially being signed as a backup for the already established <b> Jonathan Calleri </b>, the Brazilian finished the league with more goals, even though he had fewer expected goals (taking into account the players' minutes), showing, at least in a quick analysis, that he was a more efficient striker than the Argentine. <br/><br/> <h2> <b> Conclusion </b></h2> In summary, this second part of the post shows a little more about the impact of some signings in the attacking sector of Brazilian soccer. While some stood out in an extremely positive way, such as <b> Memphis Depay </b> and <b> Alerrandro </b>, being decisive and essential to their respective teams' campaigns, other players didn't have the expected effect, such as <b> Felipe Anderson </b>, from Palmeiras. <br/><br/> Furthermore, our analysis showed that the simplest metrics we used, although useful in many contexts, have limitations in capturing the full impact of certain players. In order to understand the real impact of players like <b> Everton Ribeiro </b> and <b> Luiz Henrique </b>, for example, who have been essential to their teams, it is necessary to combine different types of metrics that consider different contexts, and it is also recommended to use other types of data, such as event data. In this way, we can evaluate not only direct production in raw numbers, but also less obvious (but no less important) contributions, such as playmaking and tactical influence. <br/><br/> <div> </div></div>]]></content><author><name>Ace Laboratory Football Team - Daniel Barros, Hugo Antunes</name></author><category term="Football;"/><category term="Analysis"/><category term="Football;"/><category term="Analysis"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Analyzing Brazilian Football Signings in 2024 - Offensive Sector</title><link href="https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2024/post_contratacoes_1_en/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Analyzing Brazilian Football Signings in 2024 - Offensive Sector"/><published>2024-10-10T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-10-10T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2024/post_contratacoes_1_en</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2024/post_contratacoes_1_en/"><![CDATA[<hr/> <p align="justify"> Se quiser ler este texto em pt-br, <a href="https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2000/post_contratacoes_1_pt/"> clique aqui.</a> </p> <h2><b>Introduction </b></h2> <div style="text-align: justify"> In this series of posts, we'll bring you statistics on the main signings made by teams in Brazil's Serie A! To do this, we've separated the players into sectors: attack, midfield and defense. In this first post, we'll talk about the attackers that Brazilian clubs have invested (some of them a lot of) money in. For a better comparison, we've also chosen to showcase some players who aren't 2024 signings, precisely to compare the new players with others already established in Brazilian soccer. <br/><br/> <h3> <b> The signings </b> </h3> Our criteria for selecting players was to choose the player recruited in 2024 with the most minutes in the team for each sector (with a minimum minute equivalent to 8 matches), prioritizing teams that have greater purchasing power and have made more significant signings in the elite of Brazilian soccer. The players selected for the attacking sector were: <b>Luiz Henrique</b> (Botafogo), <b>Felipe Anderson</b> (Palmeiras), <b>Gustavo Scarpa</b> (Atlético-MG), <b>Breno Lopes</b> (Fortaleza), <b>André Silva</b> (São Paulo), <b>Everton Ribeiro</b> (Bahia), <b>Gabriel Veron</b> (Cruzeiro), <b>David</b> (Vasco), <b>Soteldo</b> (Grêmio), <b>Wesley</b> (Internacional), <b>Rodrigo Garro</b> (Corinthians), <b>Yannick Bolasie</b> (Criciúma), <b>Lucas Barbosa</b> (Juventude) and <b>Gonzalo Mastriani</b> (Athletico). <br/><br/> Some clubs haven't made any signings in the attacking sector, while others have, but the signings haven't played more than the equivalent of 8 matches. In both cases, there is no player representing the team in the comparison. <br/><br/> <h3> <b> Analysis and Comparison of the New Players </b> </h3> The data used for this analysis refers exclusively to the Brazilian Championship, covering matches up to the 29th round. It is worth noting that, due to postponements, not all teams have played 29 matches. <br/><br/> To begin the analysis, we will use two graphs which, although similar in scope, offer different perspectives. The first graph relates the number of shots to the expected goals, providing an insight into the <b>quantity and quality of chances that players receive</b>, on average, per match. The second graph relates expected goals (xG) to goals scored, making it easier to analyze <b>how players take advantage of the chances created</b>. In both graphs (and the third one too), the players signed this season are represented in cyan, while the green dots indicate players used as references. <br/><br/> The first graph shows average lines on both axes, which helps to identify players who are above or below average in each metric, dividing the graph into four quadrants. In the Goals vs. xG graph, a single line was used, dividing the graph into two quadrants: above the line are the players who scored more goals than expected; below the line, those who scored less than expected. <br/><br/> <div style="width: 100%; margin: 0 auto; text-align: center;"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2024-10-10-post_contratacoes/shots_vs_xg.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <center>Graph 1. xG per 90 x Shots Per 90<br/><br/></center> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2024-10-10-post_contratacoes/xg_vs_goals.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <center>Graph 2. Goals per 90 x xG per 90 <br/><br/></center> <ul> <li> <p>Among the players signed this season, <b>Gonzalo Mastriani** and <b>Yannick Bolasie</b> stand out in terms of the number of shots and goals expected. Their statistics in these metrics are similar to those of other players who can be considered the main finishers for their respective teams, such as <b>Hulk<b>, <b>Pablo Vegetti</b> and <b>José López</b> (Flaco López). <br/><br/></b></b></b></p> </li> <li> <p>It’s also worth highlighting the efficiency of São Paulo’s center forward, <b>André Silva</b>. Although he doesn’t have a very high number of expected shots and goals, he stands out in the number of goals scored, being the player furthest away from the middle line and can therefore be considered the “most efficient” of the signings shown. <br/><br/></p> </li> <li> <p>In contrast, <b>Everton Ribeiro</b> has low values in these metrics directly related to finishing moves. This highlights a big difference between him and the rest of the strikers being compared. <b>Everton Ribeiro</b>, as we’ll see later, is not a player marked by direct participation in finishing moves, but rather in constructing them. In the graph, he is in the bottom left quadrant, which suggests that he plays a lesser role in both shooting and scoring goals in a match. <br/><br/></p> </li> <li> <p>Although it’s not the main focus of this analysis, it’s important to mention young <b>Estevão</b>, from Palmeiras. Although he is not a new signing, he “emerged” in the elite of Brazilian soccer in 2024. Despite not being a center-forward, he is one of the players who finishes the most, as well as accumulating high numbers of expected goals and goals per game. That’s impressive, considering he’s only <b>17 years old</b> and is in his debut season in the league. <br/><br/></p> </li> </ul> <p>Finally, we chose another graph to visualize participation with the ball and the number of passes in the final third of the pitch. The interesting thing about this visualization is that we were able to ‘divide’ the players into three groups, where it’s possible to understand why the player belongs to each group according to their individual and team characteristics. <br/><br/></p> <div style="width: 100%; margin: 0 auto; text-align: center;"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2024-10-10-post_contratacoes/passes_vs_touches.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <center>Graph 3. Accurate Final Third Passes per 90 x Touches per 90<br/><br/></center> <ul> <li> <p>The center forwards, such as <b>Yannick Bolasie</b>, <b>Gonzalo Mastriani</b> and <b>André Silva</b>, are below average both in terms of the number of touches they get on the ball and the number of correct passes in the final third. This isn’t necessarily a demerit, but a characteristic of the role. Center forwards tend to receive the ball less than most other players, and when they do, they’re often put under a lot of pressure, which increases the chance of a misplaced pass. <br/><br/></p> </li> <li> <p>On the other hand, attacking players who are more constructive, such as <b>Rodrigo Garro</b>, <b>Gustavo Scarpa</b> and <b>Everton Ribeiro</b>, are above average in these two metrics. <b>Everton Ribeiro</b>, in particular, stands out from the rest, both because of his individual characteristics and because of the way Bahia uses him. The team sees him as a key player in the offensive progression, taking advantage of his superior technical quality, which makes him the main player in the construction of plays and participation with the ball. <br/><br/></p> </li> <li> <p>Located on the graph between these two groups are the players most characterized by dribbling, such as <b>Wesley</b>, <b>Luiz Henrique</b>, <b>Lucas Barbosa</b> and <b>David</b>. The interpretation is that, despite having a number of touches and passes in the final third close to the average, these players progress in a different way to the builders. They prefer to advance with the ball through quick and, in some cases, long carries. In addition, they tend to be more involved in finishing off moves, which is why they often don’t receive the ball back in the same move after receiving it.</p> </li> </ul> <h2> <b>Conclusion</b> </h2> <p>In summary, the attacking signings of Serie A clubs in 2024 reveal different player profiles, reflecting the specific characteristics of each team and their tactical needs. While central strikers such as <b>Bolasie</b> and <b>Mastriani</b> stand out for their finishing, although with less involvement in the build-up play, more creative and constructive players such as <b>Rodrigo Garro</b> and <b>Everton Ribeiro</b> play a key role in attacking progression. On the other hand, players who focus on dribbling, such as <b>Wesley</b> and <b>Luiz Henrique</b>, take a different approach, with a greater emphasis on carrying and dribbling. These distinctions reveal how the teams function differently, whether because of economic reality, the rest of the squad, or the choice of the coaching staff. <br/><br/></p> <div> </div>]]></content><author><name>Ace Laboratory Football Team - Daniel Barros, Hugo Antunes</name></author><category term="Football;"/><category term="Analysis"/><category term="Football;"/><category term="Analysis"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Se quiser ler este texto em pt-br, clique aqui. Introduction In this series of posts, we'll bring you statistics on the main signings made by teams in Brazil's Serie A! To do this, we've separated the players into sectors: attack, midfield and defense. In this first post, we'll talk about the attackers that Brazilian clubs have invested (some of them a lot of) money in. For a better comparison, we've also chosen to showcase some players who aren't 2024 signings, precisely to compare the new players with others already established in Brazilian soccer. The signings Our criteria for selecting players was to choose the player recruited in 2024 with the most minutes in the team for each sector (with a minimum minute equivalent to 8 matches), prioritizing teams that have greater purchasing power and have made more significant signings in the elite of Brazilian soccer. The players selected for the attacking sector were: Luiz Henrique (Botafogo), Felipe Anderson (Palmeiras), Gustavo Scarpa (Atlético-MG), Breno Lopes (Fortaleza), André Silva (São Paulo), Everton Ribeiro (Bahia), Gabriel Veron (Cruzeiro), David (Vasco), Soteldo (Grêmio), Wesley (Internacional), Rodrigo Garro (Corinthians), Yannick Bolasie (Criciúma), Lucas Barbosa (Juventude) and Gonzalo Mastriani (Athletico). Some clubs haven't made any signings in the attacking sector, while others have, but the signings haven't played more than the equivalent of 8 matches. In both cases, there is no player representing the team in the comparison. Analysis and Comparison of the New Players The data used for this analysis refers exclusively to the Brazilian Championship, covering matches up to the 29th round. It is worth noting that, due to postponements, not all teams have played 29 matches. To begin the analysis, we will use two graphs which, although similar in scope, offer different perspectives. The first graph relates the number of shots to the expected goals, providing an insight into the quantity and quality of chances that players receive, on average, per match. The second graph relates expected goals (xG) to goals scored, making it easier to analyze how players take advantage of the chances created. In both graphs (and the third one too), the players signed this season are represented in cyan, while the green dots indicate players used as references. The first graph shows average lines on both axes, which helps to identify players who are above or below average in each metric, dividing the graph into four quadrants. In the Goals vs. xG graph, a single line was used, dividing the graph into two quadrants: above the line are the players who scored more goals than expected; below the line, those who scored less than expected. Graph 1. xG per 90 x Shots Per 90 Graph 2. Goals per 90 x xG per 90 Among the players signed this season, Gonzalo Mastriani** and Yannick Bolasie stand out in terms of the number of shots and goals expected. Their statistics in these metrics are similar to those of other players who can be considered the main finishers for their respective teams, such as Hulk, Pablo Vegetti and José López (Flaco López). It’s also worth highlighting the efficiency of São Paulo’s center forward, André Silva. Although he doesn’t have a very high number of expected shots and goals, he stands out in the number of goals scored, being the player furthest away from the middle line and can therefore be considered the “most efficient” of the signings shown. In contrast, Everton Ribeiro has low values in these metrics directly related to finishing moves. This highlights a big difference between him and the rest of the strikers being compared. Everton Ribeiro, as we’ll see later, is not a player marked by direct participation in finishing moves, but rather in constructing them. In the graph, he is in the bottom left quadrant, which suggests that he plays a lesser role in both shooting and scoring goals in a match. Although it’s not the main focus of this analysis, it’s important to mention young Estevão, from Palmeiras. Although he is not a new signing, he “emerged” in the elite of Brazilian soccer in 2024. Despite not being a center-forward, he is one of the players who finishes the most, as well as accumulating high numbers of expected goals and goals per game. That’s impressive, considering he’s only 17 years old and is in his debut season in the league. Finally, we chose another graph to visualize participation with the ball and the number of passes in the final third of the pitch. The interesting thing about this visualization is that we were able to ‘divide’ the players into three groups, where it’s possible to understand why the player belongs to each group according to their individual and team characteristics. Graph 3. Accurate Final Third Passes per 90 x Touches per 90 The center forwards, such as Yannick Bolasie, Gonzalo Mastriani and André Silva, are below average both in terms of the number of touches they get on the ball and the number of correct passes in the final third. This isn’t necessarily a demerit, but a characteristic of the role. Center forwards tend to receive the ball less than most other players, and when they do, they’re often put under a lot of pressure, which increases the chance of a misplaced pass. On the other hand, attacking players who are more constructive, such as Rodrigo Garro, Gustavo Scarpa and Everton Ribeiro, are above average in these two metrics. Everton Ribeiro, in particular, stands out from the rest, both because of his individual characteristics and because of the way Bahia uses him. The team sees him as a key player in the offensive progression, taking advantage of his superior technical quality, which makes him the main player in the construction of plays and participation with the ball. Located on the graph between these two groups are the players most characterized by dribbling, such as Wesley, Luiz Henrique, Lucas Barbosa and David. The interpretation is that, despite having a number of touches and passes in the final third close to the average, these players progress in a different way to the builders. They prefer to advance with the ball through quick and, in some cases, long carries. In addition, they tend to be more involved in finishing off moves, which is why they often don’t receive the ball back in the same move after receiving it. Conclusion In summary, the attacking signings of Serie A clubs in 2024 reveal different player profiles, reflecting the specific characteristics of each team and their tactical needs. While central strikers such as Bolasie and Mastriani stand out for their finishing, although with less involvement in the build-up play, more creative and constructive players such as Rodrigo Garro and Everton Ribeiro play a key role in attacking progression. On the other hand, players who focus on dribbling, such as Wesley and Luiz Henrique, take a different approach, with a greater emphasis on carrying and dribbling. These distinctions reveal how the teams function differently, whether because of economic reality, the rest of the squad, or the choice of the coaching staff.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Analysis of the Best Football Leagues</title><link href="https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2024/post_analise_ligas_en/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Analysis of the Best Football Leagues"/><published>2024-09-22T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-09-22T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2024/post_analise_ligas_en</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2024/post_analise_ligas_en/"><![CDATA[<hr/> <p align="justify"> Se quiser ler este texto em pt-br, <a href="https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2000/post_analise_ligas_pt/"> clique aqui. </a> </p> <div style="text-align: justify"> <h2>Introduction</h2> In today’s post, we decided to touch on a topic that is discussed every year: What is the best league in the world? Does the Brasileirão belong among these leagues? We will analyze everything from the total Market Value to each league's performance in international competitions. The leagues studied were: Premier League (England), La Liga (Spain), Ligue 1 (France), Bundesliga (Germany), Serie A (Italy), and Brasileirão (Brazil). The international tournaments studied were the Copa Libertadores (CONMEBOL), Copa Sulamericana (CONMEBOL), Champions League (UEFA) and Europa League (UEFA). <br/><br/> <h2> <b>Research</b> </h2> The data used in this research were collected from Transfermarkt, which provides market values for each team in the leagues studied per season; Sofascore, with the final standings of each season; UEFA, with the results from the Champions League and Europa League; and CONMEBOL, with the results from the Copa Libertadores and Copa Sulamericana. The last five years were taken into consideration: for European teams, the seasons from 2019-2020 to 2023-2024, and for Brazilian teams, from 2019 to 2023. Scripts were used to extract data from Transfermarkt and Sofascore. <br/><br/> <h2> <b>Market Value</b> </h2> The following bar chart shows the total Market Value of the teams by league and by season. In the case of the Brasileirão, 19-20 refers to the 2019 season, 20-21 refers to the 2020 season, and so on. <br/><br/> <div style="width: 100%; margin: 0 auto; text-align: center;"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2024-09-22-post_analise_ligas/marketvalue.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <center>Image 1. Market Value of Leagues in the last 5 seasons<br/><br/></center> The difference between the Premier League and the other leagues is enormous, and the growth in market value per season is exponential. The financial model of team ownership in England may influence this, as many of the top English teams are owned by billionaires who inject money for signings. The model for distributing broadcast rights revenues also contributes to this high value, with hundreds of millions of pounds being distributed almost equally among the clubs. <br/><br/> Among the other European leagues, there isn’t much variation between seasons or among them. When comparing the European leagues to the Brasileirão, the colossal difference can be explained by various factors, from the weakness of the Brazilian Real compared to the Euro to the early sale of promising Brazilian players to European teams, often motivated by poor management of Brazilian clubs, forcing teams to sell promising players to pay off large debts. <br/><br/> <h2> <b>Performance in Unequal Matches</b> </h2> Performance in Unequal Matches (PUM) measures a team's performance in games against opponents whose market value is lower. The formula to calculate PUM is simple: divide the number of points won in these matches by the total points disputed. <br/><br/> Now that we understand what PUM is, let’s explain why it is useful. Our goal is to evaluate whether economically dominant teams also show sporting superiority, as they have better squads and infrastructure compared to their opponents in the leagues. <br/><br/> <div style="width: 100%; margin: 0 auto; text-align: center;"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2024-09-22-post_analise_ligas/graficoACD.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <center>Image 2. Average PUM chart for leagues in the last 5 seasons<br/><br/></center> Based on the chart showing the average PUM per season in each analyzed championship, we notice that, in the Brasileirão, performance in unequal matches is the lowest among the six leagues. This indicates that teams with lower market value can compete more evenly against the top national clubs. In the Premier League and Bundesliga, the trend is the opposite, with higher market value teams having a significantly higher average performance compared to the other leagues. <br/><br/> <h2> <b>International Competitions</b> </h2> The following tables show the number of defeats of Brazilian clubs by stage in the Copa Libertadores and Copa Sulamericana over the last 5 seasons. <br/><br/> <h3> <b>Copa Libertadores</b></h3> Brazil's dominance in the biggest club competition in South America is undeniable. In the last five finals, all featured Brazilian teams, three were entirely Brazilian, and five titles went to Brazil. The technical level difference between Brazil's top clubs and other South American teams can be attributed to several factors. Besides other countries being smaller and poorer than Brazil, some are going through major economic crises, such as Argentina, the country with the most titles in the "Glória Eterna" tournament. But Brazil has dominated in recent years, and the trend is likely to continue. Another possible analysis is the large number of talents exported from "smaller" Latin American countries to high-level Brazilian football, weakening their leagues' competitiveness against Brazilian giants. <br/><br/> <div style="width: 100%; margin: 0 auto; text-align: center;"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2024-09-22-post_analise_ligas/tabelaliba.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <center>Image 3. Number of Brazilian teams per stage of Libertadores by year<br/><br/></center> <h3> <b>Copa Sulamericana</b></h3> In the Copa Sulamericana, the scenario is different: in the last five finals, Brazil has "only" one title and three participations (with one all-Brazilian final). Why is this different from Libertadores? Could the large number of spots given to Brasileirão teams mean that weaker and less experienced teams are playing and losing early? However, this scheme may be about to change. Since 2019, the number of Brazilian clubs dropping out in the group stage has significantly decreased, replaced by later-stage eliminations. Additionally, since the all-Brazilian final in 2021, Brazil has participated in every final, although without further titles. <br/><br/> <div style="width: 100%; margin: 0 auto; text-align: center;"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2024-09-22-post_analise_ligas/tabelasula.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <center>Image 4. Number of Brazilian teams per stage of Sulamericana by year<br/><br/></center> The fact is: in the last five seasons, Brazil has won six titles in South America’s main international competitions. But what is the situation in Europe? <br/><br/> The following tables show the number of defeats of European clubs from the mentioned leagues by stage in the Champions League and Europa League over the last 5 seasons. <h3> <b>Champions League</b></h3> In the Champions League, France and Italy did not win titles, but had two runner-up finishes. What differentiates them from the winning leagues? France had the fewest teams reaching the round of 16 and fewer total participations, with only two teams making the semifinals: Lyon and PSG (twice). Italy had the most eliminations in the round of 16, with poor performance overall. Another interesting observation: Spain had a 100% success rate in finals, winning both in which they participated. England, however, had an extraordinary performance: two titles and two runner-up finishes, with one all-English final. In other words, they had the best performance, appearing in 3 out of 5 finals. <br/><br/> <div style="width: 100%; margin: 0 auto; text-align: center;"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2024-09-22-post_analise_ligas/tabelachamp.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <center>Image 5. Number of teams from each country by stage in the UCL in the last 5 years<br/><br/></center> <h3> <b>Europa League</b></h3> In the Europa League, the scenario changes: Spain dominated the period with a 100% success rate in finals, reaching three finals and winning all three. Once again, France had the fewest participations in the competition. Only three French teams made it past the group stage. Italy reached three finals but managed to win only one. Germany’s numbers are similar in both competitions, with nothing standing out. The biggest difference between the competitions is in England’s performance: in the Europa League, the English only reached one final and were runners-up. <br/><br/> <div style="width: 100%; margin: 0 auto; text-align: center;"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2024-09-22-post_analise_ligas/tabelaeuro.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <center>Image 6. Number of teams from each country by stage in the UEL in the last 5 years<br/><br/></center> <br/><br/> <h2> <b>Discussion</b> </h2> From the above analysis, we will combine all this information to try to answer the question from the introduction: "What is the best league in the world?" This question carries a degree of subjectivity, as it depends on what you want to observe in a league. <br/><br/> Looking at the most valuable league in the world, the choice would be the Premier League, with a value greater than 12 billion euros in the last season, which has been growing exponentially year after year. <br/><br/> In terms of Performance in Unequal Matches, the Brazilian league shows a low average PUM, indicating that lower market value teams can compete more equally and win more points against richer clubs. This results in more unpredictable championships and, consequently, more competitiveness. <br/><br/> When observing the performance of countries in international competitions, it becomes more subjective. In South America, Brazil is dominant, with 6 titles won in the last five years, 5 of them in the toughest competition in the Americas. In Europe, there is a greater variety of champions: only France failed to win a title. Spain won the most titles (5), and England ties with Spain in finals appearances (5 out of 10). <br/><br/> <h2> <b>Conclusion</b> </h2> Which is the best league in the world? It depends on the point of view. European leagues have a higher market value, meaning they have the best players and coaches, resulting in higher-quality matches. However, the unpredictability of the matches is lower and, in a way, less exciting. In the Brazilian league, we can see that the lower average PUM provides greater unpredictability, which brings excitement to the championship. This unpredictability is likely related to player quality, which affects the quality of the games. Therefore, answering the question about which league is the best depends on the fan’s perspective. <br/><br/> Thank you for reading and stay tuned for future posts! <br/><br/> <div> </div></div>]]></content><author><name>Ace Laboratory Football Team - Lucas Calmon, Pedro Carvalho</name></author><category term="Football;"/><category term="Analysis"/><category term="Football;"/><category term="Analysis"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">2023 Women’s World Cup - Analyzing the progress of the Brazilian national team</title><link href="https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2024/post_women_world_cup_4_en/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="2023 Women’s World Cup - Analyzing the progress of the Brazilian national team"/><published>2024-09-05T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-09-05T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2024/post_women_world_cup_4_en</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2024/post_women_world_cup_4_en/"><![CDATA[<hr/> <p align="justify"> Se quiser ler este texto em pt-br, <a href="https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2000/post_women_world_cup_4_pt/"> clique aqui. </a> </p> <div style="text-align: justify"> In this post, we're going to analyse the Brazilian national team's campaigns in the last two World Cups. The aim is to find out whether or not there has been any kind of evolution in the Brazilian team, and to understand what level the team was at in those competitions, both in the global and continental context. To do this, we're going to compare Brazil with the teams featured in the last post (Spain, the United States, Sweden and England) and with other South American teams (Argentina, Colombia in 2023, Chile in 2019).<br/><br/> <h2> <b>Overview</b> </h2> <h3> <b>2019 World Cup</b> </h3> At the 2019 World Cup, the Brazilian team was seeded in a group with Australia, Italy and Jamaica. Their performance in the group stage was good: 2 wins in 3 games, scoring 6 goals and conceding 3 during the first phase. Despite their good run, Brazil progressed to the knockout stage in third place after a triple draw in Group C (the place was won on the basis of the best third-placed team).<br/><br/> In the Round of 16, Brazil faced France in a very tight game. Despite a balance in possession during regulation time, the Brazilians had 12 shots, while the French had 5. The match was only decided in the second half of overtime, when France scored the winning goal and ended Brazil's participation in the competition.<br/><br/> <h3> <b>2023 World Cup</b> </h3> At the 2023 World Cup, Brazil had an even shorter and more frustrating campaign. Once again, the Brazilian team finished third, now in Group F, which included France, Jamaica and Panama. The Brazilians won one and drew one in three games, but in this edition, only the top two teams in the group qualified for the knockout stage.<br/><br/> When we say that the campaign was frustrating, it was not for nothing. On the final matchday of the group stage, Brazil only needed a simple win against Jamaica, an opponent who qualified with a single goal against Panama (who conceded 11 in the competition). In theory, qualification seemed on course. In practice, Brazil, despite a giant dominance when we analyse possession, the number of passes and shots, were unable to make satisfactory use of the many chances that were created. The result could not have been any other: 0-0, and the Brazilian team was eliminated in the first phase of the competition.<br/><br/> <div style="width: 100%; margin: 0 auto; text-align: center;"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2024-09-05-post_women_world_cup_4/Shotmap.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <h2> <b>Statistics between Cups</b> </h2> In this section, we're going to analyse Brazil's participation using different scatter plots. The idea is to be able to compare both the evolution (or regression) from one World Cup to the next, as well as a general comparison between the campaigns of other teams.<br/><br/> Before starting the analyses and comments section, we have to say that, because the World Cup is a short tournament (and, unfortunately, the Brazilian team's campaigns even shorter), some matches end up having a big impact on the metrics shown below. This context must be taken into account when analysing.<br/><br/> <h2> <b>Passes and Progression</b> </h2> <div style="width: 100%; margin: 0 auto; text-align: center;"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2024-09-05-post_women_world_cup_4/Passes.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> Analysing the passes and progression of the 2019 Brazilian team, you can see the low number of progressive passes per match, which is considerably below average. In 2019, the team made an average of approximately 40 progressive passes per match, about 20% less than the average of the other teams. Furthermore, there has been a noticeable improvement from the 2019 World Cup to the 2023 World Cup, with Brazil being one of the best teams in this regard.<br/><br/> - Brazil's opponents in South America are not well placed on the graph, either in relation to the main European teams or in relation to Brazil.<br/><br/> - In 2023, Brazil improved in both aspects, with around 30 progressive drives and almost 70 progressive passes per game, revealing a significant evolution, with the team assuming a more aggressive and progressive profile on the pitch compared to the much less offensive behaviour of the team in 2019. In the 2019 campaign, Brazil made approximately 20% fewer progressive passes than the average of the other teams.<br/><br/> <h2> <b>Shots and xG per shot</b> </h2> <div style="width: 100%; margin: 0 auto; text-align: center;"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2024-09-05-post_women_world_cup_4/Shots.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> To analyse the quality of the teams' shots, we'll use the graph of shots per match vs. xG per shot.<br/><br/> - Once again, Brazil are better placed than their South American opponents, indicating that there is a big advantage for the Brazilian national team on their continent.<br/><br/> - Despite a much higher number of shots per match in 2023, Brazil have not seen a considerable improvement in the quality of their chances (expected goals per shot). The lack of progress in this area was, as we said, a determining factor in Brazil's elimination in the group stage.<br/><br/> - As we've already mentioned, the fact that the World Cup is a short tournament means that some matches have a big impact on the statistics. In this graph, we have a clear example of this in the number of shots that the Brazilian national team produced. In the second round of the group stage, against Panama, Brazil shot 33 times, scoring 4 goals on the occasion. This number of shots is greater than the sum of the shots in the other two matches, showing that the match against Panama creates a false impression that the Brazilian team had the characteristic of shooting often, but that this was an isolated episode in the competition.<br/><br/> <h2> <b>Final considerations and conclusion</b></h2> The graphs show that Brazil have had considerably better campaigns than their rivals in South America, but their main opponents in Europe and North America (who have a much more established national women's football scene) still have a big advantage.<br/><br/> Even though the campaigns analysed were short and, in some ways, disappointing, Brazil made great progress after 2023. In 2024, the Brazilian team, now led by coach Arthur Elias, won the silver medal at the Olympic Games in Paris, revealing important new players to the team, such as goalkeeper Lorena and defender Tarciane.<br/><br/> And so ends our series of posts analysing the 2023 Women's World Cup. Stay tuned, there's lots more to come!<br/><br/> <div> </div></div>]]></content><author><name>Ace Laboratory Football Team - Daniel Barros, Hugo Antunes</name></author><category term="Football;"/><category term="Analysis"/><category term="Football;"/><category term="Analysis"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">2023 Women’s World Cup - Analyzing the evolution of the main teams</title><link href="https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2024/post_women_world_cup_3_en/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="2023 Women’s World Cup - Analyzing the evolution of the main teams"/><published>2024-08-22T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-08-22T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2024/post_women_world_cup_3_en</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2024/post_women_world_cup_3_en/"><![CDATA[<hr/> <p align="justify"> Se quiser ler este texto em pt-br, <a href="https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2000/post_women_world_cup_3_pt/"> clique aqui. </a> </p> <h2><b>Introduction</b></h2> <div style="text-align: justify"> In this post, we will analyze the evolution of the teams in the Women's World Cup, comparing the performance of the main teams in the 2019 and 2023 World Cups. The teams analyzed will be: <b>Spain</b>, the current champions; <b>England</b>, the current vice-champions; the <b>United States</b>, champions in 2019 and <b>Sweden</b>, who finished third in the last two editions. <br/><br/> <h2> <b>Retrospect</b> </h2> <h3> <b>Spain</b> </h3> After winning the 2023 World Cup, Spain have established themselves as one of the<b> best teams in international football</b>. With an excellent campaign in the last edition, they won the title in a final against England (these two teams were the subject of the <a href="https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2024/post_women_world_cup_1_en/"> first post of our series</a>). <br/><br/> In 2019, though, Spain's situation was very different. <b>With fewer established players and without several of the young players who made a difference in 2023</b>, such as Salma Paralluelo, Spain got through the group stage via goal difference, with a below-average campaign (1W, 1D, 1L). In the round of 16, <b>they were eliminated by the United States</b>, winners of that edition. <br/><br/> <h3> <b>England</b> </h3> <b>England have performed well in the last two World Cups</b>. In 2019, they finished in fourth place, losing to Sweden after losing in the semi-finals to the United States, who won that edition. In addition, as we mentioned, England are the current vice-champions of the world, defeated in the final by Spain. <br/><br/> In 2019, despite falling into a tough group with Japan, Argentina and Scotland, they didn't face much difficulty and came out on top with 3 wins in 3 games. In the knockout stage, they were only defeated in the semi-finals 2-1 in a match against the United States. <br/><br/> <h3> <b>United States</b> </h3> At the 2019 World Cup, <b>the United States won their fourth world title</b> (they also won 1991, 1999 and 2015), their second in a row, in a final against Netherlands. In this edition, the US broke a record that still stands today: <b>the team with the most goals in a World Cup (26!)</b>. <br/><br/> However, at the 2023 World Cup, the United States were eliminated in the round of 16 in a penalty shootout against Sweden. This campaign can be considered frustrating and was marked by a big decline in the performance of the United States attack (we'll see why in the following analysis). <br/><br/> <h3> <b>Sweden</b> </h3> <b>Sweden has done well in recent World Cups</b>. In 2019, they won third place, having eliminated strong teams like <b>Germany</b> and <b>Argentina</b> in the knockout stage. In this edition, Sweden only lost to the two finalists: the United States (in the group stage) and the Netherlands (in the semi-final). <br/><br/> In 2023, Sweden repeated their 2019 campaign and managed to win third place again. This time, they only lost one match (against champion Spain in the semi-final) out of the seven they played. In the match for third place, Sweden beat Australia 2-0. <br/><br/> <h2> <b>Comparison of World Cup campaigns</b> </h2> In this section, we will analyze the teams using different scatter graphs. The idea is to be able to compare both the evolution (or decline) of a team from one Cup to the next, as well as a general comparison between all the campaigns of the teams mentioned so far. <br/><br/> <h3> <b>Passes and Progression</b> </h3> First, it's important to mention that we've updated our definition of progressive action compared to the last post. <br/><br/> <b>Definition of progressive passing:</b> Actions in the first 30% of the pitch are ignored. They must reduce the distance from the ball to the center of the opponent's goal by at least <b>20%</b>. Only successful passes that are completed closer to the opponent's goal vertically or that have their end point inside the opponent's penalty area are counted. <br/><br/> <div style="width: 100%; margin: 0 auto; text-align: center;"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2024-08-23-post_women_world_cup_3/passes_vs_progressive_passes.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <center>Graph showing passes per match and progressive passes per match<br/><br/></center> Looking at the passing and progression of these teams, there are a few points to highlight: <br/><br/> - It's important to highlight the difference in the amount of passes per game made by Spain in the two campaigns, with Spain 2023 being by far the <b>team with the most passes and progressive passes out of all the teams that played in the two World Cups</b>. This is a clear consolidation of the style of play based on <b>passing, possession and pressing</b> that is implemented in both the women's and men's national teams. <br/><br/> - All of these teams (consolidated on the national team scene) began to pass more in the transition from one World Cup to the next, with the exception of the United States. This may be a trend in women's international football: <b>passing and proposing the game are key factors for success</b>. <br/><br/> <h3> <b>Shots and Expected Goals </b></h3> <div style="width: 100%; margin: 0 auto; text-align: center;"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2024-08-23-post_women_world_cup_3/shots_vs_xg.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <center> Graph showing shots per match and expected goals per match <br/><br/></center> In this graph relating the number of shots per match to the xG accumulated per match ( excluding penalties), we have the following observations: <br/><br/> - Once again, Spain's evolution deserves to be highlighted. The team has made considerable improvements in attack, becoming the <b>team with the most shots and expected goals of all teams in the last two World Cups</b>. <br/><br/> - Despite a reasonable increase in shots, the United States had a decrease in their xG compared to 2019, indicating that the <b>team has, on average, decreased the quality of its scoring opportunities</b>. In addition, the team's attacking efficiency has also decreased dramatically. Disregarding penalties, the 2019 United States had a <b>positive balance of +8.63 (!!!) </b>in the difference between goals and xG. In 2023, the balance was<b> -3.01</b>. <br/><br/> - The England team of 2023, despite being a <b>highlight in terms of the number of passes and progressive passes</b>, doesn't have the same impact when it comes to finishing moves. Among the teams compared, they have the <b>fewest xG per game (1.26)</b>, reinforcing what we said in our first post when we commented that England 2023 had a very <b>methodical style of play</b>. Even with a good capacity for progression, the team doesn't take many shots and, consequently, doesn't accumulate many expected goals compared to the other top teams. <br/><br/> <h2> <b>Final Considerations and Conclusion</b></h2> Throughout this post, we've focused on comparing teams that are well-established on the women's football scenario (perhaps the least well-established of these is Spain in 2019, a fact that only magnifies their winning campaign in 2023). So it was only natural that all the teams, even with differences in play and style, would be <b>“well placed”</b> in the graphs shown. At least in the two graphs shown, the prediction actually came true, with <b>all 8 teams being above average in the 4 metrics used</b>. <br/><br/> This concludes another post in our series on the 2023 Women's World Cup, and the fourth post will be the last in the series. Stay tuned for future posts! <br/><br/> <div> </div></div>]]></content><author><name>Ace Laboratory Football Team - Daniel Barros, Hugo Antunes</name></author><category term="Football;"/><category term="Analysis"/><category term="Football;"/><category term="Analysis"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Se quiser ler este texto em pt-br, clique aqui. Introduction In this post, we will analyze the evolution of the teams in the Women's World Cup, comparing the performance of the main teams in the 2019 and 2023 World Cups. The teams analyzed will be: Spain, the current champions; England, the current vice-champions; the United States, champions in 2019 and Sweden, who finished third in the last two editions. Retrospect Spain After winning the 2023 World Cup, Spain have established themselves as one of the best teams in international football. With an excellent campaign in the last edition, they won the title in a final against England (these two teams were the subject of the first post of our series). In 2019, though, Spain's situation was very different. With fewer established players and without several of the young players who made a difference in 2023, such as Salma Paralluelo, Spain got through the group stage via goal difference, with a below-average campaign (1W, 1D, 1L). In the round of 16, they were eliminated by the United States, winners of that edition. England England have performed well in the last two World Cups. In 2019, they finished in fourth place, losing to Sweden after losing in the semi-finals to the United States, who won that edition. In addition, as we mentioned, England are the current vice-champions of the world, defeated in the final by Spain. In 2019, despite falling into a tough group with Japan, Argentina and Scotland, they didn't face much difficulty and came out on top with 3 wins in 3 games. In the knockout stage, they were only defeated in the semi-finals 2-1 in a match against the United States. United States At the 2019 World Cup, the United States won their fourth world title (they also won 1991, 1999 and 2015), their second in a row, in a final against Netherlands. In this edition, the US broke a record that still stands today: the team with the most goals in a World Cup (26!). However, at the 2023 World Cup, the United States were eliminated in the round of 16 in a penalty shootout against Sweden. This campaign can be considered frustrating and was marked by a big decline in the performance of the United States attack (we'll see why in the following analysis). Sweden Sweden has done well in recent World Cups. In 2019, they won third place, having eliminated strong teams like Germany and Argentina in the knockout stage. In this edition, Sweden only lost to the two finalists: the United States (in the group stage) and the Netherlands (in the semi-final). In 2023, Sweden repeated their 2019 campaign and managed to win third place again. This time, they only lost one match (against champion Spain in the semi-final) out of the seven they played. In the match for third place, Sweden beat Australia 2-0. Comparison of World Cup campaigns In this section, we will analyze the teams using different scatter graphs. The idea is to be able to compare both the evolution (or decline) of a team from one Cup to the next, as well as a general comparison between all the campaigns of the teams mentioned so far. Passes and Progression First, it's important to mention that we've updated our definition of progressive action compared to the last post. Definition of progressive passing: Actions in the first 30% of the pitch are ignored. They must reduce the distance from the ball to the center of the opponent's goal by at least 20%. Only successful passes that are completed closer to the opponent's goal vertically or that have their end point inside the opponent's penalty area are counted. Graph showing passes per match and progressive passes per match Looking at the passing and progression of these teams, there are a few points to highlight: - It's important to highlight the difference in the amount of passes per game made by Spain in the two campaigns, with Spain 2023 being by far the team with the most passes and progressive passes out of all the teams that played in the two World Cups. This is a clear consolidation of the style of play based on passing, possession and pressing that is implemented in both the women's and men's national teams. - All of these teams (consolidated on the national team scene) began to pass more in the transition from one World Cup to the next, with the exception of the United States. This may be a trend in women's international football: passing and proposing the game are key factors for success. Shots and Expected Goals Graph showing shots per match and expected goals per match In this graph relating the number of shots per match to the xG accumulated per match ( excluding penalties), we have the following observations: - Once again, Spain's evolution deserves to be highlighted. The team has made considerable improvements in attack, becoming the team with the most shots and expected goals of all teams in the last two World Cups. - Despite a reasonable increase in shots, the United States had a decrease in their xG compared to 2019, indicating that the team has, on average, decreased the quality of its scoring opportunities. In addition, the team's attacking efficiency has also decreased dramatically. Disregarding penalties, the 2019 United States had a positive balance of +8.63 (!!!) in the difference between goals and xG. In 2023, the balance was -3.01. - The England team of 2023, despite being a highlight in terms of the number of passes and progressive passes, doesn't have the same impact when it comes to finishing moves. Among the teams compared, they have the fewest xG per game (1.26), reinforcing what we said in our first post when we commented that England 2023 had a very methodical style of play. Even with a good capacity for progression, the team doesn't take many shots and, consequently, doesn't accumulate many expected goals compared to the other top teams. Final Considerations and Conclusion Throughout this post, we've focused on comparing teams that are well-established on the women's football scenario (perhaps the least well-established of these is Spain in 2019, a fact that only magnifies their winning campaign in 2023). So it was only natural that all the teams, even with differences in play and style, would be “well placed” in the graphs shown. At least in the two graphs shown, the prediction actually came true, with all 8 teams being above average in the 4 metrics used. This concludes another post in our series on the 2023 Women's World Cup, and the fourth post will be the last in the series. Stay tuned for future posts!]]></summary></entry></feed>