<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://ac3lab.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://ac3lab.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2024-04-12T15:34:56+00:00</updated><id>https://ac3lab.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">blank</title><subtitle>Marrying academic rigor with practical applications to benefit sports </subtitle><entry><title type="html">Carioca Championship 2024 - Final - Second Leg</title><link href="https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2024/post_carioca_final2-en/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Carioca Championship 2024 - Final - Second Leg"/><published>2024-04-12T13:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-04-12T13:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2024/post_carioca_final2-en</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2024/post_carioca_final2-en/"><![CDATA[<hr/> <p align="justify"> Se quiser ler este texto em pt-br, <a href="https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2000/post_carioca_final2-pt/"> clique aqui.</a> </p> <h2>Introduction</h2> <div style="width: 55%; margin: 0 auto; text-align: center;"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2024-03-07-post_carioca_compilado/Carioca_2024_FERJ.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <div style="text-align: justify"> <p align="justify"> Last Sunday, Flamengo and Nova Iguaçu played the final match of the 2024 Carioca Championship. The result of 1x0 in favor of the team commanded by Tite only confirmed what was already expected and the rubro-negros are now state champions, thanks to a campaign marked by its defensive stability. So, let’s finish our coverage of Cariocão by talking about what we can analyze from the final’s statistics. </p> </div> <h2>Flamengo x Nova Iguaçu</h2> <div style="text-align: justify"> <h3>Match Analysis</h3> <div style="width: 80%; margin: 0 auto; text-align: center;"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2024-04-12-post_carioca_final2/en/game1.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <p align="justify"> Once more, Flamengo didn’t concede any goals during the match, equalizing Fluminense’s historic mark (in 1911) of just one goal conceded in the entire tournament. Repeating the script from the first leg, the rubro-negro’s defense prevented Nova Iguaçu from developing great chances, as they managed only 5 shots from inside the box and had a xG of just 0.7. </p> <p align="justify"> Although the Gávea team followed the high defensive standard shown throughout the competition, the attacking sector was way less objective than usual, with a xG of 1.64 and 10 shots from inside the box. Compared to the inspired performance of the attack in the first leg (xG of 3.35 and 16 shots inside the box), there was a considerable drop in performance, certainly associated with the interest in managing the advantage created in the first encounter. </p> <h3>Highlights</h3> <div style="width: 80%; margin: 0 auto; text-align: center;"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2024-04-12-post_carioca_final2/en/players1.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <p align="justify"> Despite a relatively uneventful game, there were players with performances worth highlighting. On Flamengo's side, defender Léo Pereira kept up his high standards and was instrumental in stopping the Baixada side's attack, with 4 tackles won and only 1 dribble conceded. It's also worth highlighting the player's role in creating plays, as he had 14 successful long balls (82% success rate). In addition to him, left winger Bruno Henrique came on in the second half and scored the winning goal for his team, with an impressive finish of just 0.05 xG. </p> <p align="justify"> For the team from Baixada, right-winger Xandinho put in a great attacking performance, with 5 shots, 100% of his dribbles correct and adding 0.60 xG to Nova Iguaçu's 0.70 total. Another highlight was goalkeeper Fabrício, who made 5 saves from inside the area. </p> </div> <h2>Final Remarks</h2> <div style="text-align: justify"> <p align="justify"> Finally, after three months of competition, the Carioca Championship is over. Looking at the tournament as a whole, we can see that the two finalists really were the great teams of the tournament. Flamengo, for their consistency and defensive solidity, and Nova Iguaçu, who stood up to the big teams in Rio de Janeiro with a much smaller budget, revealing very competent players and coaches. </p> </div>]]></content><author><name>Ace Laboratory Football Team</name></author><category term="Football;"/><category term="Analysis"/><category term="Football;"/><category term="Carioca;"/><category term="Analysis"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Se quiser ler este texto em pt-br, clique aqui. Introduction Last Sunday, Flamengo and Nova Iguaçu played the final match of the 2024 Carioca Championship. The result of 1x0 in favor of the team commanded by Tite only confirmed what was already expected and the rubro-negros are now state champions, thanks to a campaign marked by its defensive stability. So, let’s finish our coverage of Cariocão by talking about what we can analyze from the final’s statistics. Flamengo x Nova Iguaçu Match Analysis Once more, Flamengo didn’t concede any goals during the match, equalizing Fluminense’s historic mark (in 1911) of just one goal conceded in the entire tournament. Repeating the script from the first leg, the rubro-negro’s defense prevented Nova Iguaçu from developing great chances, as they managed only 5 shots from inside the box and had a xG of just 0.7. Although the Gávea team followed the high defensive standard shown throughout the competition, the attacking sector was way less objective than usual, with a xG of 1.64 and 10 shots from inside the box. Compared to the inspired performance of the attack in the first leg (xG of 3.35 and 16 shots inside the box), there was a considerable drop in performance, certainly associated with the interest in managing the advantage created in the first encounter. Highlights Despite a relatively uneventful game, there were players with performances worth highlighting. On Flamengo's side, defender Léo Pereira kept up his high standards and was instrumental in stopping the Baixada side's attack, with 4 tackles won and only 1 dribble conceded. It's also worth highlighting the player's role in creating plays, as he had 14 successful long balls (82% success rate). In addition to him, left winger Bruno Henrique came on in the second half and scored the winning goal for his team, with an impressive finish of just 0.05 xG. For the team from Baixada, right-winger Xandinho put in a great attacking performance, with 5 shots, 100% of his dribbles correct and adding 0.60 xG to Nova Iguaçu's 0.70 total. Another highlight was goalkeeper Fabrício, who made 5 saves from inside the area. Final Remarks Finally, after three months of competition, the Carioca Championship is over. Looking at the tournament as a whole, we can see that the two finalists really were the great teams of the tournament. Flamengo, for their consistency and defensive solidity, and Nova Iguaçu, who stood up to the big teams in Rio de Janeiro with a much smaller budget, revealing very competent players and coaches.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Carioca Championship 2024 - Final - First Leg</title><link href="https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2024/post_carioca_final1-en/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Carioca Championship 2024 - Final - First Leg"/><published>2024-04-03T11:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-04-03T11:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2024/post_carioca_final1-en</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2024/post_carioca_final1-en/"><![CDATA[<hr/> <p align="justify"> Se quiser ler este texto em pt-br, <a href="https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2000/post_carioca_final1-pt/"> clique aqui.</a> </p> <h2>Introduction</h2> <div style="width: 55%; margin: 0 auto; text-align: center;"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2024-03-07-post_carioca_compilado/Carioca_2024_FERJ.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <div style="text-align: justify"> <p align="justify"> After waiting some time, last Saturday we had the first leg of the Campeonato Carioca 2024 final. The favorite Flamengo completely dominated the championship’s big surprise, Nova Iguaçu, winning 3x0 on the weekend. With this result, the team from Gávea is even closer to being the champions of Rio. Let’s analyze the data of those games and talk about what they can tell us of the game. </p> </div> <h2>Nova Iguaçu x Flamengo</h2> <div style="text-align: justify"> <h3>Match Analysis</h3> <div style="width: 80%; margin: 0 auto; text-align: center;"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2024-04-03-post_carioca_final1/en/game1.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <p align="justify"> Flamengo reached the amazing mark of 12 games without suffering a goal, the biggest sequence in the club’s history. Rubro-Negro’s great defense is shown in data by the low number of Nova Iguaçu’s shots from inside the zone (only 5) and by the even lower number of Expected Goals from the club from Baixada (0.59), which shows that only a small amount of shots meant danger to Agustín Rossi. While having a great defense, Flamengo also demonstrated great offensive plays, with 3.35 Expected Goals and 3 scored (2 for Pedro, and 1 own goal). </p> <p align="justify"> If on one side Nova Iguaçu’s attack wasn’t efficient, lots of shots were made, being comparable to both teams’ shots/minutes with the ball. But the Gigante da Baixada offered a small amount of risks and couldn’t impose their game style against Flamengo’s defense. The ball possession is one more thing that shows how the game was played, with 60% to the Rubro-Negro and 40% to the Gigante da Baixada. </p> <p align="justify"> In addition to the already good numbers, Flamengo made more than 75% of its shots from inside the opponent’s box. But it was evident that the goal difference could’ve been bigger, which makes it important to say that Flamengo has less goals than Expected Goals in the last two matches. On the second leg of the semifinal, Rubro-Negro’s attack didn’t reach expectations, and against Nova Iguaçu it wasn’t different. Considering the match’s one own goal, Flamengo just scored two times, with at least 3 being expected. </p> <h3>Highlights</h3> <div style="width: 80%; margin: 0 auto; text-align: center;"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2024-04-03-post_carioca_final1/en/players1.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <p align="justify"> Scoring two goals, we have to mention Pedro when talking about this match. In addition to his goals, he also had two key passes and four shots. In general, Flamengo’s left side played very well, Everton Cebolinha also did well, hitting 91% of his passes and 90% completed dribbles. While in defense goalkeeper Rossi had another great match, making 6 saves -2 from inside the zone- and having 100% accuracy on passes (23 passes and 4 long balls). </p> <p align="justify"> Besides having few opportunities, Nova Iguaçu’s attack can be highlighted through Bill. The attacker contributed alone to almost 40% of the team’s Expected Goals, plus 5 successful dribbles and 3 key passes. Another player that we should praise is Fabricio, the goalkeeper, making 6 saves and 4 from inside the zone. </p> </div> <h2>Final Remarks</h2> <div style="text-align: justify"> <p align="justify"> The first game of the Cariocão Final is gone. Flamengo has a big advantage, and it’s very hard, or even impossible for Nova Iguaçu to score 3 goals on the team that only suffered 1 in the entire Championship. But football is full of impossible events. </p> </div>]]></content><author><name>Ace Laboratory Football Team</name></author><category term="Football;"/><category term="Analysis"/><category term="Football;"/><category term="Carioca;"/><category term="Analysis"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Se quiser ler este texto em pt-br, clique aqui. Introduction After waiting some time, last Saturday we had the first leg of the Campeonato Carioca 2024 final. The favorite Flamengo completely dominated the championship’s big surprise, Nova Iguaçu, winning 3x0 on the weekend. With this result, the team from Gávea is even closer to being the champions of Rio. Let’s analyze the data of those games and talk about what they can tell us of the game. Nova Iguaçu x Flamengo Match Analysis Flamengo reached the amazing mark of 12 games without suffering a goal, the biggest sequence in the club’s history. Rubro-Negro’s great defense is shown in data by the low number of Nova Iguaçu’s shots from inside the zone (only 5) and by the even lower number of Expected Goals from the club from Baixada (0.59), which shows that only a small amount of shots meant danger to Agustín Rossi. While having a great defense, Flamengo also demonstrated great offensive plays, with 3.35 Expected Goals and 3 scored (2 for Pedro, and 1 own goal). If on one side Nova Iguaçu’s attack wasn’t efficient, lots of shots were made, being comparable to both teams’ shots/minutes with the ball. But the Gigante da Baixada offered a small amount of risks and couldn’t impose their game style against Flamengo’s defense. The ball possession is one more thing that shows how the game was played, with 60% to the Rubro-Negro and 40% to the Gigante da Baixada. In addition to the already good numbers, Flamengo made more than 75% of its shots from inside the opponent’s box. But it was evident that the goal difference could’ve been bigger, which makes it important to say that Flamengo has less goals than Expected Goals in the last two matches. On the second leg of the semifinal, Rubro-Negro’s attack didn’t reach expectations, and against Nova Iguaçu it wasn’t different. Considering the match’s one own goal, Flamengo just scored two times, with at least 3 being expected. Highlights Scoring two goals, we have to mention Pedro when talking about this match. In addition to his goals, he also had two key passes and four shots. In general, Flamengo’s left side played very well, Everton Cebolinha also did well, hitting 91% of his passes and 90% completed dribbles. While in defense goalkeeper Rossi had another great match, making 6 saves -2 from inside the zone- and having 100% accuracy on passes (23 passes and 4 long balls). Besides having few opportunities, Nova Iguaçu’s attack can be highlighted through Bill. The attacker contributed alone to almost 40% of the team’s Expected Goals, plus 5 successful dribbles and 3 key passes. Another player that we should praise is Fabricio, the goalkeeper, making 6 saves and 4 from inside the zone. Final Remarks The first game of the Cariocão Final is gone. Flamengo has a big advantage, and it’s very hard, or even impossible for Nova Iguaçu to score 3 goals on the team that only suffered 1 in the entire Championship. But football is full of impossible events.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Even under pressure, Brazil changes the game with substitutions and draw</title><link href="https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2024/post_brasil_espanha-en/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Even under pressure, Brazil changes the game with substitutions and draw"/><published>2024-03-28T16:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-03-28T16:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2024/post_brasil_espanha-en</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2024/post_brasil_espanha-en/"><![CDATA[<p align="justify"> Se quiser ler este texto em pt-br, <a href="https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2000/post_brasil_espanha-pt/"> clique aqui.</a> </p> <h2>Introduction</h2> <p align="justify"> Giving sequence to the friendly matches, Spain and Brazil faced each other at Santiago Bernabéu, playing a hard-fought match with lots of goals. Rodrygo, Endrick and Paquetá scored for Brazil, while Rodri with two penalty goals and Dani Olmo scored the Spanish national team’s goals in Tuesday's draw. </p> <h2>Spain x Brazil</h2> <div style="text-align: justify"> <p align="justify"> On team’s second match at the international break, Dorival Jr’s Brazil continued to excite fans, with a last minute 3x3 draw against Spain’s strong national team, but the defensive flaws of a team with little chemistry and small training period were shown on the first half of the match, where the Seleção suffered with constant pressure from the Spaniards. But with good subs on the second half things started to get better for the Brazilians, that managed to get the draw from a penalty kick. </p> <p align="justify"> On the other side, Jose Luis’ Spain showed good options on the offensive side, like the young prospect Lamine Yamal, with only 16 years old, causing problems for Brazil’s defense, suffering a penalty and winning several duels. But the team also showed problems on the defensive side, with a failed pass crucial to Brazil’s first goal and a penalty conceded in the last minute of the game. </p> </div> <h3>Match Analysis</h3> <div style="width: 80%; margin: 0 auto; text-align: center;"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2024-03-28-brasil_espanha/en/game1.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <div style="text-align: justify"> <p align="justify"> In a match where both teams seemed very determined to win, we had one half to each team: Spain dominated the first 45 minutes, scoring two goals and pressuring Seleção’s ball possession. While Brazil got more freedom in the second half with half-time subs, scoring two goals at the last part of the game. </p> <p align="justify"> Despite relatively equal 90 minutes to both sides - with 4 big chances for each team - the ball possession was Spain’s (59% x 41%), and also shot more than Brazil (19 Spanish shots x 12 Brazilian shots). In defense, data are more similar, with little difference on duels won (54 x 49) and on interceptions (6 x 8). </p> </div> <h3>Highlights</h3> <div style="width: 80%; margin: 0 auto; text-align: center;"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2024-03-28-brasil_espanha/en/players1.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <div style="text-align: justify"> <p align="justify"> If on one side the defensive system of both teams was not exciting, the offensive one was excellent. The combination of a bad day for the defenses and a great one for the attackers resulted in a match with 6 goals. To the main duel, we brought Douglas Luiz, who despite only having 19 minutes played, managed to have 1 key pass and 100% correct passes; and Rodri, the big Spanish star, with 3 key passes, 2 goals and 95% correct passes in 90 minutes played, besides 100% long balls accuracy. </p> <p align="justify"> Even with less opportunities and ball possession, Brazil’s attack was very efficient thanks to the number 10 Rodrygo. While the Spanish’s attack was marked by the performance of the young Lamine Yamal, who dominated Brazilian defense. While Rodrygo scored one goal, Yamal gave an assist. Going to duels and dribbles, the young star wins on duels (11 x 5) but loses on successful dribbles (60% x 75%), even trying more. For Brazil, Endrick also played well, scoring a goal after only 4 minutes played. </p> <p align="justify"> Despite the offensive highlights, both teams’ defenses did not live up to expectation. The best defensive players from Spain and Brazil were Carvajal and Bento, respectively. Carvajal won 42% duels, completed 88% of his passes, made 4 tackles and suffered one penalty. The Brazilian goalkeeper Bento completed 84% of his passes, made 5 defenses and had 56 ball touches. </p> </div>]]></content><author><name>Ace Laboratory Football Team</name></author><category term="Football;"/><category term="Analysis"/><category term="Football;"/><category term="Carioca;"/><category term="Analysis"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Se quiser ler este texto em pt-br, clique aqui. Introduction Giving sequence to the friendly matches, Spain and Brazil faced each other at Santiago Bernabéu, playing a hard-fought match with lots of goals. Rodrygo, Endrick and Paquetá scored for Brazil, while Rodri with two penalty goals and Dani Olmo scored the Spanish national team’s goals in Tuesday's draw. Spain x Brazil On team’s second match at the international break, Dorival Jr’s Brazil continued to excite fans, with a last minute 3x3 draw against Spain’s strong national team, but the defensive flaws of a team with little chemistry and small training period were shown on the first half of the match, where the Seleção suffered with constant pressure from the Spaniards. But with good subs on the second half things started to get better for the Brazilians, that managed to get the draw from a penalty kick. On the other side, Jose Luis’ Spain showed good options on the offensive side, like the young prospect Lamine Yamal, with only 16 years old, causing problems for Brazil’s defense, suffering a penalty and winning several duels. But the team also showed problems on the defensive side, with a failed pass crucial to Brazil’s first goal and a penalty conceded in the last minute of the game. Match Analysis In a match where both teams seemed very determined to win, we had one half to each team: Spain dominated the first 45 minutes, scoring two goals and pressuring Seleção’s ball possession. While Brazil got more freedom in the second half with half-time subs, scoring two goals at the last part of the game. Despite relatively equal 90 minutes to both sides - with 4 big chances for each team - the ball possession was Spain’s (59% x 41%), and also shot more than Brazil (19 Spanish shots x 12 Brazilian shots). In defense, data are more similar, with little difference on duels won (54 x 49) and on interceptions (6 x 8). Highlights If on one side the defensive system of both teams was not exciting, the offensive one was excellent. The combination of a bad day for the defenses and a great one for the attackers resulted in a match with 6 goals. To the main duel, we brought Douglas Luiz, who despite only having 19 minutes played, managed to have 1 key pass and 100% correct passes; and Rodri, the big Spanish star, with 3 key passes, 2 goals and 95% correct passes in 90 minutes played, besides 100% long balls accuracy. Even with less opportunities and ball possession, Brazil’s attack was very efficient thanks to the number 10 Rodrygo. While the Spanish’s attack was marked by the performance of the young Lamine Yamal, who dominated Brazilian defense. While Rodrygo scored one goal, Yamal gave an assist. Going to duels and dribbles, the young star wins on duels (11 x 5) but loses on successful dribbles (60% x 75%), even trying more. For Brazil, Endrick also played well, scoring a goal after only 4 minutes played. Despite the offensive highlights, both teams’ defenses did not live up to expectation. The best defensive players from Spain and Brazil were Carvajal and Bento, respectively. Carvajal won 42% duels, completed 88% of his passes, made 4 tackles and suffered one penalty. The Brazilian goalkeeper Bento completed 84% of his passes, made 5 defenses and had 56 ball touches.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Endrick’s star shines and Brazil beat England</title><link href="https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2024/post_brasil_inglaterra-en/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Endrick’s star shines and Brazil beat England"/><published>2024-03-25T09:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-03-25T09:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2024/post_brasil_inglaterra-en</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2024/post_brasil_inglaterra-en/"><![CDATA[<h2>Introduction</h2> <p align="justify"> FIFA dates are excellent times for national teams to adjust their tactical schemes and try out new players. During this period, the Brazilian national team faced England in their first friendly match, and we're going to analyze the teams' performances and the main highlights of the match. </p> <h2>England x Brazil</h2> <div style="text-align: justify"> <p align="justify"> On this FIFA World Cup date, the Brazilian national team faced an even greater challenge, with a new coach, injured key players and the weight of a poor season last year. This is a short period of training and adjustments, but the importance of playing a friendly against a top team and the need for victory spoke louder, and even with all these obstacles, Brazil created chances and managed to beat England by the minimum score, with a goal from Endrick, who was one of the highlights of the match. </p> <p align="justify"> On the other side, England, who have been working harder with a longer-serving coach and a more settled team, but who also had a lot of injured players, were unable to beat the Brazilian national team. The English national team hadn't lost a game since 2022, when they were knocked out of the World Cup in the quarter-finals by France. </p> </div> <h3>Match Analysis</h3> <div style="width: 80%; margin: 0 auto; text-align: center;"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2024-03-25-brasil_inglaterra/en/game1.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <div style="text-align: justify"> <p align="justify"> Brazil’s first game with a new coach and only 5 days of training managed to excite Brazilian supporters, with a solid defense and creative offensive power, made possible by the genius of Lucas Paquetá. </p> <p align="justify"> The almost equal ball possession (53% / 47%) shows what a back-and-forth game it was, with intensity and changes of control that could be one of a World Cup game. Despite that parity, Brazil's dominance is shown by the 12 (!!!) shots from inside Pickford's zone, with only 2 being shot from outside. And England, even though having lost offensive power with Harry Kane's being injured, still managed to shot 14 times, 7 being from inside Bento's zone. </p> </div> <h3>Highlights</h3> <div style="width: 80%; margin: 0 auto; text-align: center;"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2024-03-25-brasil_inglaterra/en/highlights-player1.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <div style="text-align: justify"> <p align="justify"> The game was very close for both teams. The midfield of both sides had to work a lot more than the others. For comparison, we brought Lucas Paquetá and Declan Rice with very similar statistics, both in the offensive and defensive actions of the midfield. But, Lucas led anyway with the most Key passes (3x2), tackles (3x2) and correct passing rate (94% x 91%), living up to the title of MOTM.</p> <p align="justify"> On the offensive side of the field, Rodrygo and Anthony Gordon were the highlighted players of both teams, with the Brazilian leading the successful dribbles rate duel <b>(100% to 80%)</b> and an almost perfect passing rate <b>(96%)</b>. However, when it comes to shots on target, posing more threats for the opposite team, Gordon leads with <b>2 Shots on target</b> against <b>1 Shot</b> by the Real Madrid’s player. </p> <p align="justify"> The Defensive brazilian sector was led by Danilo, who had incredible <b>7 Clearances</b>, <b>4 duels won</b> and <b>2 shots blocked</b>. On other hand, Ben Chilwell, despite being a defensive player, participated a lot in the offensive and the midfield sectors, with <b>2 shots on target</b>, same as Anthony Gordon, and <b>100% long balls accuracy</b>, materializing as an incredible player involved in all sides of the field. </p> </div>]]></content><author><name>Ace Laboratory Football Team</name></author><category term="Football;"/><category term="Analysis"/><category term="Football;"/><category term="Carioca;"/><category term="Analysis"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Introduction FIFA dates are excellent times for national teams to adjust their tactical schemes and try out new players. During this period, the Brazilian national team faced England in their first friendly match, and we're going to analyze the teams' performances and the main highlights of the match.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Carioca Championship 2024 - Semifinal - Second Leg</title><link href="https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2024/post_carioca_semifinal_2-en/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Carioca Championship 2024 - Semifinal - Second Leg"/><published>2024-03-20T12:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-03-20T12:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2024/post_carioca_semifinal_2-en</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2024/post_carioca_semifinal_2-en/"><![CDATA[<p align="justify"> Se quiser ler este texto em pt-br, <a href="https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2000/post_carioca_semifinal_2-pt/"> clique aqui.</a> </p> <h2>Introduction</h2> <div style="width: 55%; margin: 0 auto; text-align: center;"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2024-03-07-post_carioca_compilado/Carioca_2024_FERJ.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <div style="text-align: justify"> <p align="justify"> This past weekend we had the second leg of the semi-finals of the Carioca Championship 2024. Flamengo held Fluminense to a draw and secured their place in the finals, and Nova Iguaçu, the big surprise of the competition, eliminated Vasco with a 1-0 win at Maracanã stadium. Now, let's analyze the data from these games and evaluate the teams' performances. </p> </div> <h2>Flamengo x Fluminense</h2> <div style="text-align: justify"> <h3>Match Analysis</h3> <div style="width: 80%; margin: 0 auto; text-align: center;"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2024-03-20-post_carioca_semifinal_2/en/game1.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <p align="justify"> Flamengo did their job and finished another game without conceding a goal. The club managed to prevent the tricolor from creating danger in their area, which is demonstrated by the fact that only <b>4 of Fluminense's 14 shots</b> came from inside the area, and none of them went towards goalkeeper Agustín Rossi. Playing on the counter-attack and without possession of the ball, Flamengo managed a higher xG than their opponent (<b>1.38 x 0.98</b>), having 5 fewer shots. </p> <p align="justify"> Fluminense this time played the way they prefer, having the most time with the ball (<b>63%</b>) and exchanging more than twice as many passes as their opponent (<b>543 x 242</b>). However, we saw this possession not converted into real chances, Flamengo's defensive scheme nullifying Fluminense's attack, which had <b>0 shots on goal</b> in the 1st and 2nd leg, even though the tricolor improved their attacking performance for the second leg. </p> <p align="justify">As a result, we can see that even though Fernando Diniz's team dictated the game, they were unable to beat Flamengo's defense, which still only conceded 1 goal in the entire competition. Flamengo goes to the finals as favorites, but they will face Nova Iguaçu, the only team to have managed to score a goal against them, and they will be hungry to win this cup as the underdogs of the championship. </p> <h3>Highlights</h3> <div style="width: 80%; margin: 0 auto; text-align: center;"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2024-03-20-post_carioca_semifinal_2/en/players1.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <p align="justify"> The game didn't have any great highlights, but we must mention some of the important players in the game, such as Flamengo's defensive duo, Léo Pereira and Fabrício Bruno. The two were essential to Fluminense's low number of shots inside the box (<b>4</b>), adding up their statistics, we have <b>14 duels won</b>, <b>9 clearances</b>, <b>8 interceptions</b>, and only <b>1 dribble suffered</b>. </p> <p align="justify"> As for the tricolor, we can highlight Lima, a key player in Fluminense's midfield, who played in basically every area of the pitch. He was the player who touched the ball the most (<b>99</b>) and yet managed to maintain a very high quality of passing (<b>93% success rate</b>). As well as Marcelo, who played at left-back in a more attacking way, hitting <b>4 long balls right</b> and making <b>2 tackles</b>. </p> </div> <h2>Nova Iguaçu x Vasco</h2> <div style="text-align: justify"> <h3>Match Analysis</h3> <div style="width: 80%; margin: 0 auto; text-align: center;"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2024-03-20-post_carioca_semifinal_2/en/game2.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <p align="justify"> On the Vasco side, the situation became increasingly complicated for the team's fans, who witnessed their team being eliminated from the championship with no chance of making the final a Clássico dos Milhões. In the match, although Vasco had <b>66% possession</b> and <b>5 shots on goal</b>, they failed to convert any of their <b>11 shots</b> at the end of the 90 minutes. </p> <p align="justify">On the other side, Nova Iguaçu, despite not dominating possession, posed more of a threat to Vasco's defense, attempting <b>14 shots</b>, <b>6 of them on target</b>, and converting one chance. Additionally, they intercepted two times more than Vasco (<b>42 vs. 18</b>) and regained possession within an average of <b>24 seconds</b> after losing it, almost half the time compared to the Cruz Maltino's average (<b>42 seconds</b>). </p> <p align="justify">Nova Iguaçu thus surpassed Vasco to reach the final of the Carioca Championship for the first time in their history. As a result, "A Laranja Mecânica da Baixada," as their fans call them, will face Flamengo on March 31st and April 7th for the title that crowns the King of Rio de Janeiro. </p> <h3>Highlights</h3> <div style="width: 80%; margin: 0 auto; text-align: center;"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2024-03-20-post_carioca_semifinal_2/en/players2.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <p align="justify">Playing for Vasco, Dimitri Payet was the team's highlight in another of our analyses. The Frenchman, with his heat map fully registering his participation in the middle and especially on the left side of the pitch, had an <b>83% successful dribble rate</b> and <b>4 key passes</b>, which, even with Gary Medel's <b>80% accuracy on long balls</b>, were exceptionally not enough for the Cruzmaltino team to score.</p> <p align="justify">For the "Gigante da Baixada", two players are noteworthy: Bill, striker for the Nova Iguaçu team, had <b>3 out of 4 successful dribbles</b> in the game and scored a goal. And Fabricio, the goalkeeper who put up a real wall in front of the goal, with <b>4 crucial saves from inside the area</b> and an incredible <b>100% rate of shots saved</b> in the match that guarantees a historic milestone for the Nova Iguaçu's team.</p> </div> <h2>Final Remarks</h2> <div style="text-align: justify"> <p align="justify"> And so ended the semi-finals of the 2024 Campeonato Carioca, with favorites Flamengo seeking their 38th title in the competition and the surprise of the championship Nova Iguaçu, participating in their first final in this tournament and seeking their unprecedented cup. </p> <p align="justify"> Share our analysis if you liked it, and keep an eye on our social media, because next week we'll be back with an analysis of the first leg of the final of the tournament. </p> </div>]]></content><author><name>Ace Laboratory Football Team</name></author><category term="Football;"/><category term="Analysis"/><category term="Football;"/><category term="Carioca;"/><category term="Analysis"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Se quiser ler este texto em pt-br, clique aqui.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Carioca Championship 2024 - Semifinal - First Leg</title><link href="https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2024/post_carioca_semifinal_1/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Carioca Championship 2024 - Semifinal - First Leg"/><published>2024-03-15T13:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-03-15T13:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2024/post_carioca_semifinal_1</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2024/post_carioca_semifinal_1/"><![CDATA[<p align="justify"> Se quiser ler este texto em pt-br, <a href="https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2000/post_carioca_semifinal_1-pt/"> clique aqui.</a> </p> <h2>Introduction</h2> <div style="width: 55%; margin: 0 auto; text-align: center;"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2024-03-07-post_carioca_compilado/Carioca_2024_FERJ.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <div style="text-align: justify"> <p align="justify"> The Carioca Championship continues to surprise the Brazilian football, with Fluminense, Flamengo, Vasco, and Nova Iguaçu in the mix. The Ace Laboratory Football Team dives into the decisive matches, from Flamengo's dominance over Fluminense to Nova Iguaçu's unexpected offensive power trying to overcome the Vasco's "Wall", offering an exciting glimpse into the tournament's electrifying action. </p> </div> <h2>Fluminense x Flamengo</h2> <div style="text-align: justify"> <h3>Match Analysis</h3> <div style="width: 80%; margin: 0 auto; text-align: center;"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2024-03-15-post_carioca_semifinal_1/en/flaflugame.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <p align="justify"> Fluminense played a match below expectations against Flamengo, being constantly pressured, and failing to impose their style of play. This was the 1st match of the 2024 Carioca Championship in which the team ended the match with less ball possession than its opponent <b>(49% x 51%)</b>, with a weak performance from its attack, which did not make any shots to the goal defended by goalkeeper Agustín Rossi. Furthermore, the team committed a total of <b>11 errors that led to shots</b> in the game, and until this match, they had committed <b>31 errors</b> in the entire championship. </p> <p align="justify"> The rubro-negro, who had their greatest strength in the defensive sector, demonstrated that they also have high offensive capacity, making a total of <b>23 shots</b> in the match, with <b>9</b> of these shots being on Fábio's goal. If we consider the team's approximate time with the ball, we have a rate of <b>1 shot every 2 minutes</b> in possession of the ball. </p> <p align="justify"> The data showed complete dominance by Tite's team on the field, both in the defensive and offensive sectors, Flamengo created and did not let the opponent take advantage of the few chances they had. Fluminense will have a difficult job to qualify for the finals, scoring 3 goals against a team that only conceded 1 goal in the entire championship, for the next match coach Fernando Diniz will need to change his strategies, and possibly behave more aggressively if he wants to guarantee his place in the final. </p> <h3>Highlights</h3> <div style="width: 80%; margin: 0 auto; text-align: center;"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2024-03-15-post_carioca_semifinal_1/en/flafluplayers.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <p align="justify"> One of the ways to see how Fluminense played defensively was the positioning of Jhon Arias, a player who normally acts as a winger in an offensive way, ended up staying for most of the game on the tricolor field, playing on the right flank as a defender and unable to exploit his best qualities, his dribbling and his important passes. </p> <p align="justify"> Another point was the number of saves that goalkeeper Fábio had to make from shots from inside his area <b>(5)</b>, showing how effective Flamengo's creation was, and in large part this was due to Nicolás De La Cruz. The midfielder made a total of <b>6 key passes</b> for his team, playing mainly on the left side of the field, the side where the club took the most shots. </p> <p align="justify"> It is also worth noting the performance of striker Pedro, who took advantage of his team's opportunities, scoring <b>1 goal</b> at the end of the match, and making a total ofv<b>6 shots</b>, with <b>3</b> in the goal, having the opportunity to increase the score, if it weren't for the good performance of goalkeeper Fábio. </p> </div> <h2>Vasco x Nova Iguaçu</h2> <div style="text-align: justify"> <h3>Match Analysis</h3> <div style="width: 80%; margin: 0 auto; text-align: center;"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2024-03-15-post_carioca_semifinal_1/en/vasconovaiguacugame.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <p align="justify"> The two teams engaged in a match that, despite having only two goals, was marked by a large number of shots from both sides. The total number of shots is impressive for a semifinal match, especially when considering that the clash between Flamengo and Fluminense had only 31 shots, nearly 1.5 times fewer than the encounter between Vasco da Gama and Nova Iguaçu, which featured 45 shots total by the end of the game. </p> <p align="justify"> For Vasco, the offensive game was unusual, considering that the team has an average of 10.8 shots on goal in their last 5 games, yet they managed to shoot 21 times, with only 7 shots directed at goalkeeper Fabricio. Vasco’s midfield also demonstrated a lot of creativity reaching the attack, tallying 16 key passes throughout the first 90 minutes of the Carioca Championship semifinal. </p> <p align="justify"> For Nova Iguaçu, on the other hand, it was not a game much different from the usual experience in their last 5 games, as the team’s average number of shots in the Carioca Championship is 17 shots per game. The data observed in the match also shows the preference of Nova Iguaçu to shoot from outside the box, with more shots from outside <b>(13)</b> than from inside <b>(11)</b>, creating a lot of work, for the opposing goalkeeper. </p> <h3>Highlights</h3> <div style="width: 80%; margin: 0 auto; text-align: center;"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2024-03-15-post_carioca_semifinal_1/en/vasconovaiguacuplayers.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <p align="justify"> Undoubtedly, it was a highly contested match with several chances for both teams, and in this context, it is essential to highlight both the main chance creators and the main defenders of each team. </p> <p align="justify"> On Vasco’s side, with an incredible performance, the Frenchman Dimitri Payet stood out with an 88% pass accuracy rate, with 5 key passes executed solely by the former Olympique Marseille midfielder. Simultaneously, in the defensive sector, the attacking midfielder was also fundamental, with 12 duels won by the Cruz-Maltino and possessing a very participative heat map on the left side of the defensive third of the Gigante da Colina. </p> <p align="justify"> In a game with many shots and above-average performances, attackers who had good performances like Carlinhos, who shot on goal 5 times, were overshadowed by the miraculous performances of both teams' goalkeepers. Léo Jardim made incredible 14 saves, with 9 of these shots from inside the box, representing a total of 93% of balls saved, and even conceding one goal was considered the MOTM. While Fabricio, Nova Iguaçu's goalkeeper, despite "only" making 6 saves, with 50% of them coming from shots from inside the box, successfully completed 80% of long balls launched for the team's possession in the field, a characteristic that is increasingly needed in today's goalkeepers. </p> </div> <h2>Final Remarks</h2> <div style="text-align: justify"> <p align="justify"> The first two games of the semifinals are in the books. Flamengo has the advantage, and Fluminense will need a much better performance to reverse the score. Vasco, despite being saved by Leo Jardim's great performance, will need at least a simple victory to guarantee their place in the final. Nova Iguaçu, on the other hand, has the advantage of a draw. </p> <p align="justify"> The Ace Football Laboratory team will continue to follow the Carioca Championship, bringing detailed analysis of the games and the players. Stay tuned! </p> </div>]]></content><author><name>Ace Laboratory Football Team</name></author><category term="Football;"/><category term="Analysis"/><category term="Football;"/><category term="Carioca;"/><category term="Analysis"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Se quiser ler este texto em pt-br, clique aqui.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Odyssey of Women in the Olympic Games: A Data-Driven Tale</title><link href="https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2024/post_olympic_women/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Odyssey of Women in the Olympic Games: A Data-Driven Tale"/><published>2024-03-08T17:40:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-03-08T17:40:00+00:00</updated><id>https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2024/post_olympic_women</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2024/post_olympic_women/"><![CDATA[<h3 id="the-historical-march-of-womens-olympic-aspirations">The Historical March of Women’s Olympic Aspirations</h3> <p align="justify"> As 2024, an Olympic year, draws near, and on this International Women's Day, we take a moment to honor and reflect on the remarkable journey of women in the Olympic Games. This saga, marked by unyielding courage, monumental breakthroughs, and a shared quest for equality, resonates with the spirit of today's celebrations. It was in Paris, at the dawn of the 20th century, that 39 pioneering women first made their mark in the annals of the Olympics. Amidst a societal backdrop heavily shadowed by restrictive norms, these audacious women ventured into sports such as golf, tennis, and sailing, setting the stage for a revolution in the realm of athletics. From the silken swimsuits of the 1912 British swim team to the defiant establishment of the Women's Olympiad in the '20s, each leap forward was both a triumph over adversity and a step towards greater inclusion. Yet, it wasn't without setbacks. The 800m run controversy of 1928 and the subsequent exclusion of women from these events. </p> <p align="justify"> From the silken swimsuits of the 1912 British swim team to the defiant establishment of the Women's Olympiad in the '20s, each leap forward was both a triumph over adversity and a step towards greater inclusion. Yet, it wasn't without setbacks. The 800m run controversy of 1928 and the subsequent exclusion of women from these events. </p> <h3 id="the-data-driven-story-from-past-achievements-to-present-pursuits">The Data-Driven Story: From Past Achievements to Present Pursuits</h3> <p align="justify"> Our historical data shines a light on these formative years, displaying not just the numbers, but the narratives they represent—of initial hesitancy giving way to gradual acceptance. </p> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2024-03-08-post_olympic_women-Images/1.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <p align="justify"> Fast forward to the present, and we see a remarkable transformation. The recent Olympiads (2020) underscore a record-breaking surge, with women constituting over 49% of competitors winning medals—a testament to the indomitable spirit of countless female Olympians. </p> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2024-03-08-post_olympic_women-Images/2.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2024-03-08-post_olympic_women-Images/3.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <p align="justify"> As we marvel at these visual testaments of progress, it's clear the journey is far from over. Even as we acknowledge the soaring participation rates and celebrate the barriers broken, our data reveals a patchwork of investment in female athletes across nations. Some countries lead with burgeoning enthusiasm, while others reveal a hesitance to embrace the full potential of their female contenders. </p> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2024-03-08-post_olympic_women-Images/4.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <p align="justify"> The dashed line of ideal equality on our charts is more than a benchmark—it's a call to action. A call to support and elevate the role of women in sports, ensuring that the future of the Olympics is not just gender-balanced in participation but also in recognition, support, and celebration. </p> <h3 id="concluding-thoughts-a-salute-to-pioneers-and-a-vision-for-tomorrow">Concluding Thoughts: A Salute to Pioneers and a Vision for Tomorrow</h3> <p align="justify"> On this day, as we celebrate the monumental achievements of women across the globe, we turn our admiration towards the Olympians who've not only competed but have rewritten the history of sports. In the spirit of International Women's Day, we pay homage to trailblazers like Larisa Latynina, Birgit Fischer-Schmidt and Jenny Thompson, whose medal counts stand as towering testaments to female prowess and resilience in the face of adversity. </p> <p align="justify"> Their victories are not just etched in gold, silver, or bronze but are imprinted in the hearts of countless young girls who dare to dream bigger because of them. It is in their footsteps that the next generation will tread, inspired to leap higher, run faster, and push harder. </p> <p align="justify"> In their honor, and in the spirit of fostering a future where every girl has the opportunity to chase her Olympic dreams, we invite you to delve deeper into the evolution of women's participation in the Olympics. Our dashboard provides a comprehensive look at the strides made over the years, showcasing participation by National Olympic Committees (NOC) and by each Olympic Game. </p> <p align="justify"> Explore our dashboard and witness the journey of women in the Olympics: <a href="https://app.powerbi.com/view?r=eyJrIjoiY2M3ZGNjNzctMzMxYS00MjJhLThkM2ItODU5ODcxOGQ5Zjg0IiwidCI6IjhlZWNhNDA0LWE0N2QtNDU1NS1hMmQ0LTBmMzYxOTA0MWM5YyJ9" target="_blank">Women in Olympics</a>. </p>]]></content><author><name>Amanda Azevedo</name></author><category term="Olympics;"/><category term="PowerBI"/><category term="Olympics;"/><category term="Women;"/><category term="PowerBI"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A data-infused tribute on International Women's Day to female Olympians' journey, showcased in our dashboard, from 1900 Paris to the 2024 Olympics, underlining ongoing strides towards sports gender equality.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Carioca Championship 2024 - A compiled analysis</title><link href="https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2024/post_carioca_compilado/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Carioca Championship 2024 - A compiled analysis"/><published>2024-03-07T12:20:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-03-07T12:20:00+00:00</updated><id>https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2024/post_carioca_compilado</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2024/post_carioca_compilado/"><![CDATA[<p align="justify"> Se quiser ler este texto em pt-br, <a href="https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2000/post_carioca_compilado-pt/"> clique aqui.</a> </p> <h2>Introduction</h2> <div style="width: 65%; margin: 0 auto; text-align: center;"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2024-03-07-post_carioca_compilado/Carioca_2024_FERJ.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <div style="text-align: justify"> The 2024 Carioca Championship has reached the semifinal stage, and Ace Laboratory brings a compiled analysis of the four Rio giants and Nova Iguaçu, which had an impressive campaign and qualified for the final phase of the competition. Flamengo, leading the league stage, Nova Iguaçu, surprising everyone, Vasco, boasting a quality midfield, Fluminense, with a solid defense, and Botafogo, underperforming. Let's analyze the performance of each team and the individual highlights of the competition. </div> <div style="width: 80%; margin: 0 auto; text-align: center;"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2024-03-07-post_carioca_compilado/table.jpeg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <h2>Flamengo</h2> <div style="width: 80%; margin: 0 auto; text-align: center;"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2024-03-07-post_carioca_compilado/flamengo-en.jpeg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <div style="text-align: justify"> <p align="justify"> We can say that Flamengo's highlight in this championship was its defensive sector. The team conceded just 1 goal in the 11 matches of the competition, being the 3rd team with the best rate of duels won <b>(40.1%)</b> and the 2nd best if we only consider aerial duels <b>(49.4%)</b> . This security in duels, added to the quality of the players, made Flamengo the club that made the fewest mistakes that led to shots <b>(31)</b> and the one that took the least shots <b>(79)</b> from opponents, with more than 15 shots difference from 2nd place. </p> <p align="justify"> With Giorgian De Arrascaeta in midfield, Flamengo's offensive work was also impressive, the player is **above the 3rd quartile** in 6 of the 7 offensive categories we observed, being in the Top 10 of the championship in goals, assists and passes key. The rubro-negro likes to dictate the game and with that he managed to create many opportunities, he was 2nd with the most possession of the ball <b>(57.8%)</b>, 1st in the rate of successful crosses <b>(43.3%)</b> , 1st in goals scored <b>(23)</b> and 1st in shots <b>(178)</b>, with more than 20 shots ahead of 2nd place. </p> <p align="justify"> With this we saw Flamengo's dominance in the 2024 Carioca Championship, the team proved to be solid defensively, being the one that conceded the least goals, and solid offensively, being the one that scored the most goals. With the quality of their players, Flamengo will be favorites for the semi-final against Fluminense, and will be looking for the title undefeated. </p> </div> <h2>Nova Iguaçu</h2> <div style="width: 80%; margin: 0 auto; text-align: center;"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2024-03-07-post_carioca_compilado/nova-iguacu-en.jpeg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <div style="text-align: justify"> <p align="justify"> The Nova Iguaçu team surprised many with the second-best performance in the league stage of the Carioca Championship. The team does not have a good average in overall defensive metrics, having the lowest possession average among the qualified teams <b>(7th in the entire league)</b>, the highest foul rate, and conceding a total of thirteen goals. The key factor for Nova Iguaçu's victories was capitalizing on their shots on goal and converting chances into goals. </p> <p align="justify"> Midfielder Bill was the standout player for the team in the competition. The athlete ranked <b>1st</b> in assists, key passes, and successful dribbles for the team, highlighting his importance throughout the championship. The radar chart below also illustrates the player's versatility in defense, playmaking, and finishing. </p> <p align="justify"> With 24 points, seven wins, three draws, and only one defeat, the "Clockwork Orange" team from the Baixada qualifies for the semifinals and eliminates one of the Rio giants. Just like in the league stage, Nova Iguaçu will need to capitalize on their chances to surprise Vasco and reach the final of the Carioca 2024. </p> </div> <h2>Vasco</h2> <div style="width: 80%; margin: 0 auto; text-align: center;"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2024-03-07-post_carioca_compilado/vasco-en.jpeg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <div style="text-align: justify"> <p align="justify"> Vasco da Gama's championship was marked by its attack, ranking as the <b>2nd</b> highest-scoring team in the tournament with a total of 20 goals. With a team that maintains ball possession and precision in its passes, Vasco was the <b>3rd</b> team with the most possession <b>(55%)</b>, 3rd in passes <b>(5290)</b>, and 3rd in pass accuracy <b>(87.7%)</b>. </p> <p align="justify"> The standout player of the team is none other than the Frenchman Dimitri Payet. The midfielder was the team's <b>2nd</b> highest scorer, <b>1st</b> in assists, and <b>1st</b> in key passes. Looking at the radar chart, we can see that the player plays a crucial role in creating and finishing plays. Payet was a fundamental piece for Vasco during the league stage and will be essential for the team in the semifinal against Nova Iguaçu. </p> <p align="justify"> For the semifinals, Vasco will need to maintain the quality that its midfield and attack have shown in the recent matches of the tournament to avoid surprises and secure a spot in the final of the Carioca 2024. </p> </div> <h2>Fluminense</h2> <div style="width: 80%; margin: 0 auto; text-align: center;"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2024-03-07-post_carioca_compilado/fluminense-en.jpeg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <div style="text-align: justify"> <p align="justify"> Fluminense had a solid defense in the competition, together with Botafogo it was the 3rd team that conceded the least goals in the tournament <b>(11)</b>, was the leader in duels won <b>(42.0%)</b> and in aerial duels <b>(50.2%)</b>, was tied with Flamengo as the one that made the fewest errors that led to shots <b>(31)</b> and was the 2nd club that took the fewest shots <b>(96)</b>. </p> <p align="justify"> Fernando Diniz's style was present in the championship, with Fluminense being the team with the most ball possession <b>(63.7%)</b>, with the most passes <b>(5843)</b> and 1st in passing accuracy <b>(91.0%)</b>, characteristic of the coach's game. Midfielder Jhon Arias was a fundamental part of the tricolor squad, having an offensive characteristic, the player was the team's leader in key passes <b>(16)</b>, and 8th in the entire competition, which did not correspond to more goals, given that the club scored the fewest goals in the G4 <b>(17)</b>. The club's attack was not satisfactory, being 7th in shots <b>(143)</b>, Fluminense demonstrated that despite the great exchange of passes, it did not create real opportunities, which resulted in a low number of goals. </p> <p align="justify"> Despite the quality defense, the Tricolor attack did not keep up with the performance that its midfield created. This became more evident in the classics, where Fluminense scored just 1 point from the 9 played, scoring 2 goals and conceding 6, more than half of what they conceded in the entire championship. Recopa champions, Fluminense will have work to do if they want to guarantee their third Carioca 2024 championship. </p> </div> <h2>Botafogo</h2> <div style="width: 80%; margin: 0 auto; text-align: center;"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2024-03-07-post_carioca_compilado/botafogo-en.jpeg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <div style="text-align: justify"> <p align="justify"> Botafogo had a good defense in the championship, with numbers of the G4, was the 2nd in duels won <b>(40.3%)</b>, the 3rd that committed the least errors that led to shots <b>(32)</b>, only 1 more than Flamengo and Fluminense, and also the 3rd that received the least shots <b>(101)</b>. And to complement the offensive sector, full-back Hugo did a great job creating the team's plays, being 1st in assists in the championship <b>(5)</b> and 7th in key passes <b>(18)</b>. </p> <p align="justify"> Taking less control of the game, Botafogo preferred to leave the ball with the opponent, being the only team from the Big 4 in Rio to have possession of the ball less than 50% <b>(49.6%)</b>, 5th in the championship in exchange of passes <b>(4357)</b>, 6th in the accuracy of these passes <b>(84.67%)</b> and 10th in accurate crosses <b>(30.9%)</b>. However, its attack proved to be quite efficient with individual plays, the club was 3rd in successful dribbles <b>(234)</b> and goals <b>(19)</b>, and 2nd in shots <b>(157 )</b>. </p> <p align="justify"> The Carioca Championship is decided in detail, and analyzing the numbers, we saw that Botafogo had an even better performance than Fluminense <b>(4th place)</b> in some statistics, however, the defeat to Boavista in the 3rd round It was decisive for the club not to qualify for the semi-finals of the tournament, opening space for Nova Iguaçu, the surprise of the competition. </p> </div> <h2>Semifinals</h2> <div style="text-align: justify"> <p align="justify"> The semifinals of the 2024 Carioca Championship promise to be exciting. Flamengo, the title favorite, faces Fluminense, which must overcome offensive deficiencies to surprise. </p> <p align="justify"> Nova Iguaçu, the surprise package, takes on Vasco, boasting a quality midfield that could be decisive for the team. </p> <p align="justify"> We will closely follow all the matches and provide analyses of the semifinals and the final of the Carioca 2024. Stay tuned! </p> </div>]]></content><author><name>Ace Laboratory Football Team</name></author><category term="Football;"/><category term="Analysis"/><category term="Football;"/><category term="Carioca;"/><category term="Analysis"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Se quiser ler este texto em pt-br, clique aqui.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Running — Part 2: How a Machine Learning model allows me, through an API, to level my runs</title><link href="https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2024/post_running_model/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Running — Part 2: How a Machine Learning model allows me, through an API, to level my runs"/><published>2024-03-01T12:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-03-01T12:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2024/post_running_model</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2024/post_running_model/"><![CDATA[<figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2024-03-01-post_running_model_Images/15.webp" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <p align="justify"> Recently, I did an exploratory analysis of my runs using data exported from the Nike Run Club app, and it helped me make better decisions in sport. I ran more, now having a better understanding of my training performance. All of this provided me insights that I decided to do more: I trained a model that clusters my runs and built an API that allows me to, with each new run, query this model to understand the "level" this run is, based on all my other runs. </p> <p>Introducing</p> <p align="justify"> As I already knew my data because the EDA I had done, the first step was to train the model. My goal was to find patterns in my runs, and once I found these patterns, I wanted to segment them in groups with different characteristics, so that, with each new run, I could identify which of these groups it would be included in. </p> <p align="justify"> There are many clustering algorithms, and like any other machine learning problem, there isn't the best approach. To simplify the selection process, in addition to experimentation, we must take in consideration some factors, as the characteristics of the clusters, the features of the dataset, and possible outliers. </p> <p align="justify"> In this case, I was familiar with my data in space and believed that one of the famous clustering algorithm could work well: <a href="https://scikit-learn.org/stable/modules/generated/sklearn.cluster.KMeans.html">K-Means</a>. Without going in too much details, K-Means is an algorithm that groups data in k clusters with same variance, minimizing inertia (sum of squared distances of samples to the nearest cluster center). However, like any other algorithm, it also has its limitations, and we need understand them in the evaluation process. </p> <p align="justify"> In short, the algorithm begins randomly generating k centroids (central points of clusters), to which each record is assigned based on the centroid with the smallest distance (forming a cluster). After that, the model calculates the average values of the points in each cluster and uses this value to reposition the centroids. This process is repeated until the positions of the centroids converge or a specified stopping criterion is met. In other words, as I wrote above, the goal of this task is to choose centroids that the inertia is minimized. It's important to note that as the initialization step is random (a non-deterministic algorithm), we should to execute multiple initializations with different centroid seeds to find the best result. </p> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2024-03-01-post_running_model_Images/16.gif" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <p align="justify"> As it's not the purpose of this post to address deeply about clustering algorithm, I take this opportunity to provide the entire <a href="https://scikit-learn.org/stable/modules/clustering.html">documentation</a> in scikit-learn. Additionally, you can find a great post on some of these algorithms in practice at this <a href="https://machinelearningmastery.com/clustering-algorithms-with-python/">link</a>. </p> <p>The model</p> <p align="justify"> As I have already realized data <a href="https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2024/post_running/">exploration</a> step, I will go straight to training the model. </p> <p align="justify"> Always remembering that in the preprocessing step, the features need to be resized to the same scale, what we call standardization. This process rescales the data to the set has a mean close to 0 and a standard deviation close to 1, optimizing the learning of distance-based algorithms. For this, I used the StandardScaler() function. </p> <p align="justify"> Regarding the algorithm, the K-Means doesn't "decide" the ideal number of clusters. We need to do that, and I used a simple technique: Elbow Method. When we increase the number of clusters, the inertia decreases, meaning the distance from each point to its nearest centroid becomes smaller. What we need is this distance as small as possible, as we need the optimal point that minimizes the number of clusters and the variance in each cluster. </p> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2024-03-01-post_running_model_Images/17.webp" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <p align="justify"> The plot above is a plot of inertia (within-clusters sum-of-squares - wcss) when we increase k. The "elbow" point indicates a kind of trade-off between error and the number of clusters, meaning when the wcss no longer significantly decreases with each iteration, and there aren't no substantial gains with an increase in k. For my problem, 5 would be the optimal number of k, but just to confirm, I used a package called kneed, that finds the point on the line where the curvature is maximum. </p> <div class="language-python highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="n">knl</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="nc">KneeLocator</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">n_cluster</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">wcss</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">curve</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="sh">"</span><span class="s">convex</span><span class="sh">"</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">direction</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="sh">"</span><span class="s">decreasing</span><span class="sh">"</span><span class="p">)</span>
<span class="n">knl</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="n">elbow</span>
</code></pre></div></div> <p align="justify"> According to the documentation, inertia can be recognized as a measure of how internally cohesive the clusters are, but it has some disadvantages: </p> <blockquote> Inertia makes the assumption that clusters are convex and isotropic, which is not always the case. It responds poorly to elongated clusters, or manifolds with irregular shapes.<br/><br/> Inertia is not a normalized metric: we just know that lower values are better and zero is optimal. But in very high-dimensional spaces, Euclidean distances tend to become inflated (this is an instance of the so-called “curse of dimensionality”). Running a dimensionality reduction algorithm such as Principal component analysis (PCA) prior to k-means clustering can alleviate this problem and speed up the computations. </blockquote> <p>Knowing the optimal number of clusters, I can adjust the model to the data:</p> <div class="language-python highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="n">km</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="nc">KMeans</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">n_clusters</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="mi">5</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">n_init</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="mi">30</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">random_state</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="mi">1</span><span class="p">)</span>
<span class="n">km</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">fit</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">X</span><span class="p">)</span>
</code></pre></div></div> <p align="justify"> With the trained model, I plotted a graph with the distance vs. pace of my races, already segmented in their respective interpreted clusters: </p> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2024-03-01-post_running_model_Images/18.webp" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <p>Finally, I saved:</p> <ul> <li>The trained model;</li> <li>The scaler;</li> <li>A dict with cluster labels.</li> </ul> <p>Building the API and making requests</p> <p align="justify"> To build the API I used Flask, a micro framework for web development and written in Python. It's very lightweight, simple to use and so much used for building Rest APIs. </p> <p>Creating the file.py</p> <p align="justify"> 1) Import of the necessary libraries and modules. I also imported the data_preparing.py file that I created in class format, which contains all the necessary transformations that the data needs for prediction;<br/> 2) Loading of the model and labels that were exported in the training process;<br/> 3) Assigning Flask in the variable app;<br/> 4) Creation of the endpoint that bring the prediction using the data passed through POST, which has been added to the variable 'data_json';<br/> 5) Initializing the Flask that will receive requests on port 5000, running locally. </p> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2024-03-01-post_running_model_Images/19.webp" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <p>With file.py ready, just start it in the terminal:</p> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2024-03-01-post_running_model_Images/20.webp" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <p align="justify"> To test it I will use Postman, a tool that allows to run API tests and make requests in general. To do this, I will take a data from some run that wasn't used in model training: </p> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2024-03-01-post_running_model_Images/21.webp" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <p>On Postman:</p> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2024-03-01-post_running_model_Images/22.webp" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <p align="justify"> At this moment, the model's response wasn't a surprise to me, because I knew my information (my sample of runs was small). However, as my dataset grows, it becomes a bit out of control, and that's where modeling shortens the paths. Another example of how a machine learning model can help us in real life. </p> <p align="justify"> The complete analysis code can be found on my <a href="https://github.com/nathaliatito">github</a>. </p> <p>References</p> <p>https://scikit-learn.org/stable/modules/clustering.html#k-means<br/> https://realpython.com/k-means-clustering-python/<br/> https://medium.com/data-hackers/como-fazer-uma-api-rest-para-modelos-de-m-l-com-flask-e-documenta%C3%A7%C3%A3o-swagger-7e74bfa19137</p>]]></content><author><name>Nathália Tito</name></author><category term="Running;"/><category term="Python;"/><category term="MachineLearning"/><category term="Running;"/><category term="Python;"/><category term="MachineLearning"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Deployed! Construction of an API for querying and evaluating the level of new races based on a previously trained clustering model]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Complex Networks on football</title><link href="https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2024/post_complex_network_football/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Complex Networks on football"/><published>2024-02-21T08:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-02-21T08:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2024/post_complex_network_football</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2024/post_complex_network_football/"><![CDATA[<figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2024-02-21-post_complex_network_football-Images/data-analysis-pass-network.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <p align="justify"> Complex networks, or science networks, is a concept in computer science that study objects and their interactions. The objects are usually called nodes, and the interactions are edges. The area has been used to investigate various subjects, such as social networks, biological networks, and transportation networks. This post will show how to use this area to analyze football matches. </p> <p align="justify"> The first thing we need to do is to define what we want to analyze in the football match. The most common analysis is to study the pass network. The passes network is a network where the nodes are the players, and the edges are the passes between the players. This network can be used to analyze the team's strategy, the players' performance, and the team's performance. The network can be studied using several metrics, such as degree, clustering coefficient, centrality, and betweenness. Besides the passes network, we can also analyze the distance network between the players. Here, we will focus on the passes network. </p> <p align="justify"> This post will focus on the theoretical aspects of Complex Networks and how to use it to analyze football matches. We will not show the code to analyze the matches. In a future post, we will demonstrate step-by-step how to analyze a football match using Complex Networks. </p> <h2 id="the-data">The Data</h2> <p align="justify"> To model your network, you must have an event dataset from the match. The event dataset is a dataset that contains all the events that occurred during the match, such as passes, shots, and fouls. Some sources for this type of dataset are StatsBomb, Wyscout, and Opta. Statsbomb provides these datasets for free in their <a href="https://github.com/statsbomb/open-data" target="_blank">github repository</a>. </p> <h2 id="modeling-the-network">Modeling the network</h2> <p align="justify"> To model a pass network, you must follow some steps: <ol> <li>Select the team that you want to analyze</li> <li>Filter to get only the passes</li> <li>They must have an outcome of success</li> <li>You can remove connections with less than a certain number of passes (optional)</li> <li>You can remove passes from set-pieces (optional)</li> </ol> The two last steps are optional because you may want to analyze the set pieces separately, and you may wish to filter meaningless passes. After this filtering, you must aggregate the data by the player that made the pass and the player that received the pass. This will give you the information necessary to prepare your network. </p> <p align="justify"> One observation is that your network must be directional. This means that the edges must have a direction, indicating the direction of the pass. This is important because the direction of the pass can give you information about the team's strategy. </p> <p align="justify"> After you have the data for your network, you can use a package like NetworkX to model your network. NetworkX is a Python package for the creation, manipulation, and study of the structure, dynamics, and functions of complex networks. The package provides tools to create and analyze the network. </p> <h2 id="analyzing-the-network">Analyzing the network</h2> <p align="justify"> With these steps done, you can start the analysis of your network. After that, one thing you can do is plot the network to observe how the objects (players) are connected. After that, you can use some metrics to understand some concepts of the match and team you are analyzing. The metrics we will describe here are: <ol> <li>Degree</li> <li>Clustering Coefficient</li> <li>Centrality</li> <ul> <li>Closeness</li> <li>Betweenness</li> </ul> <li>Hubs</li> <li>Authorities</li> <li>Pagerank</li> </ol> </p> <p align="justify"> So, let's go! </p> <h2 id="metrics">Metrics</h2> <p align="justify"> Before everything, it is essential to realize that when analyzing a game, you must bring some subjectives of the team to have a complete understanding of the match. The metrics can give you some insights, but the final analysis must consider how the team plays, the players' characteristics, and the match context. </p> <p align="justify"> Having a high or low value in a metric can mean different things depending on the team's strategy and the players' behaviour. You should explore the differences between the players, compare with the players' positions, and compare with the team's performance. Remember, it is a network, everything is connected. <h4>Degree</h4> <p align="justify"> The degree of a node is the number of edges connected to it (the number of passes). The degree can inform you how much that player was involved in the match. A player with a high degree can be considered a key player in the match. A player with a low degree can be viewed as a player who was not involved in the team's plays (can also be a strategy). Nowadays, we can consider the player who pivots the game as a key player with this metric, usually the midfielder. Kevin De Bruyne, for example, is a player with a high degree in the matches. </p> <p align="justify"> Degrees can be in and out. The in-degree is the number of passes received by the player, and the out-degree is the number of passes made by the player. <p align="justify"> In summary, the degree can inform you about the players' involvement in the match. </p> <h4>Clustering Coefficient</h4> <p align="justify"> The Clustering Coefficient is an interesting one. When playing football, you learn the importance of creating triangles between the players, appearing in the game, receiving the ball, and having options to pass. </p> <p align="justify"> It will give this information to you. It measures the degree to which nodes in a graph tend to cluster together. In the context of football, it can provide you with information about how the team is creating triangles and options to pass. </p> <p align="justify"> Briefly, the Clustering Coefficient can give you an understanding of how the team creates options to pass and triangulates the plays. </p> <h4>Closeness Centrality</h4> <p align="justify"> The Closeness Centrality measures the average shortest distance path between every player on the network. Regarding a pass network it can give you information about how the player is close to the other players in terms of passes. In other words, a player with a higher closeness centrality is a player that is more connected to the other players in the network. </p> <p align="justify"> An example can be a midfielder who constructs the plays and tends to have a higher closeness centrality. Another one is a center-forward can have a lower closeness centrality because he tends to be more isolated from the other players. We can say that Jorginho in Italy's national team has a high closeness centrality, he is always very near of every play. </p> <p align="justify"> In a nutshell, the Closeness Centrality can give you information about how the player is connected to the other players in the network. </p> <h4>Betweenness Centrality</h4> <p align="justify"> The Betweenness Centrality is a metric that measures the number of times a node acts as a bridge along the shortest path between two other nodes. Bringing it to our context can give you information about how the player connects to the other players in the network. </p> <p align="justify"> It is like the role that Busquets had in the Barcelona team. He was the player that connected the defense to the attack. He was the bridge between the two sectors of the team. </p> <p align="justify"> Short, Betweeness shows how the player is in the middle of the plays, connecting the other players. </p> <h4>Hubs and Authorities</h4> <p align="justify"> Hubs and Authorities are much exciting metrics for understanding the role of the players in the network. The Hubs are the players that make a lot of passes, and the Authorities are the players that receive a lot of passes. The concepts are simple, but the insights you can get from them can be unique. </p> <p align="justify"> Hubs are the players that are the source of the plays. In other words, they are the ones who create the plays and make passes. </p> <p align="justify"> Authorities are the players that are the target of the plays. They are the ones receiving the passes and probably finishing the plays. </p> <p align="justify"> You can combine those two metrics and compare them with the team's performance. What does it mean if you have a defender as a hub? What does it mean if you have a forward as an authority? The insights can be amazing. </p> <p align="justify"> An intuitive example is: back in the golden days of Barcelona, Messi was absolutely an authority in the Barcelona team meanwhile Xavi was a hub. Messi receives a lot of passes and finishes the plays, and Xavi is the source of the plays. </p> <h4>Pagerank</h4> <p align="justify"> Pagerank is an impressive algorithm created by Larry Page and Sergey Brin, the founders of Google. The algorithm was developed to rank web pages in the search engine. The algorithm is based on the idea that the importance of a web page can be measured by the number of pages that link to it. The more important the pages that link to a page, the more important the page is. </p> <p align="justify"> Bringing it to the football context, you can use the algorithm to rank the players in the network. Intuitively, the players showing a higher Pagerank are the most important players in the network. It can give you information that could be clearer just by looking at the passes network. </p> <p align="justify"> To sum things up, the Pagerank can give you information about the importance of the players in the network. </p> ## Conclusion <p align="justify"> In this post, we showed how to use Complex Networks to analyze football matches. We showed the steps to model the network and the metrics you can use to analyze the network. The metrics can give you information about the players' involvement in the match, the team's strategy, and the players' importance in the network. The analysis can give you insights that could be clearer just by looking at the match. In a future post, we will show how to analyze a football match using Complex Networks. </p> <p align="justify"> We hope you enjoyed the post. If you have any questions or comments, please leave them below. We will be happy to answer them. Keep following us to learn more about football and Complex Networks. </p> </p></p>]]></content><author><name>Balthazar Paixão</name></author><category term="Football;"/><category term="Complex_Networks"/><category term="Football;"/><category term="Complex_Networks;"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Using Complex Networks to analyze and understand football matches.]]></summary></entry></feed>