<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://ac3lab.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://ac3lab.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2024-03-18T13:58:50+00:00</updated><id>https://ac3lab.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">blank</title><subtitle>Marrying academic rigor with practical applications to benefit sports </subtitle><entry><title type="html">Carioca Championship 2024 - Semifinal - First Leg</title><link href="https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2024/post_carioca_semifinal_1/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Carioca Championship 2024 - Semifinal - First Leg"/><published>2024-03-15T13:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-03-15T13:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2024/post_carioca_semifinal_1</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2024/post_carioca_semifinal_1/"><![CDATA[<p align="justify"> Se quiser ler este texto em pt-br, <a href="https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2000/post_carioca_semifinal_1-pt/"> clique aqui.</a> </p> <h2>Introduction</h2> <div style="width: 55%; margin: 0 auto; text-align: center;"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2024-03-07-post_carioca_compilado/Carioca_2024_FERJ.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <div style="text-align: justify"> <p align="justify"> The Carioca Championship continues to surprise the Brazilian football, with Fluminense, Flamengo, Vasco, and Nova Iguaçu in the mix. The Ace Laboratory Football Team dives into the decisive matches, from Flamengo's dominance over Fluminense to Nova Iguaçu's unexpected offensive power trying to overcome the Vasco's "Wall", offering an exciting glimpse into the tournament's electrifying action. </p> </div> <h2>Fluminense x Flamengo</h2> <div style="text-align: justify"> <h3>Match Analysis</h3> <div style="width: 80%; margin: 0 auto; text-align: center;"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2024-03-15-post_carioca_semifinal_1/en/flaflugame.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <p align="justify"> Fluminense played a match below expectations against Flamengo, being constantly pressured, and failing to impose their style of play. This was the 1st match of the 2024 Carioca Championship in which the team ended the match with less ball possession than its opponent <b>(49% x 51%)</b>, with a weak performance from its attack, which did not make any shots to the goal defended by goalkeeper Agustín Rossi. Furthermore, the team committed a total of <b>11 errors that led to shots</b> in the game, and until this match, they had committed <b>31 errors</b> in the entire championship. </p> <p align="justify"> The rubro-negro, who had their greatest strength in the defensive sector, demonstrated that they also have high offensive capacity, making a total of <b>23 shots</b> in the match, with <b>9</b> of these shots being on Fábio's goal. If we consider the team's approximate time with the ball, we have a rate of <b>1 shot every 2 minutes</b> in possession of the ball. </p> <p align="justify"> The data showed complete dominance by Tite's team on the field, both in the defensive and offensive sectors, Flamengo created and did not let the opponent take advantage of the few chances they had. Fluminense will have a difficult job to qualify for the finals, scoring 3 goals against a team that only conceded 1 goal in the entire championship, for the next match coach Fernando Diniz will need to change his strategies, and possibly behave more aggressively if he wants to guarantee his place in the final. </p> <h3>Highlights</h3> <div style="width: 80%; margin: 0 auto; text-align: center;"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2024-03-15-post_carioca_semifinal_1/en/flafluplayers.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <p align="justify"> One of the ways to see how Fluminense played defensively was the positioning of Jhon Arias, a player who normally acts as a winger in an offensive way, ended up staying for most of the game on the tricolor field, playing on the right flank as a defender and unable to exploit his best qualities, his dribbling and his important passes. </p> <p align="justify"> Another point was the number of saves that goalkeeper Fábio had to make from shots from inside his area <b>(5)</b>, showing how effective Flamengo's creation was, and in large part this was due to Nicolás De La Cruz. The midfielder made a total of <b>6 key passes</b> for his team, playing mainly on the left side of the field, the side where the club took the most shots. </p> <p align="justify"> It is also worth noting the performance of striker Pedro, who took advantage of his team's opportunities, scoring <b>1 goal</b> at the end of the match, and making a total ofv<b>6 shots</b>, with <b>3</b> in the goal, having the opportunity to increase the score, if it weren't for the good performance of goalkeeper Fábio. </p> </div> <h2>Vasco x Nova Iguaçu</h2> <div style="text-align: justify"> <h3>Match Analysis</h3> <div style="width: 80%; margin: 0 auto; text-align: center;"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2024-03-15-post_carioca_semifinal_1/en/vasconovaiguacugame.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <p align="justify"> The two teams engaged in a match that, despite having only two goals, was marked by a large number of shots from both sides. The total number of shots is impressive for a semifinal match, especially when considering that the clash between Flamengo and Fluminense had only 31 shots, nearly 1.5 times fewer than the encounter between Vasco da Gama and Nova Iguaçu, which featured 45 shots total by the end of the game. </p> <p align="justify"> For Vasco, the offensive game was unusual, considering that the team has an average of 10.8 shots on goal in their last 5 games, yet they managed to shoot 21 times, with only 7 shots directed at goalkeeper Fabricio. Vasco’s midfield also demonstrated a lot of creativity reaching the attack, tallying 16 key passes throughout the first 90 minutes of the Carioca Championship semifinal. </p> <p align="justify"> For Nova Iguaçu, on the other hand, it was not a game much different from the usual experience in their last 5 games, as the team’s average number of shots in the Carioca Championship is 17 shots per game. The data observed in the match also shows the preference of Nova Iguaçu to shoot from outside the box, with more shots from outside <b>(13)</b> than from inside <b>(11)</b>, creating a lot of work, for the opposing goalkeeper. </p> <h3>Highlights</h3> <div style="width: 80%; margin: 0 auto; text-align: center;"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2024-03-15-post_carioca_semifinal_1/en/vasconovaiguacuplayers.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <p align="justify"> Undoubtedly, it was a highly contested match with several chances for both teams, and in this context, it is essential to highlight both the main chance creators and the main defenders of each team. </p> <p align="justify"> On Vasco’s side, with an incredible performance, the Frenchman Dimitri Payet stood out with an 88% pass accuracy rate, with 5 key passes executed solely by the former Olympique Marseille midfielder. Simultaneously, in the defensive sector, the attacking midfielder was also fundamental, with 12 duels won by the Cruz-Maltino and possessing a very participative heat map on the left side of the defensive third of the Gigante da Colina. </p> <p align="justify"> In a game with many shots and above-average performances, attackers who had good performances like Carlinhos, who shot on goal 5 times, were overshadowed by the miraculous performances of both teams' goalkeepers. Léo Jardim made incredible 14 saves, with 9 of these shots from inside the box, representing a total of 93% of balls saved, and even conceding one goal was considered the MOTM. While Fabricio, Nova Iguaçu's goalkeeper, despite "only" making 6 saves, with 50% of them coming from shots from inside the box, successfully completed 80% of long balls launched for the team's possession in the field, a characteristic that is increasingly needed in today's goalkeepers. </p> </div> <h2>Final Remarks</h2> <div style="text-align: justify"> <p align="justify"> The first two games of the semifinals are in the books. Flamengo has the advantage, and Fluminense will need a much better performance to reverse the score. Vasco, despite being saved by Leo Jardim's great performance, will need at least a simple victory to guarantee their place in the final. Nova Iguaçu, on the other hand, has the advantage of a draw. </p> <p align="justify"> The Ace Football Laboratory team will continue to follow the Carioca Championship, bringing detailed analysis of the games and the players. Stay tuned! </p> </div>]]></content><author><name>Ace Laboratory Football Team</name></author><category term="Football;"/><category term="Analysis"/><category term="Football;"/><category term="Carioca;"/><category term="Analysis"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Se quiser ler este texto em pt-br, clique aqui.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Odyssey of Women in the Olympic Games: A Data-Driven Tale</title><link href="https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2024/post_olympic_women/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Odyssey of Women in the Olympic Games: A Data-Driven Tale"/><published>2024-03-08T17:40:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-03-08T17:40:00+00:00</updated><id>https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2024/post_olympic_women</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2024/post_olympic_women/"><![CDATA[<h3 id="the-historical-march-of-womens-olympic-aspirations">The Historical March of Women’s Olympic Aspirations</h3> <p align="justify"> As 2024, an Olympic year, draws near, and on this International Women's Day, we take a moment to honor and reflect on the remarkable journey of women in the Olympic Games. This saga, marked by unyielding courage, monumental breakthroughs, and a shared quest for equality, resonates with the spirit of today's celebrations. It was in Paris, at the dawn of the 20th century, that 39 pioneering women first made their mark in the annals of the Olympics. Amidst a societal backdrop heavily shadowed by restrictive norms, these audacious women ventured into sports such as golf, tennis, and sailing, setting the stage for a revolution in the realm of athletics. From the silken swimsuits of the 1912 British swim team to the defiant establishment of the Women's Olympiad in the '20s, each leap forward was both a triumph over adversity and a step towards greater inclusion. Yet, it wasn't without setbacks. The 800m run controversy of 1928 and the subsequent exclusion of women from these events. </p> <p align="justify"> From the silken swimsuits of the 1912 British swim team to the defiant establishment of the Women's Olympiad in the '20s, each leap forward was both a triumph over adversity and a step towards greater inclusion. Yet, it wasn't without setbacks. The 800m run controversy of 1928 and the subsequent exclusion of women from these events. </p> <h3 id="the-data-driven-story-from-past-achievements-to-present-pursuits">The Data-Driven Story: From Past Achievements to Present Pursuits</h3> <p align="justify"> Our historical data shines a light on these formative years, displaying not just the numbers, but the narratives they represent—of initial hesitancy giving way to gradual acceptance. </p> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2024-03-08-post_olympic_women-Images/1.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <p align="justify"> Fast forward to the present, and we see a remarkable transformation. The recent Olympiads (2020) underscore a record-breaking surge, with women constituting over 49% of competitors winning medals—a testament to the indomitable spirit of countless female Olympians. </p> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2024-03-08-post_olympic_women-Images/2.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2024-03-08-post_olympic_women-Images/3.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <p align="justify"> As we marvel at these visual testaments of progress, it's clear the journey is far from over. Even as we acknowledge the soaring participation rates and celebrate the barriers broken, our data reveals a patchwork of investment in female athletes across nations. Some countries lead with burgeoning enthusiasm, while others reveal a hesitance to embrace the full potential of their female contenders. </p> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2024-03-08-post_olympic_women-Images/4.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <p align="justify"> The dashed line of ideal equality on our charts is more than a benchmark—it's a call to action. A call to support and elevate the role of women in sports, ensuring that the future of the Olympics is not just gender-balanced in participation but also in recognition, support, and celebration. </p> <h3 id="concluding-thoughts-a-salute-to-pioneers-and-a-vision-for-tomorrow">Concluding Thoughts: A Salute to Pioneers and a Vision for Tomorrow</h3> <p align="justify"> On this day, as we celebrate the monumental achievements of women across the globe, we turn our admiration towards the Olympians who've not only competed but have rewritten the history of sports. In the spirit of International Women's Day, we pay homage to trailblazers like Larisa Latynina, Birgit Fischer-Schmidt and Jenny Thompson, whose medal counts stand as towering testaments to female prowess and resilience in the face of adversity. </p> <p align="justify"> Their victories are not just etched in gold, silver, or bronze but are imprinted in the hearts of countless young girls who dare to dream bigger because of them. It is in their footsteps that the next generation will tread, inspired to leap higher, run faster, and push harder. </p> <p align="justify"> In their honor, and in the spirit of fostering a future where every girl has the opportunity to chase her Olympic dreams, we invite you to delve deeper into the evolution of women's participation in the Olympics. Our dashboard provides a comprehensive look at the strides made over the years, showcasing participation by National Olympic Committees (NOC) and by each Olympic Game. </p> <p align="justify"> Explore our dashboard and witness the journey of women in the Olympics: <a href="https://app.powerbi.com/view?r=eyJrIjoiY2M3ZGNjNzctMzMxYS00MjJhLThkM2ItODU5ODcxOGQ5Zjg0IiwidCI6IjhlZWNhNDA0LWE0N2QtNDU1NS1hMmQ0LTBmMzYxOTA0MWM5YyJ9" target="_blank">Women in Olympics</a>. </p>]]></content><author><name>Amanda Azevedo</name></author><category term="Olympics;"/><category term="PowerBI"/><category term="Olympics;"/><category term="Women;"/><category term="PowerBI"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A data-infused tribute on International Women's Day to female Olympians' journey, showcased in our dashboard, from 1900 Paris to the 2024 Olympics, underlining ongoing strides towards sports gender equality.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Carioca Championship 2024 - A compiled analysis</title><link href="https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2024/post_carioca_compilado/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Carioca Championship 2024 - A compiled analysis"/><published>2024-03-07T12:20:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-03-07T12:20:00+00:00</updated><id>https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2024/post_carioca_compilado</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2024/post_carioca_compilado/"><![CDATA[<p align="justify"> Se quiser ler este texto em pt-br, <a href="https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2000/post_carioca_compilado-pt/"> clique aqui.</a> </p> <h2>Introduction</h2> <div style="width: 65%; margin: 0 auto; text-align: center;"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2024-03-07-post_carioca_compilado/Carioca_2024_FERJ.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <div style="text-align: justify"> The 2024 Carioca Championship has reached the semifinal stage, and Ace Laboratory brings a compiled analysis of the four Rio giants and Nova Iguaçu, which had an impressive campaign and qualified for the final phase of the competition. Flamengo, leading the league stage, Nova Iguaçu, surprising everyone, Vasco, boasting a quality midfield, Fluminense, with a solid defense, and Botafogo, underperforming. Let's analyze the performance of each team and the individual highlights of the competition. </div> <div style="width: 80%; margin: 0 auto; text-align: center;"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2024-03-07-post_carioca_compilado/table.jpeg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <h2>Flamengo</h2> <div style="width: 80%; margin: 0 auto; text-align: center;"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2024-03-07-post_carioca_compilado/flamengo-en.jpeg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <div style="text-align: justify"> <p align="justify"> We can say that Flamengo's highlight in this championship was its defensive sector. The team conceded just 1 goal in the 11 matches of the competition, being the 3rd team with the best rate of duels won <b>(40.1%)</b> and the 2nd best if we only consider aerial duels <b>(49.4%)</b> . This security in duels, added to the quality of the players, made Flamengo the club that made the fewest mistakes that led to shots <b>(31)</b> and the one that took the least shots <b>(79)</b> from opponents, with more than 15 shots difference from 2nd place. </p> <p align="justify"> With Giorgian De Arrascaeta in midfield, Flamengo's offensive work was also impressive, the player is **above the 3rd quartile** in 6 of the 7 offensive categories we observed, being in the Top 10 of the championship in goals, assists and passes key. The rubro-negro likes to dictate the game and with that he managed to create many opportunities, he was 2nd with the most possession of the ball <b>(57.8%)</b>, 1st in the rate of successful crosses <b>(43.3%)</b> , 1st in goals scored <b>(23)</b> and 1st in shots <b>(178)</b>, with more than 20 shots ahead of 2nd place. </p> <p align="justify"> With this we saw Flamengo's dominance in the 2024 Carioca Championship, the team proved to be solid defensively, being the one that conceded the least goals, and solid offensively, being the one that scored the most goals. With the quality of their players, Flamengo will be favorites for the semi-final against Fluminense, and will be looking for the title undefeated. </p> </div> <h2>Nova Iguaçu</h2> <div style="width: 80%; margin: 0 auto; text-align: center;"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2024-03-07-post_carioca_compilado/nova-iguacu-en.jpeg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <div style="text-align: justify"> <p align="justify"> The Nova Iguaçu team surprised many with the second-best performance in the league stage of the Carioca Championship. The team does not have a good average in overall defensive metrics, having the lowest possession average among the qualified teams <b>(7th in the entire league)</b>, the highest foul rate, and conceding a total of thirteen goals. The key factor for Nova Iguaçu's victories was capitalizing on their shots on goal and converting chances into goals. </p> <p align="justify"> Midfielder Bill was the standout player for the team in the competition. The athlete ranked <b>1st</b> in assists, key passes, and successful dribbles for the team, highlighting his importance throughout the championship. The radar chart below also illustrates the player's versatility in defense, playmaking, and finishing. </p> <p align="justify"> With 24 points, seven wins, three draws, and only one defeat, the "Clockwork Orange" team from the Baixada qualifies for the semifinals and eliminates one of the Rio giants. Just like in the league stage, Nova Iguaçu will need to capitalize on their chances to surprise Vasco and reach the final of the Carioca 2024. </p> </div> <h2>Vasco</h2> <div style="width: 80%; margin: 0 auto; text-align: center;"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2024-03-07-post_carioca_compilado/vasco-en.jpeg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <div style="text-align: justify"> <p align="justify"> Vasco da Gama's championship was marked by its attack, ranking as the <b>2nd</b> highest-scoring team in the tournament with a total of 20 goals. With a team that maintains ball possession and precision in its passes, Vasco was the <b>3rd</b> team with the most possession <b>(55%)</b>, 3rd in passes <b>(5290)</b>, and 3rd in pass accuracy <b>(87.7%)</b>. </p> <p align="justify"> The standout player of the team is none other than the Frenchman Dimitri Payet. The midfielder was the team's <b>2nd</b> highest scorer, <b>1st</b> in assists, and <b>1st</b> in key passes. Looking at the radar chart, we can see that the player plays a crucial role in creating and finishing plays. Payet was a fundamental piece for Vasco during the league stage and will be essential for the team in the semifinal against Nova Iguaçu. </p> <p align="justify"> For the semifinals, Vasco will need to maintain the quality that its midfield and attack have shown in the recent matches of the tournament to avoid surprises and secure a spot in the final of the Carioca 2024. </p> </div> <h2>Fluminense</h2> <div style="width: 80%; margin: 0 auto; text-align: center;"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2024-03-07-post_carioca_compilado/fluminense-en.jpeg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <div style="text-align: justify"> <p align="justify"> Fluminense had a solid defense in the competition, together with Botafogo it was the 3rd team that conceded the least goals in the tournament <b>(11)</b>, was the leader in duels won <b>(42.0%)</b> and in aerial duels <b>(50.2%)</b>, was tied with Flamengo as the one that made the fewest errors that led to shots <b>(31)</b> and was the 2nd club that took the fewest shots <b>(96)</b>. </p> <p align="justify"> Fernando Diniz's style was present in the championship, with Fluminense being the team with the most ball possession <b>(63.7%)</b>, with the most passes <b>(5843)</b> and 1st in passing accuracy <b>(91.0%)</b>, characteristic of the coach's game. Midfielder Jhon Arias was a fundamental part of the tricolor squad, having an offensive characteristic, the player was the team's leader in key passes <b>(16)</b>, and 8th in the entire competition, which did not correspond to more goals, given that the club scored the fewest goals in the G4 <b>(17)</b>. The club's attack was not satisfactory, being 7th in shots <b>(143)</b>, Fluminense demonstrated that despite the great exchange of passes, it did not create real opportunities, which resulted in a low number of goals. </p> <p align="justify"> Despite the quality defense, the Tricolor attack did not keep up with the performance that its midfield created. This became more evident in the classics, where Fluminense scored just 1 point from the 9 played, scoring 2 goals and conceding 6, more than half of what they conceded in the entire championship. Recopa champions, Fluminense will have work to do if they want to guarantee their third Carioca 2024 championship. </p> </div> <h2>Botafogo</h2> <div style="width: 80%; margin: 0 auto; text-align: center;"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2024-03-07-post_carioca_compilado/botafogo-en.jpeg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <div style="text-align: justify"> <p align="justify"> Botafogo had a good defense in the championship, with numbers of the G4, was the 2nd in duels won <b>(40.3%)</b>, the 3rd that committed the least errors that led to shots <b>(32)</b>, only 1 more than Flamengo and Fluminense, and also the 3rd that received the least shots <b>(101)</b>. And to complement the offensive sector, full-back Hugo did a great job creating the team's plays, being 1st in assists in the championship <b>(5)</b> and 7th in key passes <b>(18)</b>. </p> <p align="justify"> Taking less control of the game, Botafogo preferred to leave the ball with the opponent, being the only team from the Big 4 in Rio to have possession of the ball less than 50% <b>(49.6%)</b>, 5th in the championship in exchange of passes <b>(4357)</b>, 6th in the accuracy of these passes <b>(84.67%)</b> and 10th in accurate crosses <b>(30.9%)</b>. However, its attack proved to be quite efficient with individual plays, the club was 3rd in successful dribbles <b>(234)</b> and goals <b>(19)</b>, and 2nd in shots <b>(157 )</b>. </p> <p align="justify"> The Carioca Championship is decided in detail, and analyzing the numbers, we saw that Botafogo had an even better performance than Fluminense <b>(4th place)</b> in some statistics, however, the defeat to Boavista in the 3rd round It was decisive for the club not to qualify for the semi-finals of the tournament, opening space for Nova Iguaçu, the surprise of the competition. </p> </div> <h2>Semifinals</h2> <div style="text-align: justify"> <p align="justify"> The semifinals of the 2024 Carioca Championship promise to be exciting. Flamengo, the title favorite, faces Fluminense, which must overcome offensive deficiencies to surprise. </p> <p align="justify"> Nova Iguaçu, the surprise package, takes on Vasco, boasting a quality midfield that could be decisive for the team. </p> <p align="justify"> We will closely follow all the matches and provide analyses of the semifinals and the final of the Carioca 2024. Stay tuned! </p> </div>]]></content><author><name>Ace Laboratory Football Team</name></author><category term="Football;"/><category term="Analysis"/><category term="Football;"/><category term="Carioca;"/><category term="Analysis"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Se quiser ler este texto em pt-br, clique aqui.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Running — Part 2: How a Machine Learning model allows me, through an API, to level my runs</title><link href="https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2024/post_running_model/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Running — Part 2: How a Machine Learning model allows me, through an API, to level my runs"/><published>2024-03-01T12:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-03-01T12:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2024/post_running_model</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2024/post_running_model/"><![CDATA[<figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2024-03-01-post_running_model_Images/15.webp" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <p align="justify"> Recently, I did an exploratory analysis of my runs using data exported from the Nike Run Club app, and it helped me make better decisions in sport. I ran more, now having a better understanding of my training performance. All of this provided me insights that I decided to do more: I trained a model that clusters my runs and built an API that allows me to, with each new run, query this model to understand the "level" this run is, based on all my other runs. </p> <p>Introducing</p> <p align="justify"> As I already knew my data because the EDA I had done, the first step was to train the model. My goal was to find patterns in my runs, and once I found these patterns, I wanted to segment them in groups with different characteristics, so that, with each new run, I could identify which of these groups it would be included in. </p> <p align="justify"> There are many clustering algorithms, and like any other machine learning problem, there isn't the best approach. To simplify the selection process, in addition to experimentation, we must take in consideration some factors, as the characteristics of the clusters, the features of the dataset, and possible outliers. </p> <p align="justify"> In this case, I was familiar with my data in space and believed that one of the famous clustering algorithm could work well: <a href="https://scikit-learn.org/stable/modules/generated/sklearn.cluster.KMeans.html">K-Means</a>. Without going in too much details, K-Means is an algorithm that groups data in k clusters with same variance, minimizing inertia (sum of squared distances of samples to the nearest cluster center). However, like any other algorithm, it also has its limitations, and we need understand them in the evaluation process. </p> <p align="justify"> In short, the algorithm begins randomly generating k centroids (central points of clusters), to which each record is assigned based on the centroid with the smallest distance (forming a cluster). After that, the model calculates the average values of the points in each cluster and uses this value to reposition the centroids. This process is repeated until the positions of the centroids converge or a specified stopping criterion is met. In other words, as I wrote above, the goal of this task is to choose centroids that the inertia is minimized. It's important to note that as the initialization step is random (a non-deterministic algorithm), we should to execute multiple initializations with different centroid seeds to find the best result. </p> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2024-03-01-post_running_model_Images/16.gif" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <p align="justify"> As it's not the purpose of this post to address deeply about clustering algorithm, I take this opportunity to provide the entire <a href="https://scikit-learn.org/stable/modules/clustering.html">documentation</a> in scikit-learn. Additionally, you can find a great post on some of these algorithms in practice at this <a href="https://machinelearningmastery.com/clustering-algorithms-with-python/">link</a>. </p> <p>The model</p> <p align="justify"> As I have already realized data <a href="https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2024/post_running/">exploration</a> step, I will go straight to training the model. </p> <p align="justify"> Always remembering that in the preprocessing step, the features need to be resized to the same scale, what we call standardization. This process rescales the data to the set has a mean close to 0 and a standard deviation close to 1, optimizing the learning of distance-based algorithms. For this, I used the StandardScaler() function. </p> <p align="justify"> Regarding the algorithm, the K-Means doesn't "decide" the ideal number of clusters. We need to do that, and I used a simple technique: Elbow Method. When we increase the number of clusters, the inertia decreases, meaning the distance from each point to its nearest centroid becomes smaller. What we need is this distance as small as possible, as we need the optimal point that minimizes the number of clusters and the variance in each cluster. </p> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2024-03-01-post_running_model_Images/17.webp" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <p align="justify"> The plot above is a plot of inertia (within-clusters sum-of-squares - wcss) when we increase k. The "elbow" point indicates a kind of trade-off between error and the number of clusters, meaning when the wcss no longer significantly decreases with each iteration, and there aren't no substantial gains with an increase in k. For my problem, 5 would be the optimal number of k, but just to confirm, I used a package called kneed, that finds the point on the line where the curvature is maximum. </p> <div class="language-python highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="n">knl</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="nc">KneeLocator</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">n_cluster</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">wcss</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">curve</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="sh">"</span><span class="s">convex</span><span class="sh">"</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">direction</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="sh">"</span><span class="s">decreasing</span><span class="sh">"</span><span class="p">)</span>
<span class="n">knl</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="n">elbow</span>
</code></pre></div></div> <p align="justify"> According to the documentation, inertia can be recognized as a measure of how internally cohesive the clusters are, but it has some disadvantages: </p> <blockquote> Inertia makes the assumption that clusters are convex and isotropic, which is not always the case. It responds poorly to elongated clusters, or manifolds with irregular shapes.<br/><br/> Inertia is not a normalized metric: we just know that lower values are better and zero is optimal. But in very high-dimensional spaces, Euclidean distances tend to become inflated (this is an instance of the so-called “curse of dimensionality”). Running a dimensionality reduction algorithm such as Principal component analysis (PCA) prior to k-means clustering can alleviate this problem and speed up the computations. </blockquote> <p>Knowing the optimal number of clusters, I can adjust the model to the data:</p> <div class="language-python highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="n">km</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="nc">KMeans</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">n_clusters</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="mi">5</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">n_init</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="mi">30</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">random_state</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="mi">1</span><span class="p">)</span>
<span class="n">km</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">fit</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">X</span><span class="p">)</span>
</code></pre></div></div> <p align="justify"> With the trained model, I plotted a graph with the distance vs. pace of my races, already segmented in their respective interpreted clusters: </p> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2024-03-01-post_running_model_Images/18.webp" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <p>Finally, I saved:</p> <ul> <li>The trained model;</li> <li>The scaler;</li> <li>A dict with cluster labels.</li> </ul> <p>Building the API and making requests</p> <p align="justify"> To build the API I used Flask, a micro framework for web development and written in Python. It's very lightweight, simple to use and so much used for building Rest APIs. </p> <p>Creating the file.py</p> <p align="justify"> 1) Import of the necessary libraries and modules. I also imported the data_preparing.py file that I created in class format, which contains all the necessary transformations that the data needs for prediction;<br/> 2) Loading of the model and labels that were exported in the training process;<br/> 3) Assigning Flask in the variable app;<br/> 4) Creation of the endpoint that bring the prediction using the data passed through POST, which has been added to the variable 'data_json';<br/> 5) Initializing the Flask that will receive requests on port 5000, running locally. </p> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2024-03-01-post_running_model_Images/19.webp" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <p>With file.py ready, just start it in the terminal:</p> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2024-03-01-post_running_model_Images/20.webp" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <p align="justify"> To test it I will use Postman, a tool that allows to run API tests and make requests in general. To do this, I will take a data from some run that wasn't used in model training: </p> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2024-03-01-post_running_model_Images/21.webp" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <p>On Postman:</p> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2024-03-01-post_running_model_Images/22.webp" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <p align="justify"> At this moment, the model's response wasn't a surprise to me, because I knew my information (my sample of runs was small). However, as my dataset grows, it becomes a bit out of control, and that's where modeling shortens the paths. Another example of how a machine learning model can help us in real life. </p> <p align="justify"> The complete analysis code can be found on my <a href="https://github.com/nathaliatito">github</a>. </p> <p>References</p> <p>https://scikit-learn.org/stable/modules/clustering.html#k-means<br/> https://realpython.com/k-means-clustering-python/<br/> https://medium.com/data-hackers/como-fazer-uma-api-rest-para-modelos-de-m-l-com-flask-e-documenta%C3%A7%C3%A3o-swagger-7e74bfa19137</p>]]></content><author><name>Nathália Tito</name></author><category term="Running;"/><category term="Python;"/><category term="MachineLearning"/><category term="Running;"/><category term="Python;"/><category term="MachineLearning"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Deployed! Construction of an API for querying and evaluating the level of new races based on a previously trained clustering model]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Complex Networks on football</title><link href="https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2024/post_complex_network_football/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Complex Networks on football"/><published>2024-02-21T08:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-02-21T08:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2024/post_complex_network_football</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2024/post_complex_network_football/"><![CDATA[<figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2024-02-21-post_complex_network_football-Images/data-analysis-pass-network.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <p align="justify"> Complex networks, or science networks, is a concept in computer science that study objects and their interactions. The objects are usually called nodes, and the interactions are edges. The area has been used to investigate various subjects, such as social networks, biological networks, and transportation networks. This post will show how to use this area to analyze football matches. </p> <p align="justify"> The first thing we need to do is to define what we want to analyze in the football match. The most common analysis is to study the pass network. The passes network is a network where the nodes are the players, and the edges are the passes between the players. This network can be used to analyze the team's strategy, the players' performance, and the team's performance. The network can be studied using several metrics, such as degree, clustering coefficient, centrality, and betweenness. Besides the passes network, we can also analyze the distance network between the players. Here, we will focus on the passes network. </p> <p align="justify"> This post will focus on the theoretical aspects of Complex Networks and how to use it to analyze football matches. We will not show the code to analyze the matches. In a future post, we will demonstrate step-by-step how to analyze a football match using Complex Networks. </p> <h2 id="the-data">The Data</h2> <p align="justify"> To model your network, you must have an event dataset from the match. The event dataset is a dataset that contains all the events that occurred during the match, such as passes, shots, and fouls. Some sources for this type of dataset are StatsBomb, Wyscout, and Opta. Statsbomb provides these datasets for free in their <a href="https://github.com/statsbomb/open-data" target="_blank">github repository</a>. </p> <h2 id="modeling-the-network">Modeling the network</h2> <p align="justify"> To model a pass network, you must follow some steps: <ol> <li>Select the team that you want to analyze</li> <li>Filter to get only the passes</li> <li>They must have an outcome of success</li> <li>You can remove connections with less than a certain number of passes (optional)</li> <li>You can remove passes from set-pieces (optional)</li> </ol> The two last steps are optional because you may want to analyze the set pieces separately, and you may wish to filter meaningless passes. After this filtering, you must aggregate the data by the player that made the pass and the player that received the pass. This will give you the information necessary to prepare your network. </p> <p align="justify"> One observation is that your network must be directional. This means that the edges must have a direction, indicating the direction of the pass. This is important because the direction of the pass can give you information about the team's strategy. </p> <p align="justify"> After you have the data for your network, you can use a package like NetworkX to model your network. NetworkX is a Python package for the creation, manipulation, and study of the structure, dynamics, and functions of complex networks. The package provides tools to create and analyze the network. </p> <h2 id="analyzing-the-network">Analyzing the network</h2> <p align="justify"> With these steps done, you can start the analysis of your network. After that, one thing you can do is plot the network to observe how the objects (players) are connected. After that, you can use some metrics to understand some concepts of the match and team you are analyzing. The metrics we will describe here are: <ol> <li>Degree</li> <li>Clustering Coefficient</li> <li>Centrality</li> <ul> <li>Closeness</li> <li>Betweenness</li> </ul> <li>Hubs</li> <li>Authorities</li> <li>Pagerank</li> </ol> </p> <p align="justify"> So, let's go! </p> <h2 id="metrics">Metrics</h2> <p align="justify"> Before everything, it is essential to realize that when analyzing a game, you must bring some subjectives of the team to have a complete understanding of the match. The metrics can give you some insights, but the final analysis must consider how the team plays, the players' characteristics, and the match context. </p> <p align="justify"> Having a high or low value in a metric can mean different things depending on the team's strategy and the players' behaviour. You should explore the differences between the players, compare with the players' positions, and compare with the team's performance. Remember, it is a network, everything is connected. <h4>Degree</h4> <p align="justify"> The degree of a node is the number of edges connected to it (the number of passes). The degree can inform you how much that player was involved in the match. A player with a high degree can be considered a key player in the match. A player with a low degree can be viewed as a player who was not involved in the team's plays (can also be a strategy). Nowadays, we can consider the player who pivots the game as a key player with this metric, usually the midfielder. Kevin De Bruyne, for example, is a player with a high degree in the matches. </p> <p align="justify"> Degrees can be in and out. The in-degree is the number of passes received by the player, and the out-degree is the number of passes made by the player. <p align="justify"> In summary, the degree can inform you about the players' involvement in the match. </p> <h4>Clustering Coefficient</h4> <p align="justify"> The Clustering Coefficient is an interesting one. When playing football, you learn the importance of creating triangles between the players, appearing in the game, receiving the ball, and having options to pass. </p> <p align="justify"> It will give this information to you. It measures the degree to which nodes in a graph tend to cluster together. In the context of football, it can provide you with information about how the team is creating triangles and options to pass. </p> <p align="justify"> Briefly, the Clustering Coefficient can give you an understanding of how the team creates options to pass and triangulates the plays. </p> <h4>Closeness Centrality</h4> <p align="justify"> The Closeness Centrality measures the average shortest distance path between every player on the network. Regarding a pass network it can give you information about how the player is close to the other players in terms of passes. In other words, a player with a higher closeness centrality is a player that is more connected to the other players in the network. </p> <p align="justify"> An example can be a midfielder who constructs the plays and tends to have a higher closeness centrality. Another one is a center-forward can have a lower closeness centrality because he tends to be more isolated from the other players. We can say that Jorginho in Italy's national team has a high closeness centrality, he is always very near of every play. </p> <p align="justify"> In a nutshell, the Closeness Centrality can give you information about how the player is connected to the other players in the network. </p> <h4>Betweenness Centrality</h4> <p align="justify"> The Betweenness Centrality is a metric that measures the number of times a node acts as a bridge along the shortest path between two other nodes. Bringing it to our context can give you information about how the player connects to the other players in the network. </p> <p align="justify"> It is like the role that Busquets had in the Barcelona team. He was the player that connected the defense to the attack. He was the bridge between the two sectors of the team. </p> <p align="justify"> Short, Betweeness shows how the player is in the middle of the plays, connecting the other players. </p> <h4>Hubs and Authorities</h4> <p align="justify"> Hubs and Authorities are much exciting metrics for understanding the role of the players in the network. The Hubs are the players that make a lot of passes, and the Authorities are the players that receive a lot of passes. The concepts are simple, but the insights you can get from them can be unique. </p> <p align="justify"> Hubs are the players that are the source of the plays. In other words, they are the ones who create the plays and make passes. </p> <p align="justify"> Authorities are the players that are the target of the plays. They are the ones receiving the passes and probably finishing the plays. </p> <p align="justify"> You can combine those two metrics and compare them with the team's performance. What does it mean if you have a defender as a hub? What does it mean if you have a forward as an authority? The insights can be amazing. </p> <p align="justify"> An intuitive example is: back in the golden days of Barcelona, Messi was absolutely an authority in the Barcelona team meanwhile Xavi was a hub. Messi receives a lot of passes and finishes the plays, and Xavi is the source of the plays. </p> <h4>Pagerank</h4> <p align="justify"> Pagerank is an impressive algorithm created by Larry Page and Sergey Brin, the founders of Google. The algorithm was developed to rank web pages in the search engine. The algorithm is based on the idea that the importance of a web page can be measured by the number of pages that link to it. The more important the pages that link to a page, the more important the page is. </p> <p align="justify"> Bringing it to the football context, you can use the algorithm to rank the players in the network. Intuitively, the players showing a higher Pagerank are the most important players in the network. It can give you information that could be clearer just by looking at the passes network. </p> <p align="justify"> To sum things up, the Pagerank can give you information about the importance of the players in the network. </p> ## Conclusion <p align="justify"> In this post, we showed how to use Complex Networks to analyze football matches. We showed the steps to model the network and the metrics you can use to analyze the network. The metrics can give you information about the players' involvement in the match, the team's strategy, and the players' importance in the network. The analysis can give you insights that could be clearer just by looking at the match. In a future post, we will show how to analyze a football match using Complex Networks. </p> <p align="justify"> We hope you enjoyed the post. If you have any questions or comments, please leave them below. We will be happy to answer them. Keep following us to learn more about football and Complex Networks. </p> </p></p>]]></content><author><name>Balthazar Paixão</name></author><category term="Football;"/><category term="Complex_Networks"/><category term="Football;"/><category term="Complex_Networks;"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Using Complex Networks to analyze and understand football matches.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Analyzing Complex Network metrics from the 1958 World Cup final</title><link href="https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2024/post_58_worldcup_final/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Analyzing Complex Network metrics from the 1958 World Cup final"/><published>2024-01-17T16:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-01-17T16:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2024/post_58_worldcup_final</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2024/post_58_worldcup_final/"><![CDATA[<figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2024-01-17-post_58_worldcup_final-Images/pele1958.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <p align="justify"> The World Cup is the most important football competition in the world. It is held every four years and gathers the best national teams in the world. The first edition of the competition was held in 1930, in Uruguay, and since then, the competition has been held every four years, except in 1942 and 1946, due to World War II. The competition is organized by FIFA (Fédération Internationale de Football Association), the world's football governing body. </p> <p align="justify"> The 1958 World Cup was the sixth edition of the competition and was held in Sweden. The competition was attended by 16 teams, which were divided into four groups of four teams each. The first two teams in each group advanced to the quarterfinals. The competition was won by Brazil, which beat Sweden 5-2 in the final. The Brazilian team was led by the legendary Pelé, who was only 17 years old at the time. </p> <p align="justify"> This post aims to analyze the 1958 World Cup final passes networks between the Brazilian players. The data used in this post was obtained from the <a href="https://github.com/statsbomb/open-data" target="_blank">StatsBomb Open Data</a> repository. We will explore some Complex Network metrics to investigate the Brazilian team's passing network in the final match. Let's code! </p> <p>Data extraction</p> <p align="justify"> The data extraction process can be considered the easiest one. It is because Statsbomb provides a Python package called <a href="https://github.com/statsbomb/statsbombpy" target="_blank">statsbombpy</a> that allows us to extract the data directly from the repository based on the match_id that they provide in the repository. The extraction would be as follows: </p> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2024-01-17-post_58_worldcup_final-Images/data-extration-statsbombpy.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <p>Data preparation (to the passes network)</p> <p align="justify"> With the DataFrame from avents loaded, we can begin creating a class for the players and a function to get all the Starting XI players from the match (the ones that we will use in the passes network). The class for the players is as follows: </p> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2024-01-17-post_58_worldcup_final-Images/data-preparation-player-class.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <p align="justify"> Using our DataFrame we want to filter the data following some criteria, so: <ol> <li>The event must be a pass</li> <li>It cannot be a pass from set-pieces</li> <li>And it must have an outcome of success</li> </ol> </p> <p align="justify"> After this filtering, we aggregate the data by the player that made the pass and the player that received the pass. And that's it, we have our passes network. </p> <p>Analysis</p> <p align="justify"> Now that we have our passes network, we can start the analysis. The first thing we can do is to plot the network. We can do this using the <a href="https://networkx.org/" target="_blank">NetworkX</a> package. The result will be like this: </p> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2024-01-17-post_58_worldcup_final-Images/data-analysis-pass-network-simple.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <p align="justify"> Yeah... It's not very informative. We can see that Pelé is the player who receives the most passes, but we can't extract much information from this plot. So, let's try to improve it... </p> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2024-01-17-post_58_worldcup_final-Images/data-analysis-pass-network.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <p align="justify"> Much better! Now we can see that Pelé and Vavá are occupying almost the same average position in the field. We can also see some differences compared with modern football. For example, there is no player with an average position in the center of the field. </p> <p>Complex Network metrics</p> <p align="justify"> As could be noted, we explore the creation of a pass network where our graph is a DiGraph, i.e., a directed graph. This is because we are interested in the direction of the passes. Given that, we can explore some Complex Network metrics to investigate the Brazilian team's passing network in the final match and their behavior. </p> <p>Degrees</p> <p align="justify"> The degree of a node is the number of edges incident to the node, the passes between the players. The player that showed the lowest degree was, unexpectedly, Bellini; and the player that showed the highest degree was Waldir. This could indicate how Brazil was exploiting spaces on the right side of the field. The average degree was 14.2. One interesting thing is that Pelé is not the player that received the most passes, the player is Garrincha. </p> <p>Clustering Coefficient</p> <p align="justify"> Clustering indicates how close a node and its neighbors are to being a clique. In our case, it indicates how close a player and his teammates are to being a clique (a group of players that pass the ball between them). The player that showed the highest clustering coefficient was Pelé. This could indicate that Pelé was the player that was more involved in the passing game. The lowest clustering coefficient was shown by Gylmar, the goalkeeper, which is expected. </p> <p>Closeness Centrality</p> <p align="justify"> Closeness centrality indicates how close a node is to all other nodes in the network. In our case, it indicates how close a player is to all other players in the network. The player that showed the highest closeness centrality was Garrincha, one of the most important players regarding dribbling and creating chances. The lowest closeness centrality was shown by Bellini, as the game was not being explored on his side of the field based on our theory. </p> <p>Betweenness Centrality</p> <p align="justify"> Betweenness centrality indicates how often a node appears on a shortest path between two other nodes. In our case, it indicates how often a player appears on a shortest path between two other players. The player that showed the highest betweenness centrality was Waldir, while the lowest betweenness centrality was shown by Bellini, which indicates that our beliefs are correct. </p> <p>Hubs and Authorities</p> <p align="justify"> Hubs and Authorities are two metrics that are used to identify how the degrees are distributed between the nodes in a network. The Hubs metric identifies the nodes that passed the ball the most, while the Authorities metric identifies the nodes that received the ball the most. The player that showed the highest Hubs metric was Waldir, and the player that showed the highest Authorities metric was Pelé. This indicates that Waldir was the player who passed the ball the most, while Pelé was the player who received the ball the most. </p> <p>Pagerank</p> <p align="justify"> Pagerank is a metric that is used to identify the nodes that are more important in a network. The player that showed the highest Pagerank was Pelé, and the player that showed the lowest Pagerank was Bellini. This indicates that Pelé was the player that was more important in the network, while Bellini was the player that was less important in the network. </p> <p>Conclusion</p> <p align="justify"> In this post, we analyzed the 1958 World Cup final passes network between the Brazilian players. We explored some Complex Network metrics to investigate the Brazilian team's passing network in the final match and their behavior. We found that Pelé, Garrincha and Waldir showed a great importance in the network, while Bellini and Gylmar showed a low importance in the network. We also found that Brazil was exploiting spaces on the right side of the field. </p> <p align="justify"> I hope you enjoyed this post and could learn a little bit more about complex networks. If you have any questions or suggestions, please leave a comment below. The complete analysis code can be found on the <a href="https://github.com/balthapaixao/football-networks/blob/main/analysis/others/public/complex-network-analysis-1958-brazil.ipynb ">notebook</a>. </p>]]></content><author><name>Balthazar Paixão</name></author><category term="Football;"/><category term="Python"/><category term="Football;"/><category term="World_Cup;"/><category term="Python"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Investigating the 1958 World Cup final match between Brazil and Sweden using Complex Network metrics.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Running — Part 1: Extracting my Nike Run Club data and exploring in python to evaluate my performance</title><link href="https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2024/post_running/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Running — Part 1: Extracting my Nike Run Club data and exploring in python to evaluate my performance"/><published>2024-01-06T11:12:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-01-06T11:12:00+00:00</updated><id>https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2024/post_running</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2024/post_running/"><![CDATA[<figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2024-01-06-post_running-Images/1.webp" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <p align="justify"> Anyone who knows me knows that I love sport. Since I was a kid, I always was influenced to practice something and never went long without it. Some sports I've played: swimming, futsal, handball (I still play) and now running, my most recent addiction. </p> <p align="justify"> A few months ago, running has become part of my routine. Every week I try to run 2 or 3 times, and always outdoors (I hate treadmills with all my might). To measure my performance, I have been running with the Nike Run Club (NRC) app and recording my runs on it. Looking my data in the app, I felt the need to do more, some analysis of my performance. And is here that another passion comes into to play: data science. </p> <p align="justify"> Anyone who also knows me knows that I am a data scientist and rarely believe in anything or make any decision without evidence. It's a bit of cliche, but analyzing everything is also part of my routine, and so, why not bring the data to my side, and like this, who knows, it can help me make decisions that get better my results? This is what I want to start to test. Let's code! </p> <p>Data extraction</p> <p align="justify"> Firstly, I needed the data from my runs. Doing a quick research, I realized that Nike didn't officially instrument to data export, and for get it would be necessary to take alternative paths. </p> <p align="justify"> I used a program called nrc-exporter (created by some curious programmer), and it exports data to a local directory easily and quickly. As a first step, we need to install the program in the terminal using pip install nrc-exporter. The annoying part is that we need to provide the program with authentication tokens that Nike generates when you do a login, what is simple but so manual. </p> <p align="justify"> 1) Go to the Nike website and do a login normally;<br/> 2) Open Developer tools &gt; Application. Then just copy the token like this image: </p> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2024-01-06-post_running-Images/2.webp" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <p align="justify"> Now, back in the terminal, just run nrc-exporter with the token, like this: </p> <p>nrc-exporter -t token</p> <p>You will see this execution:</p> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2024-01-06-post_running-Images/3.webp" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <p align="justify"> It's ready! All data will be downloaded to a folder called activities and will be inside the folder where you run the script. The file's format will be .json. </p> <p align="justify"> If this process doesn't work, there are other ways. I'll leave the link <a href="https://pypi.org/project/nrc-exporter/">here</a> if you want to know more about nrc-exporter. </p> <p>Exploratory</p> <p align="justify"> I loaded the files in a jupyter notebook to do the analysis. As all files are .json format, using the pandas json_normalize() function helps a lot. </p> <p align="justify"> After the preprocessing, creating, selecting and transforming the variables — as the average pace, for example, which comes in total minutes and not in minutes'seconds' how we normally use —, I wanted to analyze, my final dataframe looked like this: </p> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2024-01-06-post_running-Images/4.webp" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <p>To contextualize, some descriptive statistics:</p> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2024-01-06-post_running-Images/5.webp" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <p align="justify"> I analyzed a sample of races in the period of 137 days (a little over 4 months). During this period, I ran 31 races totaling 180km! I also calculated the interval average in days between one race and another. Excluding the period that I was unable to run (20 days), that I understood as an outlier that shouldn't be taken in consideration, this interval was 4 days. </p> <p align="justify"> Considering these 31 races, the average distance was 5.81km and my average pace was 6'24'' per km. Additionally, with these runs, I burned a total of 9981 calories! </p> <p>Let’s to the graphical analyses:</p> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2024-01-06-post_running-Images/6.webp" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <p align="justify"> The graph above illustrates the evolution of my average pace throughout the runs and the overall average. We can observe that in my recent runs, my pace has been above this average. </p> <p align="justify"> As I mentioned above, I created a variable called "days without running" to try to understand if my pace increased with many days without running. The peaks on the gray line follow the peaks on the purple line in the graph below, confirming what I already suspected: an extended period without exercise may be one of the variables affecting my time. </p> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2024-01-06-post_running-Images/7.webp" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <p align="justify"> Something a little obvious, but it's also cool to visualize: the opposite trajectory of the average pace and average speed. </p> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2024-01-06-post_running-Images/8.webp" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <p>Let’s follow:</p> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2024-01-06-post_running-Images/9.webp" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <p align="justify"> The graph above shows the progression of distances in my runs. The majority of my runs are in the range of 5km, and when I run more than that, I run the double. This is what pushes the average up. </p> <p>When crossing the average pace data with the distance, we have:</p> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2024-01-06-post_running-Images/10.webp" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <p align="justify"> The distribution of my pace in the 5km runs is varied, which doesn't surprise me. Another thing I confirmed looking the image above was the increase in my pace as I increase the distance. There's another aspect that I need to work on. </p> <p>To analyze calories, I plotted two graphs:</p> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2024-01-06-post_running-Images/11.webp" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2024-01-06-post_running-Images//12.webp" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <p align="justify"> The first one makes clear the positive correlation between calories and distance, meaning if you want to burn more calories, run more (remembering that correlation doesn't imply causality, but in this case, I know it does). The second one doesn't show a correlation between calories and speed. Note that many times I burned almost the same amount of calories, running at different average speeds (probably during the many 5km runs). </p> <p align="justify"> Another feeling I had was that on cloudy days, my performance was a bit better. No sun, and a little breeze, you know how it is... But that's not what the data showed me. The boxplot below suggests that on "clear days," the distribution of my speed is the "best": </p> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2024-01-06-post_running-Images/13.webp" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <p>Finally, the distribution of elevation and descent on my routes:</p> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2024-01-06-post_running-Images/14.webp" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <p>Relevant insights</p> <p align="justify"> 1) Always run to try to keep/lower my pace for distances that I'm already used to running and consequently be able to improve for longer distances;<br/> 2) I need to run longer distances, even with a bad time, if I want to lose more calories;<br/> 3) The weather, apparently, doesn't have impact on my performance;<br/> 4) Apparently elevation gain doesn't have great correlations with running time and calories. Therefore, I can keep my usual routes if I wanted to change some of these variables. </p> <p>Some observations for who want to replicate the analysis:</p> <p align="justify"> 1) It's possible to find the latitude and longitude of the routes in the data, making it possible to georeference the races. In my case I didn't think it was relevant to use, since I almost always run in the same place.<br/> 2) As wrote above, the average pace data comes in total minutes, so if like me, you want to look at this more friendly and usual — minutes'seconds'' — it is necessary to treat this variable.<br/> 3) Also as wrote above, I didn't find the time information per section, so I preferred not to use it. </p> <p align="justify"> There are a lot of people entering/wanting to enter the data analytics/data science area and who need data to train programming or even to build their portfólios. The message I would also share with this post is that there is nothing cooler than using our data for this. In addition to using them for our benefit, generating insights that help us make better decisions (for running in my case), we address topics as treatment and transformation of variables, outliers, data quality and others, clarifying how all of this works in the real life. </p> <p align="justify"> Any suggestions are welcome! The complete analysis code can be found on my <a href="https://github.com/nathaliatito">github</a>. </p>]]></content><author><name>Nathália Tito</name></author><category term="Running;"/><category term="Python"/><category term="Running;"/><category term="Python"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[How I used data science methods to evaluate my running performance]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Campeonato Carioca 2024 - Uma análise compilada</title><link href="https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2000/post_carioca_compilado-pt/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Campeonato Carioca 2024 - Uma análise compilada"/><published>2000-01-01T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2000-01-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2000/post_carioca_compilado-pt</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2000/post_carioca_compilado-pt/"><![CDATA[<h2>Introdução</h2> <div style="width: 65%; margin: 0 auto; text-align: center;"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2024-03-07-post_carioca_compilado/Carioca_2024_FERJ.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <div style="text-align: justify"> O Campeonato Carioca 2024 chegou à fase de semifinais, e o Ace Laboratory traz uma análise compilada dos quatro grandes do Rio e do Nova Iguaçu que fez uma grande campanha e se classificou para a fase final da competição. O Flamengo, que liderou a fase de pontos corridos, o Nova Iguaçu, que surpreendeu a todos, o Vasco, que teve um meio campo de qualidade, o Fluminense, que teve uma defesa sólida, e o Botafogo, que teve um desempenho abaixo do esperado. Vamos analisar o desempenho de cada um dos times e os destaques individuais da competição. </div> <div style="width: 80%; margin: 0 auto; text-align: center;"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2024-03-07-post_carioca_compilado/table.jpeg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <h2>Flamengo</h2> <div style="width: 80%; margin: 0 auto; text-align: center;"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2024-03-07-post_carioca_compilado/flamengo-pt.jpeg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <div style="text-align: justify"> <p align="justify"> Podemos afirmar que o destaque do Flamengo nesse campeonato foi o seu setor defensivo. O time tomou apenas 1 gol nas 11 partidas da competição, sendo o 3° time com melhor taxa de duelos ganhos <b>(40.1%)</b> e o 2° melhor se considerarmos apenas os duelos aéreos <b>(49.4%)</b>. Essa segurança nos duelos, somado à qualidade dos jogadores, fez o Flamengo ser o clube que menos cometeu erros que levaram a chutes <b>(31)</b> e o que menos levou chutes <b>(79)</b> dos adversários, com mais de 15 chutes de diferença do 2° colocado. </p> <p align="justify"> Com Giorgian De Arrascaeta no meio de campo, o trabalho ofensivo do Flamengo também impressionou, o jogador está acima do 3° quartil em 6 das 7 categorias ofensivas que observamos, estando no Top 10 do campeonato em gols, assistências e passes chave. O rubro-negro gosta de ditar o jogo e com isso conseguiu criar muitas oportunidades, foi 2° com mais posse de bola <b>(57.8%)</b>, o 1° em taxa de cruzamentos certos <b>(43.3%)</b>, o 1° em gols marcados <b>(23)</b> e o 1° em chutes <b>(178)</b>, com mais de 20 chutes na frente do 2° lugar. </p> <p align="justify"> Com isso vimos o domínio do Flamengo no Campeonato Carioca 2024, o time se mostrou sólido defensivamente, sendo o que menos tomou gols, e sólido ofensivamente, sendo o que mais marcou gols. Com a qualidade de seus jogadores, o Flamengo vai favorito para a semifinal contra o Fluminense, e vai em busca do título invicto. </p> </div> <h2>Nova Iguaçu</h2> <div style="width: 80%; margin: 0 auto; text-align: center;"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2024-03-07-post_carioca_compilado/nova-iguacu-pt.jpeg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <div style="text-align: justify"> <p align="justify"> O time do Nova Iguaçu surpreendeu a muitos com a segunda melhor campanha dos pontos corridos do Cariocão. O time não apresenta uma boa média das métricas defensivas no geral, apresentando a menor média de posse de bola dos times classificados <b>(7º em todo o campeonato)</b>, a maior taxa de faltas cometidas e sofrendo um total de treze gols. O fator importante para as vitórias do Nova Iguaçu foi aproveitar os chutes a gol que tiveram e converter as chances em gols. </p> <p align="justify"> O meio campista Bill foi o destaque do time na competição. O atleta foi o <b>1º</b> do time em número de assistências, passes chave e dribles certos, deixando nítida a sua importância ao longo do campeonato. O gráfico de radar mostrado abaixo também demonstra a polivalencia do jogador na defesa, armação e conclusão das jogadas. </p> <p align="justify"> Conquistando 24 pontos, com sete vitórias, três empates e apenas uma única derrota, a laranja mecânica da baixada se classifica para as semifinais e deixa um dos grandes do Rio para fora. Assim como nos pontos corridos, o Nova Iguaçu terá que aproveitar as chances que tiver para surpreender o Vasco e chegar a final do Carioca 2024. </p> </div> <h2>Vasco</h2> <div style="width: 80%; margin: 0 auto; text-align: center;"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2024-03-07-post_carioca_compilado/vasco-pt.jpeg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <div style="text-align: justify"> <p align="justify"> O campeonato do Gigante da Colina foi marcado por seu ataque, sendo o <b>2º</b> maior do campeonato com 20 gols no total. Com um time que mantém a posse de bola e é preciso em seus passes, o Vasco foi o <b>3º</b> time com mais posse de bola <b>(55%)</b>, o 3° em passes <b>(5290)</b> e o 3° em precisão dos passes <b>(87.7%)</b>. </p> <p align="justify"> O destaque do time não poderia ser ninguém menos do que o francês Dimitri Payet. O meio campo foi o <b>2°</b> do time em gols, <b>1º</b> em assistências e <b>1º</b> em passes chave. Ao observamos o gráfico de radar, podemos ver que o jogador apresenta uma grande importância na criação de jogadas e na finalização das mesmas. Payet foi uma peça fundamental para o Vasco durante os pontos corridos, e será essencial para o time na semifinal contra o Nova Iguaçu. </p> <p align="justify"> Para as semifinais, o Vasco precisará manter a qualidade que o seu setor de meio campo e ataque tem apresentado nas últimas partidas do campeonato, para não tomar sustos e garantir a vaga na final do Carioca 2024. </p> </div> <h2>Fluminense</h2> <div style="width: 80%; margin: 0 auto; text-align: center;"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2024-03-07-post_carioca_compilado/fluminense-pt.jpeg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <div style="text-align: justify"> <p align="justify"> O Fluminense teve uma defesa sólida na competição, junto com o Botafogo foi o <b>3°</b> time que menos levou gols no torneio <b>(11)</b>, foi líder nos duelos ganhos <b>(42.0%)</b> e nos duelos aéreos <b>(50.2%)</b>, ficou empatado com o Flamengo como o que menos cometeu erros que levaram a chutes <b>(31)</b> e o foi o 2° clube que menos levou chutes <b>(96)</b>. </p> <p align="justify"> O estilo de Fernando Diniz se mostrou presente no campeonato, sendo o Fluminense o time com mais posse de bola <b>(63.7%)</b>, com mais passes <b>(5843)</b> e o 1° em precisão dos passes <b>(91.0%)</b>, característico do jogo do treinador. O meia Jhon Arias foi peça fundamental do elenco tricolor, tendo uma característica ofensiva, o jogador foi o líder do time em passes chave <b>(16)</b>, e o 8° em toda competição, o que não correspondeu em mais gols, dado que o clube foi o que menos marcou gols no G4 <b>(17)</b>. O ataque do clube não foi satisfatório, sendo o 7° em chutes <b>(143)</b>, o Fluminense demonstrou que apesar da grande troca de passes, não criou oportunidades reais, que se traduziram na baixa quantidade de gols. </p> <p align="justify"> Apesar da defesa de qualidade, o ataque tricolor não acompanhou o rendimento que seu meio de campo criava. Isso se tornou mais evidente nos clássicos, onde o Fluminense somou apenas 1 ponto dos 9 disputados, fazendo 2 gols e levando 6, mais da metade do que levou em todo campeonato. Campeão da Recopa, o Fluminense terá trabalho a fazer se quiser garantir o tricampeonato do Carioca 2024. </p> </div> <h2>Botafogo</h2> <div style="width: 80%; margin: 0 auto; text-align: center;"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2024-03-07-post_carioca_compilado/botafogo-pt.jpeg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <div style="text-align: justify"> <p align="justify"> O Botafogo teve uma boa defesa no campeonato, tendo números de G4, foi o 2° em duelos ganhos <b>(40.3%)</b>, o 3° que menos cometeu erros que levaram à chutes <b>(32)</b>, apenas 1 a mais que Flamengo e Fluminense, e também o 3° que menos recebeu chutes <b>(101)</b>. E para complementar no setor ofensivo, o lateral Hugo fez uma ótima atuação na criação de jogadas do time, sendo o 1° em assistências no campeonato <b>(5)</b> e o 7° em passes chave <b>(18)</b>. </p> <p align="justify"> Tomando menos controle do jogo, o Botafogo preferiu deixar a bola com o adversário, sendo o único time dos 4 grandes do Rio a ter uma posse de bola menor que 50% <b>(49.6%)</b>, o 5° do campeonato em troca de passes <b>(4357)</b>, o 6° na precisão desses passes <b>(84.67%)</b> e o 10° em cruzamentos certos <b>(30.9%)</b>. Contudo, seu ataque se mostrou bastante eficiente com as jogadas individuais, o clube foi o 3° em dribles bem sucedidos <b>(234)</b> e gols <b>(19)</b>, e o 2° em chutes <b>(157)</b>. </p> <p align="justify"> O Campeonato Carioca se decide em detalhes, e analisando os números, vimos que o Botafogo teve um rendimento até melhor que o Fluminense <b>(4° lugar)</b> em algumas estatísticas, no entanto, a derrota para o Boavista na 3° rodada foi decisiva para o clube não se classificar para as semifinais do torneio, abrindo espaço para o Nova Iguaçu, a surpresa da competição. </p> </div> <h2>Semifinais</h2> <div style="text-align: justify"> <p align="justify"> As semifinais do Campeonato Carioca 2024 prometem ser emocionantes. O Flamengo, favorito ao título, enfrenta o Fluminense, que terá que superar a deficiência ofensiva para surpreender. </p> <p align="justify"> O Nova Iguaçu, que surpreendeu a todos, enfrenta o Vasco, que tem um meio campo de qualidade e que pode ser decisivo para o time. </p> <p align="justify"> Faremos o acompanhamento de todas as partidas e traremos as análises das semifinais e da final do Carioca 2024. Fiquem ligados! </p> </div>]]></content><author><name>Ace Laboratory Football Team</name></author><category term="Football;"/><category term="Analysis"/><category term="Football;"/><category term="Carioca;"/><category term="Analysis"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Introdução]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Campeonato Carioca 2024 - Semifinal - Primeiro Jogo</title><link href="https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2000/post_carioca_semifinal_1-pt/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Campeonato Carioca 2024 - Semifinal - Primeiro Jogo"/><published>2000-01-01T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2000-01-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2000/post_carioca_semifinal_1-pt</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2000/post_carioca_semifinal_1-pt/"><![CDATA[<h2>Introdução</h2> <div style="width: 55%; margin: 0 auto; text-align: center;"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2024-03-07-post_carioca_compilado/Carioca_2024_FERJ.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <div style="text-align: justify"> <p align="justify"> O Campeonato Carioca continua a surpreender o futebol brasileiro, com Fluminense, Flamengo, Vasco e Nova Iguaçu na disputa. A equipe de Futebol do Laboratório Ace mergulha nos jogos decisivos, desde o domínio do Flamengo sobre o Fluminense até o inesperado poder ofensivo do Nova Iguaçu tentando superar a "Muralha" do Vasco, oferecendo um vislumbre empolgante da ação eletrizante do torneio. </p> </div> <h2>Fluminense x Flamengo</h2> <div style="text-align: justify"> <h3>Análise da partida</h3> <div style="width: 80%; margin: 0 auto; text-align: center;"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2024-03-15-post_carioca_semifinal_1/pt-br/flaflugame.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <p align="justify"> O Fluminense fez uma partida abaixo do esperado contra o Flamengo, sendo constantemente pressionado, e não conseguindo impor seu estilo de jogo. Esta foi 1° partida do Campeonato Carioca 2024 em que o time acabou a partida com menor posse de bola que seu adversário <b>(49% x 51%)</b>, com uma atuação fraca de seu ataque, que não realizou nenhuma finalização ao gol do goleiro Agustín Rossi. Além disso, o time cometeu um total de <b>11 erros que levaram à chutes</b> no jogo, sendo que até essa partida, tinha cometido <b>31 erros</b> em todo o campeonato. </p> <p align="justify"> Já o rubro-negro, que possuía sua maior força no setor defensivo, demonstrou que também tem alta capacidade ofensiva, realizando um total de <b>23 finalizações</b> na partida, sendo <b>9</b> desses chutes no gol de Fábio. Se considerarmos o tempo aproximado do time com a bola, temos uma taxa de <b>1 chute a cada 2 minutos</b> com a posse de bola. </p> <p align="justify"> Os dados mostraram um domínio completo do time de Tite em campo, tanto no setor defensivo, quanto ofensivo, o Flamengo criou e não deixou o adversário aproveitar as poucas chances que teve. O Fluminense terá um trabalho difícil para se classificar para as finais, marcar 3 gols em um time que tomou apenas 1 gol em todo campeonato, para isso o técnico Fernando Diniz precisará mudar suas estratégias, e possivelmente se portar de forma mais agressiva para o 2° jogo se quiser garantir seu lugar na final. </p> <h3>Destaques</h3> <div style="width: 80%; margin: 0 auto; text-align: center;"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2024-03-15-post_carioca_semifinal_1/pt-br/flafluplayers.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <p align="justify"> Uma das formas de ver como o Fluminense jogou defensivamente foi o posicionamento de Jhon Arias, jogador que normalmente atua como um ponta de forma ofensiva, acabou ficando na maior parte do jogo no campo tricolor, atuando na lateral direita como um defensor e não conseguindo explorar suas melhores qualidades, os seus dribles e seus passes importantes. </p> <p align="justify"> Outro ponto foram a quantidade de defesas que o goleiro Fábio teve que fazer de chutes de dentro de sua área <b>(5)</b>, mostrando como a criação do Flamengo foi efetiva, e em grande parte isto ocorreu por conta de Nicolás De La Cruz. O meia deu um total de <b>6 passes chave</b> para seu time, atuando principalmente no lado esquerdo do campo, lado em que o clube deu mais chutes. </p> <p align="justify"> Também é preciso notar a atuação do atacante Pedro, que aproveitou bem as oportunidades de seu time, marcando <b>1 gol</b> no fim da partida, e realizando um total de <b>6 finalizações</b>, sendo <b>3</b> no gol, tendo a oportunidade de aumentar o placar, se não fosse a boa atuação do goleiro Fábio. </p> </div> <h2>Vasco x Nova Iguaçu</h2> <div style="text-align: justify"> <h3>Análise da partida</h3> <div style="width: 80%; margin: 0 auto; text-align: center;"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2024-03-15-post_carioca_semifinal_1/pt-br/vasconovaiguacugame.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <p align="justify"> As duas equipes realizaram um confronto que, por mais que só tenha tido dois gols, foi marcado por um grande número de finalizações para ambos os times. O total de finalizações é impressionante para um confronto de semifinal, principalmente quando se observa que o confronto entre Flamengo e Fluminense teve apenas <b>31</b> finalizações, métrica quase <b>1,5x menor</b> do que o confronto do Gigante da Colina com o Gigante da Baixada, que contou com <b>45 finalizações</b> ao todo no final do jogo. </p> <p align="justify"> Para o Vasco, o jogo ofensivo se caracterizou como incomum, visto que o Cruz-Maltino possui uma média de <b>10,8 finalizações</b> nos últimos 5 jogos que disputou e nesse finalizou <b>21 vezes</b> com apenas <b>7 disparos</b> na direção do goleiro Fabrício. O meio campo do Vasco também demonstrou muita criatividade ao chegar no ataque, somando <b>16 passes-chave</b> ao longo dos 90 primeiros minutos da semifinal do Campeonato Carioca. </p> <p align="justify"> Para o Nova Iguaçu, por outro lado, foi um jogo não muito diferente do habitual vivido nos últimos 5 jogos, já que a média de chutes do time no campeonato carioca é de <b>17 finalizações</b> por jogo. Os dados observados no jogo mostram também a preferência da Laranja Mecânica da Baixada de chutar de fora da área possuindo mais disparos de fora da área <b>(13)</b> do que de dentro da área <b>(11)</b>, gerando muito trabalho para o goleiro adversário. </p> <h3>Destaques</h3> <div style="width: 80%; margin: 0 auto; text-align: center;"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2024-03-15-post_carioca_semifinal_1/pt-br/vasconovaiguacuplayers.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <p align="justify"> Sem dúvidas, foi um confronto muito disputado com diversas chances para os dois times, e nesse contexto, é imprescindível colocar em pauta tanto os principais criadores de chance, quanto os principais defensores de cada time. </p> <p align="justify"> Do lado do Vasco com um desempenho invejável, o francês Dimitri Payet se destacou com uma taxa de <b>88% de passes certos</b>, com <b>5 passes chaves</b> realizados pelo meia-atacante ex-Olympique Marselha. Paralelamente, no setor defensivo o meia-atacante também foi fundamental, contando com <b>12 duelos ganhos</b> pelo Cruz-Maltino e possuindo um mapa calor muito participativo na esquerda do terço defensivo do Gigante da Colina. </p> <p align="justify"> Em um jogo com muitas finalizações e atuações acima da média, atacantes que tiveram boas atuações como Carlinhos, que finalizou para gol <b>5 vezes</b>, foram ofuscados pelas milagrosas performances dos goleiros dos dois times. Léo Jardim fez incríveis <b>14 defesas</b>, sendo 9 dessas finalizações de dentro da área, representando um total de <b>93%</b> de bolas defendidas, e ainda com um gol sofrido foi eleito o melhor jogador da partida. Enquanto Fabricio, goleiro do Nova Iguaçu, apesar de "só" ter feito 6 defesas, com 50% delas vindo de chutes de dentro da área, acertou <b>80% de bolas longas</b> lançadas para o domínio do time no campo, característica que é cada vez mais requisitada nos goleiros atuais. </p> </div> <h2>Considerações Finais</h2> <div style="text-align: justify"> <p align="justify"> Estes foram os dois primeiros jogos das semifinais. O Flamengo sai na vantagem e o Fluminense precisará de uma atuação muito melhor para reverter o placar. Já o Vasco, apesar de ter sido salvo pela grande atuação do Leo Jardim, precisará de no mínimo uma vitória simples para garantir sua vaga na final. O Nova Iguaçu, por sua vez, fica com a vantagem do empate. </p> <p align="justify"> A equipe do Laboratório Ace de Futebol continuará acompanhando o Campeonato Carioca, trazendo análises detalhadas sobre os jogos e os jogadores. Continuem ligados! </p> </div>]]></content><author><name>Ace Laboratory Football Team</name></author><category term="Football;"/><category term="Analysis"/><category term="Football;"/><category term="Carioca;"/><category term="Analysis"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Introdução]]></summary></entry></feed>