<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.4">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://ac3lab.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://ac3lab.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2024-12-13T13:38:52+00:00</updated><id>https://ac3lab.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">blank</title><subtitle>Marrying academic rigor with practical applications to benefit sports </subtitle><entry><title type="html">Analyzing Brazilian Football Signings in 2024 - Offensive Sector</title><link href="https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2024/post_contratacoes_1_en/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Analyzing Brazilian Football Signings in 2024 - Offensive Sector"/><published>2024-10-10T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-10-10T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2024/post_contratacoes_1_en</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2024/post_contratacoes_1_en/"><![CDATA[<hr/> <p align="justify"> Se quiser ler este texto em pt-br, <a href="https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2000/post_contratacoes_1_pt/"> clique aqui.</a> </p> <h2><b>Introduction </b></h2> <div style="text-align: justify"> In this series of posts, we'll bring you statistics on the main signings made by teams in Brazil's Serie A! To do this, we've separated the players into sectors: attack, midfield and defense. In this first post, we'll talk about the attackers that Brazilian clubs have invested (some of them a lot of) money in. For a better comparison, we've also chosen to showcase some players who aren't 2024 signings, precisely to compare the new players with others already established in Brazilian soccer. <br/><br/> <h3> <b> The signings </b> </h3> Our criteria for selecting players was to choose the player recruited in 2024 with the most minutes in the team for each sector (with a minimum minute equivalent to 8 matches), prioritizing teams that have greater purchasing power and have made more significant signings in the elite of Brazilian soccer. The players selected for the attacking sector were: <b>Luiz Henrique</b> (Botafogo), <b>Felipe Anderson</b> (Palmeiras), <b>Gustavo Scarpa</b> (Atlético-MG), <b>Breno Lopes</b> (Fortaleza), <b>André Silva</b> (São Paulo), <b>Everton Ribeiro</b> (Bahia), <b>Gabriel Veron</b> (Cruzeiro), <b>David</b> (Vasco), <b>Soteldo</b> (Grêmio), <b>Wesley</b> (Internacional), <b>Rodrigo Garro</b> (Corinthians), <b>Yannick Bolasie</b> (Criciúma), <b>Lucas Barbosa</b> (Juventude) and <b>Gonzalo Mastriani</b> (Athletico). <br/><br/> Some clubs haven't made any signings in the attacking sector, while others have, but the signings haven't played more than the equivalent of 8 matches. In both cases, there is no player representing the team in the comparison. <br/><br/> <h3> <b> Analysis and Comparison of the New Players </b> </h3> The data used for this analysis refers exclusively to the Brazilian Championship, covering matches up to the 29th round. It is worth noting that, due to postponements, not all teams have played 29 matches. <br/><br/> To begin the analysis, we will use two graphs which, although similar in scope, offer different perspectives. The first graph relates the number of shots to the expected goals, providing an insight into the <b>quantity and quality of chances that players receive</b>, on average, per match. The second graph relates expected goals (xG) to goals scored, making it easier to analyze <b>how players take advantage of the chances created</b>. In both graphs (and the third one too), the players signed this season are represented in cyan, while the green dots indicate players used as references. <br/><br/> The first graph shows average lines on both axes, which helps to identify players who are above or below average in each metric, dividing the graph into four quadrants. In the Goals vs. xG graph, a single line was used, dividing the graph into two quadrants: above the line are the players who scored more goals than expected; below the line, those who scored less than expected. <br/><br/> <div style="width: 100%; margin: 0 auto; text-align: center;"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2024-10-10-post_contratacoes/shots_vs_xg.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <center>Graph 1. xG per 90 x Shots Per 90<br/><br/></center> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2024-10-10-post_contratacoes/xg_vs_goals.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <center>Graph 2. Goals per 90 x xG per 90 <br/><br/></center> <ul> <li> <p>Among the players signed this season, <b>Gonzalo Mastriani** and <b>Yannick Bolasie</b> stand out in terms of the number of shots and goals expected. Their statistics in these metrics are similar to those of other players who can be considered the main finishers for their respective teams, such as <b>Hulk<b>, <b>Pablo Vegetti</b> and <b>José López</b> (Flaco López). <br/><br/></b></b></b></p> </li> <li> <p>It’s also worth highlighting the efficiency of São Paulo’s center forward, <b>André Silva</b>. Although he doesn’t have a very high number of expected shots and goals, he stands out in the number of goals scored, being the player furthest away from the middle line and can therefore be considered the “most efficient” of the signings shown. <br/><br/></p> </li> <li> <p>In contrast, <b>Everton Ribeiro</b> has low values in these metrics directly related to finishing moves. This highlights a big difference between him and the rest of the strikers being compared. <b>Everton Ribeiro</b>, as we’ll see later, is not a player marked by direct participation in finishing moves, but rather in constructing them. In the graph, he is in the bottom left quadrant, which suggests that he plays a lesser role in both shooting and scoring goals in a match. <br/><br/></p> </li> <li> <p>Although it’s not the main focus of this analysis, it’s important to mention young <b>Estevão</b>, from Palmeiras. Although he is not a new signing, he “emerged” in the elite of Brazilian soccer in 2024. Despite not being a center-forward, he is one of the players who finishes the most, as well as accumulating high numbers of expected goals and goals per game. That’s impressive, considering he’s only <b>17 years old</b> and is in his debut season in the league. <br/><br/></p> </li> </ul> <p>Finally, we chose another graph to visualize participation with the ball and the number of passes in the final third of the pitch. The interesting thing about this visualization is that we were able to ‘divide’ the players into three groups, where it’s possible to understand why the player belongs to each group according to their individual and team characteristics. <br/><br/></p> <div style="width: 100%; margin: 0 auto; text-align: center;"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2024-10-10-post_contratacoes/passes_vs_touches.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <center>Graph 3. Accurate Final Third Passes per 90 x Touches per 90<br/><br/></center> <ul> <li> <p>The center forwards, such as <b>Yannick Bolasie</b>, <b>Gonzalo Mastriani</b> and <b>André Silva</b>, are below average both in terms of the number of touches they get on the ball and the number of correct passes in the final third. This isn’t necessarily a demerit, but a characteristic of the role. Center forwards tend to receive the ball less than most other players, and when they do, they’re often put under a lot of pressure, which increases the chance of a misplaced pass. <br/><br/></p> </li> <li> <p>On the other hand, attacking players who are more constructive, such as <b>Rodrigo Garro</b>, <b>Gustavo Scarpa</b> and <b>Everton Ribeiro</b>, are above average in these two metrics. <b>Everton Ribeiro</b>, in particular, stands out from the rest, both because of his individual characteristics and because of the way Bahia uses him. The team sees him as a key player in the offensive progression, taking advantage of his superior technical quality, which makes him the main player in the construction of plays and participation with the ball. <br/><br/></p> </li> <li> <p>Located on the graph between these two groups are the players most characterized by dribbling, such as <b>Wesley</b>, <b>Luiz Henrique</b>, <b>Lucas Barbosa</b> and <b>David</b>. The interpretation is that, despite having a number of touches and passes in the final third close to the average, these players progress in a different way to the builders. They prefer to advance with the ball through quick and, in some cases, long carries. In addition, they tend to be more involved in finishing off moves, which is why they often don’t receive the ball back in the same move after receiving it.</p> </li> </ul> <h2> <b>Conclusion</b> </h2> <p>In summary, the attacking signings of Serie A clubs in 2024 reveal different player profiles, reflecting the specific characteristics of each team and their tactical needs. While central strikers such as <b>Bolasie</b> and <b>Mastriani</b> stand out for their finishing, although with less involvement in the build-up play, more creative and constructive players such as <b>Rodrigo Garro</b> and <b>Everton Ribeiro</b> play a key role in attacking progression. On the other hand, players who focus on dribbling, such as <b>Wesley</b> and <b>Luiz Henrique</b>, take a different approach, with a greater emphasis on carrying and dribbling. These distinctions reveal how the teams function differently, whether because of economic reality, the rest of the squad, or the choice of the coaching staff. <br/><br/></p> <div> </div>]]></content><author><name>Ace Laboratory Football Team - Daniel Barros, Hugo Antunes</name></author><category term="Football;"/><category term="Analysis"/><category term="Football;"/><category term="Analysis"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Se quiser ler este texto em pt-br, clique aqui. Introduction In this series of posts, we'll bring you statistics on the main signings made by teams in Brazil's Serie A! To do this, we've separated the players into sectors: attack, midfield and defense. In this first post, we'll talk about the attackers that Brazilian clubs have invested (some of them a lot of) money in. For a better comparison, we've also chosen to showcase some players who aren't 2024 signings, precisely to compare the new players with others already established in Brazilian soccer. The signings Our criteria for selecting players was to choose the player recruited in 2024 with the most minutes in the team for each sector (with a minimum minute equivalent to 8 matches), prioritizing teams that have greater purchasing power and have made more significant signings in the elite of Brazilian soccer. The players selected for the attacking sector were: Luiz Henrique (Botafogo), Felipe Anderson (Palmeiras), Gustavo Scarpa (Atlético-MG), Breno Lopes (Fortaleza), André Silva (São Paulo), Everton Ribeiro (Bahia), Gabriel Veron (Cruzeiro), David (Vasco), Soteldo (Grêmio), Wesley (Internacional), Rodrigo Garro (Corinthians), Yannick Bolasie (Criciúma), Lucas Barbosa (Juventude) and Gonzalo Mastriani (Athletico). Some clubs haven't made any signings in the attacking sector, while others have, but the signings haven't played more than the equivalent of 8 matches. In both cases, there is no player representing the team in the comparison. Analysis and Comparison of the New Players The data used for this analysis refers exclusively to the Brazilian Championship, covering matches up to the 29th round. It is worth noting that, due to postponements, not all teams have played 29 matches. To begin the analysis, we will use two graphs which, although similar in scope, offer different perspectives. The first graph relates the number of shots to the expected goals, providing an insight into the quantity and quality of chances that players receive, on average, per match. The second graph relates expected goals (xG) to goals scored, making it easier to analyze how players take advantage of the chances created. In both graphs (and the third one too), the players signed this season are represented in cyan, while the green dots indicate players used as references. The first graph shows average lines on both axes, which helps to identify players who are above or below average in each metric, dividing the graph into four quadrants. In the Goals vs. xG graph, a single line was used, dividing the graph into two quadrants: above the line are the players who scored more goals than expected; below the line, those who scored less than expected. Graph 1. xG per 90 x Shots Per 90 Graph 2. Goals per 90 x xG per 90 Among the players signed this season, Gonzalo Mastriani** and Yannick Bolasie stand out in terms of the number of shots and goals expected. Their statistics in these metrics are similar to those of other players who can be considered the main finishers for their respective teams, such as Hulk, Pablo Vegetti and José López (Flaco López). It’s also worth highlighting the efficiency of São Paulo’s center forward, André Silva. Although he doesn’t have a very high number of expected shots and goals, he stands out in the number of goals scored, being the player furthest away from the middle line and can therefore be considered the “most efficient” of the signings shown. In contrast, Everton Ribeiro has low values in these metrics directly related to finishing moves. This highlights a big difference between him and the rest of the strikers being compared. Everton Ribeiro, as we’ll see later, is not a player marked by direct participation in finishing moves, but rather in constructing them. In the graph, he is in the bottom left quadrant, which suggests that he plays a lesser role in both shooting and scoring goals in a match. Although it’s not the main focus of this analysis, it’s important to mention young Estevão, from Palmeiras. Although he is not a new signing, he “emerged” in the elite of Brazilian soccer in 2024. Despite not being a center-forward, he is one of the players who finishes the most, as well as accumulating high numbers of expected goals and goals per game. That’s impressive, considering he’s only 17 years old and is in his debut season in the league. Finally, we chose another graph to visualize participation with the ball and the number of passes in the final third of the pitch. The interesting thing about this visualization is that we were able to ‘divide’ the players into three groups, where it’s possible to understand why the player belongs to each group according to their individual and team characteristics. Graph 3. Accurate Final Third Passes per 90 x Touches per 90 The center forwards, such as Yannick Bolasie, Gonzalo Mastriani and André Silva, are below average both in terms of the number of touches they get on the ball and the number of correct passes in the final third. This isn’t necessarily a demerit, but a characteristic of the role. Center forwards tend to receive the ball less than most other players, and when they do, they’re often put under a lot of pressure, which increases the chance of a misplaced pass. On the other hand, attacking players who are more constructive, such as Rodrigo Garro, Gustavo Scarpa and Everton Ribeiro, are above average in these two metrics. Everton Ribeiro, in particular, stands out from the rest, both because of his individual characteristics and because of the way Bahia uses him. The team sees him as a key player in the offensive progression, taking advantage of his superior technical quality, which makes him the main player in the construction of plays and participation with the ball. Located on the graph between these two groups are the players most characterized by dribbling, such as Wesley, Luiz Henrique, Lucas Barbosa and David. The interpretation is that, despite having a number of touches and passes in the final third close to the average, these players progress in a different way to the builders. They prefer to advance with the ball through quick and, in some cases, long carries. In addition, they tend to be more involved in finishing off moves, which is why they often don’t receive the ball back in the same move after receiving it. Conclusion In summary, the attacking signings of Serie A clubs in 2024 reveal different player profiles, reflecting the specific characteristics of each team and their tactical needs. While central strikers such as Bolasie and Mastriani stand out for their finishing, although with less involvement in the build-up play, more creative and constructive players such as Rodrigo Garro and Everton Ribeiro play a key role in attacking progression. On the other hand, players who focus on dribbling, such as Wesley and Luiz Henrique, take a different approach, with a greater emphasis on carrying and dribbling. These distinctions reveal how the teams function differently, whether because of economic reality, the rest of the squad, or the choice of the coaching staff.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Analysis of the Best Football Leagues</title><link href="https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2024/post_analise_ligas_en/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Analysis of the Best Football Leagues"/><published>2024-09-22T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-09-22T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2024/post_analise_ligas_en</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2024/post_analise_ligas_en/"><![CDATA[<hr/> <p align="justify"> Se quiser ler este texto em pt-br, <a href="https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2000/post_analise_ligas_pt/"> clique aqui. </a> </p> <div style="text-align: justify"> <h2>Introduction</h2> In today’s post, we decided to touch on a topic that is discussed every year: What is the best league in the world? Does the Brasileirão belong among these leagues? We will analyze everything from the total Market Value to each league's performance in international competitions. The leagues studied were: Premier League (England), La Liga (Spain), Ligue 1 (France), Bundesliga (Germany), Serie A (Italy), and Brasileirão (Brazil). The international tournaments studied were the Copa Libertadores (CONMEBOL), Copa Sulamericana (CONMEBOL), Champions League (UEFA) and Europa League (UEFA). <br/><br/> <h2> <b>Research</b> </h2> The data used in this research were collected from Transfermarkt, which provides market values for each team in the leagues studied per season; Sofascore, with the final standings of each season; UEFA, with the results from the Champions League and Europa League; and CONMEBOL, with the results from the Copa Libertadores and Copa Sulamericana. The last five years were taken into consideration: for European teams, the seasons from 2019-2020 to 2023-2024, and for Brazilian teams, from 2019 to 2023. Scripts were used to extract data from Transfermarkt and Sofascore. <br/><br/> <h2> <b>Market Value</b> </h2> The following bar chart shows the total Market Value of the teams by league and by season. In the case of the Brasileirão, 19-20 refers to the 2019 season, 20-21 refers to the 2020 season, and so on. <br/><br/> <div style="width: 100%; margin: 0 auto; text-align: center;"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2024-09-22-post_analise_ligas/marketvalue.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <center>Image 1. Market Value of Leagues in the last 5 seasons<br/><br/></center> The difference between the Premier League and the other leagues is enormous, and the growth in market value per season is exponential. The financial model of team ownership in England may influence this, as many of the top English teams are owned by billionaires who inject money for signings. The model for distributing broadcast rights revenues also contributes to this high value, with hundreds of millions of pounds being distributed almost equally among the clubs. <br/><br/> Among the other European leagues, there isn’t much variation between seasons or among them. When comparing the European leagues to the Brasileirão, the colossal difference can be explained by various factors, from the weakness of the Brazilian Real compared to the Euro to the early sale of promising Brazilian players to European teams, often motivated by poor management of Brazilian clubs, forcing teams to sell promising players to pay off large debts. <br/><br/> <h2> <b>Performance in Unequal Matches</b> </h2> Performance in Unequal Matches (PUM) measures a team's performance in games against opponents whose market value is lower. The formula to calculate PUM is simple: divide the number of points won in these matches by the total points disputed. <br/><br/> Now that we understand what PUM is, let’s explain why it is useful. Our goal is to evaluate whether economically dominant teams also show sporting superiority, as they have better squads and infrastructure compared to their opponents in the leagues. <br/><br/> <div style="width: 100%; margin: 0 auto; text-align: center;"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2024-09-22-post_analise_ligas/graficoACD.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <center>Image 2. Average PUM chart for leagues in the last 5 seasons<br/><br/></center> Based on the chart showing the average PUM per season in each analyzed championship, we notice that, in the Brasileirão, performance in unequal matches is the lowest among the six leagues. This indicates that teams with lower market value can compete more evenly against the top national clubs. In the Premier League and Bundesliga, the trend is the opposite, with higher market value teams having a significantly higher average performance compared to the other leagues. <br/><br/> <h2> <b>International Competitions</b> </h2> The following tables show the number of defeats of Brazilian clubs by stage in the Copa Libertadores and Copa Sulamericana over the last 5 seasons. <br/><br/> <h3> <b>Copa Libertadores</b></h3> Brazil's dominance in the biggest club competition in South America is undeniable. In the last five finals, all featured Brazilian teams, three were entirely Brazilian, and five titles went to Brazil. The technical level difference between Brazil's top clubs and other South American teams can be attributed to several factors. Besides other countries being smaller and poorer than Brazil, some are going through major economic crises, such as Argentina, the country with the most titles in the "Glória Eterna" tournament. But Brazil has dominated in recent years, and the trend is likely to continue. Another possible analysis is the large number of talents exported from "smaller" Latin American countries to high-level Brazilian football, weakening their leagues' competitiveness against Brazilian giants. <br/><br/> <div style="width: 100%; margin: 0 auto; text-align: center;"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2024-09-22-post_analise_ligas/tabelaliba.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <center>Image 3. Number of Brazilian teams per stage of Libertadores by year<br/><br/></center> <h3> <b>Copa Sulamericana</b></h3> In the Copa Sulamericana, the scenario is different: in the last five finals, Brazil has "only" one title and three participations (with one all-Brazilian final). Why is this different from Libertadores? Could the large number of spots given to Brasileirão teams mean that weaker and less experienced teams are playing and losing early? However, this scheme may be about to change. Since 2019, the number of Brazilian clubs dropping out in the group stage has significantly decreased, replaced by later-stage eliminations. Additionally, since the all-Brazilian final in 2021, Brazil has participated in every final, although without further titles. <br/><br/> <div style="width: 100%; margin: 0 auto; text-align: center;"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2024-09-22-post_analise_ligas/tabelasula.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <center>Image 4. Number of Brazilian teams per stage of Sulamericana by year<br/><br/></center> The fact is: in the last five seasons, Brazil has won six titles in South America’s main international competitions. But what is the situation in Europe? <br/><br/> The following tables show the number of defeats of European clubs from the mentioned leagues by stage in the Champions League and Europa League over the last 5 seasons. <h3> <b>Champions League</b></h3> In the Champions League, France and Italy did not win titles, but had two runner-up finishes. What differentiates them from the winning leagues? France had the fewest teams reaching the round of 16 and fewer total participations, with only two teams making the semifinals: Lyon and PSG (twice). Italy had the most eliminations in the round of 16, with poor performance overall. Another interesting observation: Spain had a 100% success rate in finals, winning both in which they participated. England, however, had an extraordinary performance: two titles and two runner-up finishes, with one all-English final. In other words, they had the best performance, appearing in 3 out of 5 finals. <br/><br/> <div style="width: 100%; margin: 0 auto; text-align: center;"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2024-09-22-post_analise_ligas/tabelachamp.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <center>Image 5. Number of teams from each country by stage in the UCL in the last 5 years<br/><br/></center> <h3> <b>Europa League</b></h3> In the Europa League, the scenario changes: Spain dominated the period with a 100% success rate in finals, reaching three finals and winning all three. Once again, France had the fewest participations in the competition. Only three French teams made it past the group stage. Italy reached three finals but managed to win only one. Germany’s numbers are similar in both competitions, with nothing standing out. The biggest difference between the competitions is in England’s performance: in the Europa League, the English only reached one final and were runners-up. <br/><br/> <div style="width: 100%; margin: 0 auto; text-align: center;"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2024-09-22-post_analise_ligas/tabelaeuro.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <center>Image 6. Number of teams from each country by stage in the UEL in the last 5 years<br/><br/></center> <br/><br/> <h2> <b>Discussion</b> </h2> From the above analysis, we will combine all this information to try to answer the question from the introduction: "What is the best league in the world?" This question carries a degree of subjectivity, as it depends on what you want to observe in a league. <br/><br/> Looking at the most valuable league in the world, the choice would be the Premier League, with a value greater than 12 billion euros in the last season, which has been growing exponentially year after year. <br/><br/> In terms of Performance in Unequal Matches, the Brazilian league shows a low average PUM, indicating that lower market value teams can compete more equally and win more points against richer clubs. This results in more unpredictable championships and, consequently, more competitiveness. <br/><br/> When observing the performance of countries in international competitions, it becomes more subjective. In South America, Brazil is dominant, with 6 titles won in the last five years, 5 of them in the toughest competition in the Americas. In Europe, there is a greater variety of champions: only France failed to win a title. Spain won the most titles (5), and England ties with Spain in finals appearances (5 out of 10). <br/><br/> <h2> <b>Conclusion</b> </h2> Which is the best league in the world? It depends on the point of view. European leagues have a higher market value, meaning they have the best players and coaches, resulting in higher-quality matches. However, the unpredictability of the matches is lower and, in a way, less exciting. In the Brazilian league, we can see that the lower average PUM provides greater unpredictability, which brings excitement to the championship. This unpredictability is likely related to player quality, which affects the quality of the games. Therefore, answering the question about which league is the best depends on the fan’s perspective. <br/><br/> Thank you for reading and stay tuned for future posts! <br/><br/> <div> </div></div>]]></content><author><name>Ace Laboratory Football Team - Lucas Calmon, Pedro Carvalho</name></author><category term="Football;"/><category term="Analysis"/><category term="Football;"/><category term="Analysis"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">2023 Women’s World Cup - Analyzing the progress of the Brazilian national team</title><link href="https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2024/post_women_world_cup_4_en/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="2023 Women’s World Cup - Analyzing the progress of the Brazilian national team"/><published>2024-09-05T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-09-05T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2024/post_women_world_cup_4_en</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2024/post_women_world_cup_4_en/"><![CDATA[<hr/> <p align="justify"> Se quiser ler este texto em pt-br, <a href="https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2000/post_women_world_cup_4_pt/"> clique aqui. </a> </p> <div style="text-align: justify"> In this post, we're going to analyse the Brazilian national team's campaigns in the last two World Cups. The aim is to find out whether or not there has been any kind of evolution in the Brazilian team, and to understand what level the team was at in those competitions, both in the global and continental context. To do this, we're going to compare Brazil with the teams featured in the last post (Spain, the United States, Sweden and England) and with other South American teams (Argentina, Colombia in 2023, Chile in 2019).<br/><br/> <h2> <b>Overview</b> </h2> <h3> <b>2019 World Cup</b> </h3> At the 2019 World Cup, the Brazilian team was seeded in a group with Australia, Italy and Jamaica. Their performance in the group stage was good: 2 wins in 3 games, scoring 6 goals and conceding 3 during the first phase. Despite their good run, Brazil progressed to the knockout stage in third place after a triple draw in Group C (the place was won on the basis of the best third-placed team).<br/><br/> In the Round of 16, Brazil faced France in a very tight game. Despite a balance in possession during regulation time, the Brazilians had 12 shots, while the French had 5. The match was only decided in the second half of overtime, when France scored the winning goal and ended Brazil's participation in the competition.<br/><br/> <h3> <b>2023 World Cup</b> </h3> At the 2023 World Cup, Brazil had an even shorter and more frustrating campaign. Once again, the Brazilian team finished third, now in Group F, which included France, Jamaica and Panama. The Brazilians won one and drew one in three games, but in this edition, only the top two teams in the group qualified for the knockout stage.<br/><br/> When we say that the campaign was frustrating, it was not for nothing. On the final matchday of the group stage, Brazil only needed a simple win against Jamaica, an opponent who qualified with a single goal against Panama (who conceded 11 in the competition). In theory, qualification seemed on course. In practice, Brazil, despite a giant dominance when we analyse possession, the number of passes and shots, were unable to make satisfactory use of the many chances that were created. The result could not have been any other: 0-0, and the Brazilian team was eliminated in the first phase of the competition.<br/><br/> <div style="width: 100%; margin: 0 auto; text-align: center;"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2024-09-05-post_women_world_cup_4/Shotmap.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <h2> <b>Statistics between Cups</b> </h2> In this section, we're going to analyse Brazil's participation using different scatter plots. The idea is to be able to compare both the evolution (or regression) from one World Cup to the next, as well as a general comparison between the campaigns of other teams.<br/><br/> Before starting the analyses and comments section, we have to say that, because the World Cup is a short tournament (and, unfortunately, the Brazilian team's campaigns even shorter), some matches end up having a big impact on the metrics shown below. This context must be taken into account when analysing.<br/><br/> <h2> <b>Passes and Progression</b> </h2> <div style="width: 100%; margin: 0 auto; text-align: center;"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2024-09-05-post_women_world_cup_4/Passes.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> Analysing the passes and progression of the 2019 Brazilian team, you can see the low number of progressive passes per match, which is considerably below average. In 2019, the team made an average of approximately 40 progressive passes per match, about 20% less than the average of the other teams. Furthermore, there has been a noticeable improvement from the 2019 World Cup to the 2023 World Cup, with Brazil being one of the best teams in this regard.<br/><br/> - Brazil's opponents in South America are not well placed on the graph, either in relation to the main European teams or in relation to Brazil.<br/><br/> - In 2023, Brazil improved in both aspects, with around 30 progressive drives and almost 70 progressive passes per game, revealing a significant evolution, with the team assuming a more aggressive and progressive profile on the pitch compared to the much less offensive behaviour of the team in 2019. In the 2019 campaign, Brazil made approximately 20% fewer progressive passes than the average of the other teams.<br/><br/> <h2> <b>Shots and xG per shot</b> </h2> <div style="width: 100%; margin: 0 auto; text-align: center;"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2024-09-05-post_women_world_cup_4/Shots.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> To analyse the quality of the teams' shots, we'll use the graph of shots per match vs. xG per shot.<br/><br/> - Once again, Brazil are better placed than their South American opponents, indicating that there is a big advantage for the Brazilian national team on their continent.<br/><br/> - Despite a much higher number of shots per match in 2023, Brazil have not seen a considerable improvement in the quality of their chances (expected goals per shot). The lack of progress in this area was, as we said, a determining factor in Brazil's elimination in the group stage.<br/><br/> - As we've already mentioned, the fact that the World Cup is a short tournament means that some matches have a big impact on the statistics. In this graph, we have a clear example of this in the number of shots that the Brazilian national team produced. In the second round of the group stage, against Panama, Brazil shot 33 times, scoring 4 goals on the occasion. This number of shots is greater than the sum of the shots in the other two matches, showing that the match against Panama creates a false impression that the Brazilian team had the characteristic of shooting often, but that this was an isolated episode in the competition.<br/><br/> <h2> <b>Final considerations and conclusion</b></h2> The graphs show that Brazil have had considerably better campaigns than their rivals in South America, but their main opponents in Europe and North America (who have a much more established national women's football scene) still have a big advantage.<br/><br/> Even though the campaigns analysed were short and, in some ways, disappointing, Brazil made great progress after 2023. In 2024, the Brazilian team, now led by coach Arthur Elias, won the silver medal at the Olympic Games in Paris, revealing important new players to the team, such as goalkeeper Lorena and defender Tarciane.<br/><br/> And so ends our series of posts analysing the 2023 Women's World Cup. Stay tuned, there's lots more to come!<br/><br/> <div> </div></div>]]></content><author><name>Ace Laboratory Football Team - Daniel Barros, Hugo Antunes</name></author><category term="Football;"/><category term="Analysis"/><category term="Football;"/><category term="Analysis"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">2023 Women’s World Cup - Analyzing the evolution of the main teams</title><link href="https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2024/post_women_world_cup_3_en/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="2023 Women’s World Cup - Analyzing the evolution of the main teams"/><published>2024-08-22T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-08-22T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2024/post_women_world_cup_3_en</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2024/post_women_world_cup_3_en/"><![CDATA[<hr/> <p align="justify"> Se quiser ler este texto em pt-br, <a href="https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2000/post_women_world_cup_3_pt/"> clique aqui. </a> </p> <h2><b>Introduction</b></h2> <div style="text-align: justify"> In this post, we will analyze the evolution of the teams in the Women's World Cup, comparing the performance of the main teams in the 2019 and 2023 World Cups. The teams analyzed will be: <b>Spain</b>, the current champions; <b>England</b>, the current vice-champions; the <b>United States</b>, champions in 2019 and <b>Sweden</b>, who finished third in the last two editions. <br/><br/> <h2> <b>Retrospect</b> </h2> <h3> <b>Spain</b> </h3> After winning the 2023 World Cup, Spain have established themselves as one of the<b> best teams in international football</b>. With an excellent campaign in the last edition, they won the title in a final against England (these two teams were the subject of the <a href="https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2024/post_women_world_cup_1_en/"> first post of our series</a>). <br/><br/> In 2019, though, Spain's situation was very different. <b>With fewer established players and without several of the young players who made a difference in 2023</b>, such as Salma Paralluelo, Spain got through the group stage via goal difference, with a below-average campaign (1W, 1D, 1L). In the round of 16, <b>they were eliminated by the United States</b>, winners of that edition. <br/><br/> <h3> <b>England</b> </h3> <b>England have performed well in the last two World Cups</b>. In 2019, they finished in fourth place, losing to Sweden after losing in the semi-finals to the United States, who won that edition. In addition, as we mentioned, England are the current vice-champions of the world, defeated in the final by Spain. <br/><br/> In 2019, despite falling into a tough group with Japan, Argentina and Scotland, they didn't face much difficulty and came out on top with 3 wins in 3 games. In the knockout stage, they were only defeated in the semi-finals 2-1 in a match against the United States. <br/><br/> <h3> <b>United States</b> </h3> At the 2019 World Cup, <b>the United States won their fourth world title</b> (they also won 1991, 1999 and 2015), their second in a row, in a final against Netherlands. In this edition, the US broke a record that still stands today: <b>the team with the most goals in a World Cup (26!)</b>. <br/><br/> However, at the 2023 World Cup, the United States were eliminated in the round of 16 in a penalty shootout against Sweden. This campaign can be considered frustrating and was marked by a big decline in the performance of the United States attack (we'll see why in the following analysis). <br/><br/> <h3> <b>Sweden</b> </h3> <b>Sweden has done well in recent World Cups</b>. In 2019, they won third place, having eliminated strong teams like <b>Germany</b> and <b>Argentina</b> in the knockout stage. In this edition, Sweden only lost to the two finalists: the United States (in the group stage) and the Netherlands (in the semi-final). <br/><br/> In 2023, Sweden repeated their 2019 campaign and managed to win third place again. This time, they only lost one match (against champion Spain in the semi-final) out of the seven they played. In the match for third place, Sweden beat Australia 2-0. <br/><br/> <h2> <b>Comparison of World Cup campaigns</b> </h2> In this section, we will analyze the teams using different scatter graphs. The idea is to be able to compare both the evolution (or decline) of a team from one Cup to the next, as well as a general comparison between all the campaigns of the teams mentioned so far. <br/><br/> <h3> <b>Passes and Progression</b> </h3> First, it's important to mention that we've updated our definition of progressive action compared to the last post. <br/><br/> <b>Definition of progressive passing:</b> Actions in the first 30% of the pitch are ignored. They must reduce the distance from the ball to the center of the opponent's goal by at least <b>20%</b>. Only successful passes that are completed closer to the opponent's goal vertically or that have their end point inside the opponent's penalty area are counted. <br/><br/> <div style="width: 100%; margin: 0 auto; text-align: center;"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2024-08-23-post_women_world_cup_3/passes_vs_progressive_passes.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <center>Graph showing passes per match and progressive passes per match<br/><br/></center> Looking at the passing and progression of these teams, there are a few points to highlight: <br/><br/> - It's important to highlight the difference in the amount of passes per game made by Spain in the two campaigns, with Spain 2023 being by far the <b>team with the most passes and progressive passes out of all the teams that played in the two World Cups</b>. This is a clear consolidation of the style of play based on <b>passing, possession and pressing</b> that is implemented in both the women's and men's national teams. <br/><br/> - All of these teams (consolidated on the national team scene) began to pass more in the transition from one World Cup to the next, with the exception of the United States. This may be a trend in women's international football: <b>passing and proposing the game are key factors for success</b>. <br/><br/> <h3> <b>Shots and Expected Goals </b></h3> <div style="width: 100%; margin: 0 auto; text-align: center;"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2024-08-23-post_women_world_cup_3/shots_vs_xg.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <center> Graph showing shots per match and expected goals per match <br/><br/></center> In this graph relating the number of shots per match to the xG accumulated per match ( excluding penalties), we have the following observations: <br/><br/> - Once again, Spain's evolution deserves to be highlighted. The team has made considerable improvements in attack, becoming the <b>team with the most shots and expected goals of all teams in the last two World Cups</b>. <br/><br/> - Despite a reasonable increase in shots, the United States had a decrease in their xG compared to 2019, indicating that the <b>team has, on average, decreased the quality of its scoring opportunities</b>. In addition, the team's attacking efficiency has also decreased dramatically. Disregarding penalties, the 2019 United States had a <b>positive balance of +8.63 (!!!) </b>in the difference between goals and xG. In 2023, the balance was<b> -3.01</b>. <br/><br/> - The England team of 2023, despite being a <b>highlight in terms of the number of passes and progressive passes</b>, doesn't have the same impact when it comes to finishing moves. Among the teams compared, they have the <b>fewest xG per game (1.26)</b>, reinforcing what we said in our first post when we commented that England 2023 had a very <b>methodical style of play</b>. Even with a good capacity for progression, the team doesn't take many shots and, consequently, doesn't accumulate many expected goals compared to the other top teams. <br/><br/> <h2> <b>Final Considerations and Conclusion</b></h2> Throughout this post, we've focused on comparing teams that are well-established on the women's football scenario (perhaps the least well-established of these is Spain in 2019, a fact that only magnifies their winning campaign in 2023). So it was only natural that all the teams, even with differences in play and style, would be <b>“well placed”</b> in the graphs shown. At least in the two graphs shown, the prediction actually came true, with <b>all 8 teams being above average in the 4 metrics used</b>. <br/><br/> This concludes another post in our series on the 2023 Women's World Cup, and the fourth post will be the last in the series. Stay tuned for future posts! <br/><br/> <div> </div></div>]]></content><author><name>Ace Laboratory Football Team - Daniel Barros, Hugo Antunes</name></author><category term="Football;"/><category term="Analysis"/><category term="Football;"/><category term="Analysis"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Se quiser ler este texto em pt-br, clique aqui. Introduction In this post, we will analyze the evolution of the teams in the Women's World Cup, comparing the performance of the main teams in the 2019 and 2023 World Cups. The teams analyzed will be: Spain, the current champions; England, the current vice-champions; the United States, champions in 2019 and Sweden, who finished third in the last two editions. Retrospect Spain After winning the 2023 World Cup, Spain have established themselves as one of the best teams in international football. With an excellent campaign in the last edition, they won the title in a final against England (these two teams were the subject of the first post of our series). In 2019, though, Spain's situation was very different. With fewer established players and without several of the young players who made a difference in 2023, such as Salma Paralluelo, Spain got through the group stage via goal difference, with a below-average campaign (1W, 1D, 1L). In the round of 16, they were eliminated by the United States, winners of that edition. England England have performed well in the last two World Cups. In 2019, they finished in fourth place, losing to Sweden after losing in the semi-finals to the United States, who won that edition. In addition, as we mentioned, England are the current vice-champions of the world, defeated in the final by Spain. In 2019, despite falling into a tough group with Japan, Argentina and Scotland, they didn't face much difficulty and came out on top with 3 wins in 3 games. In the knockout stage, they were only defeated in the semi-finals 2-1 in a match against the United States. United States At the 2019 World Cup, the United States won their fourth world title (they also won 1991, 1999 and 2015), their second in a row, in a final against Netherlands. In this edition, the US broke a record that still stands today: the team with the most goals in a World Cup (26!). However, at the 2023 World Cup, the United States were eliminated in the round of 16 in a penalty shootout against Sweden. This campaign can be considered frustrating and was marked by a big decline in the performance of the United States attack (we'll see why in the following analysis). Sweden Sweden has done well in recent World Cups. In 2019, they won third place, having eliminated strong teams like Germany and Argentina in the knockout stage. In this edition, Sweden only lost to the two finalists: the United States (in the group stage) and the Netherlands (in the semi-final). In 2023, Sweden repeated their 2019 campaign and managed to win third place again. This time, they only lost one match (against champion Spain in the semi-final) out of the seven they played. In the match for third place, Sweden beat Australia 2-0. Comparison of World Cup campaigns In this section, we will analyze the teams using different scatter graphs. The idea is to be able to compare both the evolution (or decline) of a team from one Cup to the next, as well as a general comparison between all the campaigns of the teams mentioned so far. Passes and Progression First, it's important to mention that we've updated our definition of progressive action compared to the last post. Definition of progressive passing: Actions in the first 30% of the pitch are ignored. They must reduce the distance from the ball to the center of the opponent's goal by at least 20%. Only successful passes that are completed closer to the opponent's goal vertically or that have their end point inside the opponent's penalty area are counted. Graph showing passes per match and progressive passes per match Looking at the passing and progression of these teams, there are a few points to highlight: - It's important to highlight the difference in the amount of passes per game made by Spain in the two campaigns, with Spain 2023 being by far the team with the most passes and progressive passes out of all the teams that played in the two World Cups. This is a clear consolidation of the style of play based on passing, possession and pressing that is implemented in both the women's and men's national teams. - All of these teams (consolidated on the national team scene) began to pass more in the transition from one World Cup to the next, with the exception of the United States. This may be a trend in women's international football: passing and proposing the game are key factors for success. Shots and Expected Goals Graph showing shots per match and expected goals per match In this graph relating the number of shots per match to the xG accumulated per match ( excluding penalties), we have the following observations: - Once again, Spain's evolution deserves to be highlighted. The team has made considerable improvements in attack, becoming the team with the most shots and expected goals of all teams in the last two World Cups. - Despite a reasonable increase in shots, the United States had a decrease in their xG compared to 2019, indicating that the team has, on average, decreased the quality of its scoring opportunities. In addition, the team's attacking efficiency has also decreased dramatically. Disregarding penalties, the 2019 United States had a positive balance of +8.63 (!!!) in the difference between goals and xG. In 2023, the balance was -3.01. - The England team of 2023, despite being a highlight in terms of the number of passes and progressive passes, doesn't have the same impact when it comes to finishing moves. Among the teams compared, they have the fewest xG per game (1.26), reinforcing what we said in our first post when we commented that England 2023 had a very methodical style of play. Even with a good capacity for progression, the team doesn't take many shots and, consequently, doesn't accumulate many expected goals compared to the other top teams. Final Considerations and Conclusion Throughout this post, we've focused on comparing teams that are well-established on the women's football scenario (perhaps the least well-established of these is Spain in 2019, a fact that only magnifies their winning campaign in 2023). So it was only natural that all the teams, even with differences in play and style, would be “well placed” in the graphs shown. At least in the two graphs shown, the prediction actually came true, with all 8 teams being above average in the 4 metrics used. This concludes another post in our series on the 2023 Women's World Cup, and the fourth post will be the last in the series. Stay tuned for future posts!]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">2023 Women’s World Cup - Promising players</title><link href="https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2024/post_women_world_cup_2_en/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="2023 Women’s World Cup - Promising players"/><published>2024-08-08T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-08-08T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2024/post_women_world_cup_2_en</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2024/post_women_world_cup_2_en/"><![CDATA[<hr/> <p align="justify"> Se quiser ler este texto em pt-br, <a href="https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2000/post_women_world_cup_2_pt/"> clique aqui.</a> </p> <h2>Introduction</h2> <div style="text-align: justify"> In the second post of our series analyzing the 2023 Women's World Cup, we'll talk about two players who have shown enormous potential during the most important international competition. Even with very short careers, Spain's Salma Paralluelo, 20, and Colombia's Linda Caicedo, 19, have already been nominated to be among the 10 best players in the world in 2023 (according to the Ballon d'Or awards). <br/><br/> <h3>Salma Paralluelo</h3> Considered the third best player in the world in the 23/24 season, Paralluelo is currently one of Barcelona's main offensive players, as well as being an almost absolute starter for the Spanish national team, even though she has only been playing for a short time. The young player is left-footed, and in the national team she usually plays as a center forward. <br/><br/> Paralluelo was decisive in winning the 2023 World Cup. As well as starting in all 7 games,<b> she scored two very important goals</b> for her team in the competition: a goal against the Netherlands in the quarter-finals and another against Sweden in the semi-finals. <br/><br/> Graph 1 shows all of Paralluelo's progressive actions during the competition. It can be seen that there is a high concentration of these actions on the left side of the pitch, with many carries directed towards the back line and many passes directed towards the center of the opponent's box. In the 7 games she played during the 2023 World Cup, Salma played as a right winger, as a left winger and, above all, as a center forward. Her position wasn't fixed during the competition, and this fluctuation allowed us to better visualize her playing preference, since even though she was in other positions, she was always more participative on the left. <br/><br/> <b>Definition of progressive action:</b> Actions in the first 30% of the pitch are ignored. They must reduce the distance from the ball to the opponent's goal by at least 15%. Only successful passes or drives that are finished closer vertically to the opponent's goal or that have their end point inside the opponent's penalty area are counted. <br/><br/> <div style="width: 100%; margin: 0 auto; text-align: center;"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2024-08-09-post_women_world_cup_2/paralluelo_progressive_actions.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <center>Graph 1. Salma Paralluelo’s Progressive Actions<br/><br/></center> Something interesting to note is the <b>high number of progressive carries</b>, a common characteristic of fast players with good physical conditioning. Coincidence or not, <b>Paralluelo practiced athletics</b> (short- and middle-distance running) for many years, even going so far as to have to combine this activity with playing football at the club that revealed her, Villarreal. <br/><br/> We also need to mention another important attribute of Paralluelo's for his team: her <b>ability to pressurize the ball</b>. As we mentioned in our last post, Spain's style of play is very aggressive. To put this into practice, their attacking players have to be involved even when the team is without the ball, and Paralluelo is one of the best examples to show how this happens, as she is the <b>third Spanish player with the most defensive actions in the competition</b>, with the vast majority of these actions being performed in the opponent's half. <br/><br/> <div style="width: 100%; margin: 0 auto; text-align: center;"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2024-08-09-post_women_world_cup_2/paralluelo_defensive_actions.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <center> Graph 2. Salma Paralluelo’s Defensive Actions<br/><br/></center> <h3> Linda Caicedo </h3> Linda was nominated as the ninth best player in the world in 2023 (by the Ballon d'Or awards). She is currently a midfielder for Real Madrid and the Colombian national team, and a first team regular for both. In the national team, Linda is generally more of an offensive player, which makes it possible to think of her as a <b>classic attacking midfielder</b>. At the 2023 Women's World Cup, she was a starter in all five of Colombia's matches (eliminated in the quarter-finals), <b>scoring two goals and providing one assist</b>. <br/><br/> In the map of progressive actions, we can see a large <b>flow of actions that start on the left and end up in the center or on the right of the field</b>. Compared to Paralluelo, we can see that even with an almost equal number of progressive actions per 90 minutes, <b>Caicedo executes many more progressive passes/90</b> (Caicedo 3.75 vs. 3.27 Paralluelo), while the Spaniard uses a lot of carries to attempt to attack (Caicedo 5.06 vs. 5.64 Paralluelo). <br/><br/> In all, Linda had 47 progressive actions during the competition, making her the <b>third Colombian player with the most progressive actions per 90 minutes</b>. <br/><br/> <div style="width: 100%; margin: 0 auto; text-align: center;"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2024-08-09-post_women_world_cup_2/caicedo_progressive_actions.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <center> Graph 3. Linda Caicedo’s Progressive Actions<br/><br/></center> In addition, her passing radar (graph 4) shows that Linda's touches are mostly directed to the right side, which reinforces the idea that she is more likely to play on the left. The Colombian plays an important role in turnovers, passing medium and long balls to the opposite side of the pitch in an attempt to find spaces to attack. <br/><br/> <div style="width: 100%; margin: 0 auto; text-align: center;"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2024-08-09-post_women_world_cup_2/caicedo_sonar_map.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <center> Graph 4. Linda Caicedo's Pass Sonar Map<br/><br/></center> <h2> Salma Paralluelo x Linda Caicedo </h2> In the graph below, OP refers to "Open Play", i.e. only shots with the ball in play are considered, disregarding penalties, fouls or corners. In addition, all the metrics were normalized according to the number of minutes played by the players. <br/><br/> Despite playing in different sectors, it is still extremely valid to compare the two in terms of offensive statistics. Looking at xG and goals, <b>Linda's incredible efficiency stands out</b>, as she has accumulated over 0.37 goals with around 0.06 expected goals. <b>Salma has a very intense contribution in shots</b>, finishing almost 3 times every 90 minutes, while Linda articulates the game considerably more with passes, executing almost 30 passes per match. <br/><br/> In addition, there is a considerable discrepancy in passing accuracy between the two players, with Linda Caicedo having a good advantage. However, this can be explained by the difference in the positions and roles played by the two players. As she played most of her minutes as a center forward at the World Cup, Paralluelo was often faced with a context in which <b>passes are more difficult and more susceptible to error</b>, as she is marked more intensely than players who play in Linda's position. Despite this, we can say that <b>Paralluelo is efficient when passing under pressure</b>, a very important characteristic for any center forward. <br/><br/> <div style="width: 100%; margin: 0 auto; text-align: center;"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2024-08-09-post_women_world_cup_2/comparative_radar.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <center>Graph 5. Comparative Radar between Paralluelo and Caicedo<br/><br/></center> <h2>Conclusion</h2> After this analysis, we can get an idea of the characteristics and potential of these two young players, who should be even more important for their team and for the women's soccer scene at the 2027 World Cup, which will be hosted in Brazil. <br/><br/> This was our second post analyzing the 2023 Women's World Cup. Our next post will focus on the most outstanding players in the competition, but without the emphasis on promising young players. Stay tuned for the rest of our series! <br/><br/> <div> </div></div>]]></content><author><name>Ace Laboratory Football Team - Daniel Barros, Hugo Antunes</name></author><category term="Football;"/><category term="Analysis"/><category term="Football;"/><category term="Women&apos;s"/><category term="World"/><category term="Cup;"/><category term="Analysis"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Se quiser ler este texto em pt-br, clique aqui. Introduction In the second post of our series analyzing the 2023 Women's World Cup, we'll talk about two players who have shown enormous potential during the most important international competition. Even with very short careers, Spain's Salma Paralluelo, 20, and Colombia's Linda Caicedo, 19, have already been nominated to be among the 10 best players in the world in 2023 (according to the Ballon d'Or awards). Salma Paralluelo Considered the third best player in the world in the 23/24 season, Paralluelo is currently one of Barcelona's main offensive players, as well as being an almost absolute starter for the Spanish national team, even though she has only been playing for a short time. The young player is left-footed, and in the national team she usually plays as a center forward. Paralluelo was decisive in winning the 2023 World Cup. As well as starting in all 7 games, she scored two very important goals for her team in the competition: a goal against the Netherlands in the quarter-finals and another against Sweden in the semi-finals. Graph 1 shows all of Paralluelo's progressive actions during the competition. It can be seen that there is a high concentration of these actions on the left side of the pitch, with many carries directed towards the back line and many passes directed towards the center of the opponent's box. In the 7 games she played during the 2023 World Cup, Salma played as a right winger, as a left winger and, above all, as a center forward. Her position wasn't fixed during the competition, and this fluctuation allowed us to better visualize her playing preference, since even though she was in other positions, she was always more participative on the left. Definition of progressive action: Actions in the first 30% of the pitch are ignored. They must reduce the distance from the ball to the opponent's goal by at least 15%. Only successful passes or drives that are finished closer vertically to the opponent's goal or that have their end point inside the opponent's penalty area are counted. Graph 1. Salma Paralluelo’s Progressive Actions Something interesting to note is the high number of progressive carries, a common characteristic of fast players with good physical conditioning. Coincidence or not, Paralluelo practiced athletics (short- and middle-distance running) for many years, even going so far as to have to combine this activity with playing football at the club that revealed her, Villarreal. We also need to mention another important attribute of Paralluelo's for his team: her ability to pressurize the ball. As we mentioned in our last post, Spain's style of play is very aggressive. To put this into practice, their attacking players have to be involved even when the team is without the ball, and Paralluelo is one of the best examples to show how this happens, as she is the third Spanish player with the most defensive actions in the competition, with the vast majority of these actions being performed in the opponent's half. Graph 2. Salma Paralluelo’s Defensive Actions Linda Caicedo Linda was nominated as the ninth best player in the world in 2023 (by the Ballon d'Or awards). She is currently a midfielder for Real Madrid and the Colombian national team, and a first team regular for both. In the national team, Linda is generally more of an offensive player, which makes it possible to think of her as a classic attacking midfielder. At the 2023 Women's World Cup, she was a starter in all five of Colombia's matches (eliminated in the quarter-finals), scoring two goals and providing one assist. In the map of progressive actions, we can see a large flow of actions that start on the left and end up in the center or on the right of the field. Compared to Paralluelo, we can see that even with an almost equal number of progressive actions per 90 minutes, Caicedo executes many more progressive passes/90 (Caicedo 3.75 vs. 3.27 Paralluelo), while the Spaniard uses a lot of carries to attempt to attack (Caicedo 5.06 vs. 5.64 Paralluelo). In all, Linda had 47 progressive actions during the competition, making her the third Colombian player with the most progressive actions per 90 minutes. Graph 3. Linda Caicedo’s Progressive Actions In addition, her passing radar (graph 4) shows that Linda's touches are mostly directed to the right side, which reinforces the idea that she is more likely to play on the left. The Colombian plays an important role in turnovers, passing medium and long balls to the opposite side of the pitch in an attempt to find spaces to attack. Graph 4. Linda Caicedo's Pass Sonar Map Salma Paralluelo x Linda Caicedo In the graph below, OP refers to "Open Play", i.e. only shots with the ball in play are considered, disregarding penalties, fouls or corners. In addition, all the metrics were normalized according to the number of minutes played by the players. Despite playing in different sectors, it is still extremely valid to compare the two in terms of offensive statistics. Looking at xG and goals, Linda's incredible efficiency stands out, as she has accumulated over 0.37 goals with around 0.06 expected goals. Salma has a very intense contribution in shots, finishing almost 3 times every 90 minutes, while Linda articulates the game considerably more with passes, executing almost 30 passes per match. In addition, there is a considerable discrepancy in passing accuracy between the two players, with Linda Caicedo having a good advantage. However, this can be explained by the difference in the positions and roles played by the two players. As she played most of her minutes as a center forward at the World Cup, Paralluelo was often faced with a context in which passes are more difficult and more susceptible to error, as she is marked more intensely than players who play in Linda's position. Despite this, we can say that Paralluelo is efficient when passing under pressure, a very important characteristic for any center forward. Graph 5. Comparative Radar between Paralluelo and Caicedo Conclusion After this analysis, we can get an idea of the characteristics and potential of these two young players, who should be even more important for their team and for the women's soccer scene at the 2027 World Cup, which will be hosted in Brazil. This was our second post analyzing the 2023 Women's World Cup. Our next post will focus on the most outstanding players in the competition, but without the emphasis on promising young players. Stay tuned for the rest of our series!]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">2023 Women’s World Cup - Analyzing the finalists</title><link href="https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2024/post_women_world_cup_1_en/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="2023 Women’s World Cup - Analyzing the finalists"/><published>2024-07-31T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-07-31T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2024/post_women_world_cup_1_en</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2024/post_women_world_cup_1_en/"><![CDATA[<hr/> <p align="justify"> Se quiser ler este texto em pt-br, <a href="https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2000/post_women_world_cup_1_pt/"> clique aqui.</a> </p> <h2>Introduction</h2> <div style="text-align: justify"> In this series of posts, we're going to do a general analysis of the 2023 Women's World Cup, hosted simultaneously in Australia and New Zealand. We'll provide general comparisons between all the teams, and then delve into the four semi-finalists and the highlights of the competition. <br/><br/> In this post, we'll talk about both the finalists of the 2023 Women's World Cup: Spain and England. <br/><br/> <h3>Tournament Overview</h3> Popularly known as a short tournament, since 7 is the maximum number of games a team can play, the World Cup is the biggest tournament in the world played by national teams. In 2023, Spain were crowned world champions in women's soccer against England, with a very young team, just like in men's soccer, with an average age of less than 26 in the starting line-up.<br/><br/> <h3>The final </h3> The final of the 2023 Women's World Cup was held on August 20 and featured England and Spain. The Spaniards came out on top, winning the game 1-0 with a goal from Olga Carmona in the 29th minute (it's worth noting that Spain had the chance to extend the lead with a missed penalty in the second half). The Spanish team played a strong and solid game, accumulating <b>more than 2 expected goals</b>, superiority in possession, and <b>3 great chances created</b> during the course of the match.<br/><br/> Despite a bitter fourth place in the previous World Cup, England were coming off the back of winning the Finalissima (a play-off between the winner of the EURO and the winner of the Copa America) over Brazil, as well as an excellent run so far in the 2023 World Cup. Even so, they were unable to impose their game on the Spain team. The English side accumulated less than <b>0.5</b> expected goals, as well as <b>only one great chance created</b>, showing that the <b>43% possession</b> did not convert into volume of play.<br/><br/> <h2> Analyzing the finalists </h2> In the graphs below, you can get a better idea of how the finalists played in the tournament. In the passing graph, it is noticeable that the English team <b>tends to pass a lot behind the midfield line</b>, with the defenders playing a significant role in a very withdrawn position. Spain's passing is<b> more concentrated in midfield, suggesting a more aggressive style of play</b> compared to their opponents in the last game. This analysis of the tournament is reflected in the final, as Spain, choosing to dictate the game more and exchanging more passes in areas closer to the opponent's goal, created most of the chances and accumulated a greater number of expected goals.<br/><br/> <div style="width: 100%; margin: 0 auto; text-align: center;"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2024-08-01-post_women_world_cup_1/pass_heatmap_comparison.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <center>Graph 1. Pass Heatmap (in all the competition)<br/><br/></center> In this second graph, we show in which areas of the pitch each team applies the most pressure to their opponents throughout the tournament. Again, the Spanish side's map suggests a <b>more aggressive style</b>, concentrating their pressing actions on the opponent's pitch. On the other hand, the England team<b> presses more evenly across the pitch</b>, with only one area of high concentration: the right side, near the halfway line.<br/><br/> <div style="width: 100%; margin: 0 auto; text-align: center;"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2024-08-01-post_women_world_cup_1/pressure_heatmap_comparison.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <center>Graph 2. Pressure Heatmap (in all the competition)<br/><br/></center> Apart from the tactical aspect, something very interesting to note is the average age of the Spanish team. Spain's starting line-up in the final had an <b>average age of 25.7</b>, one of the lowest in the entire competition and the lowest among the teams that played in the knockout stage. This suggests that Spain's reformulation, which was much talked about and praised recently during the men's Euro, is also (very positively) affecting the women's team. In the final, 6 of the 10 best players in the world (according to the Ballon d'Or awards) were on the pitch. Of these, 4 were Spanish players (two were under 25, and we'll talk more about one of them in a later post!). <br/><br/> In the next section, we'll use shot maps to analyze the attacking performance of the finalist teams during the competition. Spain's map shows their aggressive style, <b>being the team with the most goals and shots per game (22.1)</b> of all the teams in the competition. On the other hand, it's important to note the efficiency of England's shots, as they had a <b>positive balance of 3.18 in the difference between goals and xG</b>. In addition, it's worth noting that the England side shoot far less than their opponents in the final, with an average of <b>13.2 shots per game</b>.<br/><br/> <div style="width: 100%; margin: 0 auto; text-align: center;"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2024-08-01-post_women_world_cup_1/spain_shot_map.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <center>Graph 3. Spain's Shot Map (in all the competition)<br/><br/></center> <div style="width: 100%; margin: 0 auto; text-align: center;"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2024-08-01-post_women_world_cup_1/england_shot_map.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <center>Graph 4. England's Shot Map (in all the competition)<br/><br/></center> As is often the case in many important finals, <b>the teams had lower attacking numbers than "expected"</b> (based on their performance throughout the competition), since, given the importance of the match, the teams usually choose to play in a more studied and less risky way. Spain had <b>13</b> shots in the match, while England had <b>8</b>.<br/><br/> <h2>Conclusion</h2> During the analysis, we can see that there is a certain duality between the teams. Spain, being an example of a young and dynamic team, successfully imposed their style of play during the tournament, <b>being aggressive with and without the ball</b>. On the other side, England play in a <b>more methodical way</b>, not daring to use high blocks of pressure and constantly keeping possession with their defenders. Both ways of playing soccer were <b>examples of success</b> during the competition, but in the end the Spanish style prevailed. <br/><br/> Despite finishing second in the most important international competition, England are the current champions of the Women's EURO (having knocked out Spain themselves during the tournament). So everything indicates that the duel that decided the world title in 2023 will continue to be very relevant and fierce in the future. <br/><br/> That was our first post analyzing the 2023 Women's World Cup. <b>Our next post will focus on the young players who stood out in the tournament</b> and are expected to be even more prominent in the 2027 World Cup, which will be hosted in Brazil. <br/><br/> <div> </div></div>]]></content><author><name>Ace Laboratory Football Team - Daniel Barros, Hugo Antunes</name></author><category term="Football;"/><category term="Analysis"/><category term="Football;"/><category term="Analysis;"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Se quiser ler este texto em pt-br, clique aqui. Introduction In this series of posts, we're going to do a general analysis of the 2023 Women's World Cup, hosted simultaneously in Australia and New Zealand. We'll provide general comparisons between all the teams, and then delve into the four semi-finalists and the highlights of the competition. In this post, we'll talk about both the finalists of the 2023 Women's World Cup: Spain and England. Tournament Overview Popularly known as a short tournament, since 7 is the maximum number of games a team can play, the World Cup is the biggest tournament in the world played by national teams. In 2023, Spain were crowned world champions in women's soccer against England, with a very young team, just like in men's soccer, with an average age of less than 26 in the starting line-up. The final The final of the 2023 Women's World Cup was held on August 20 and featured England and Spain. The Spaniards came out on top, winning the game 1-0 with a goal from Olga Carmona in the 29th minute (it's worth noting that Spain had the chance to extend the lead with a missed penalty in the second half). The Spanish team played a strong and solid game, accumulating more than 2 expected goals, superiority in possession, and 3 great chances created during the course of the match. Despite a bitter fourth place in the previous World Cup, England were coming off the back of winning the Finalissima (a play-off between the winner of the EURO and the winner of the Copa America) over Brazil, as well as an excellent run so far in the 2023 World Cup. Even so, they were unable to impose their game on the Spain team. The English side accumulated less than 0.5 expected goals, as well as only one great chance created, showing that the 43% possession did not convert into volume of play. Analyzing the finalists In the graphs below, you can get a better idea of how the finalists played in the tournament. In the passing graph, it is noticeable that the English team tends to pass a lot behind the midfield line, with the defenders playing a significant role in a very withdrawn position. Spain's passing is more concentrated in midfield, suggesting a more aggressive style of play compared to their opponents in the last game. This analysis of the tournament is reflected in the final, as Spain, choosing to dictate the game more and exchanging more passes in areas closer to the opponent's goal, created most of the chances and accumulated a greater number of expected goals. Graph 1. Pass Heatmap (in all the competition) In this second graph, we show in which areas of the pitch each team applies the most pressure to their opponents throughout the tournament. Again, the Spanish side's map suggests a more aggressive style, concentrating their pressing actions on the opponent's pitch. On the other hand, the England team presses more evenly across the pitch, with only one area of high concentration: the right side, near the halfway line. Graph 2. Pressure Heatmap (in all the competition) Apart from the tactical aspect, something very interesting to note is the average age of the Spanish team. Spain's starting line-up in the final had an average age of 25.7, one of the lowest in the entire competition and the lowest among the teams that played in the knockout stage. This suggests that Spain's reformulation, which was much talked about and praised recently during the men's Euro, is also (very positively) affecting the women's team. In the final, 6 of the 10 best players in the world (according to the Ballon d'Or awards) were on the pitch. Of these, 4 were Spanish players (two were under 25, and we'll talk more about one of them in a later post!). In the next section, we'll use shot maps to analyze the attacking performance of the finalist teams during the competition. Spain's map shows their aggressive style, being the team with the most goals and shots per game (22.1) of all the teams in the competition. On the other hand, it's important to note the efficiency of England's shots, as they had a positive balance of 3.18 in the difference between goals and xG. In addition, it's worth noting that the England side shoot far less than their opponents in the final, with an average of 13.2 shots per game. Graph 3. Spain's Shot Map (in all the competition) Graph 4. England's Shot Map (in all the competition) As is often the case in many important finals, the teams had lower attacking numbers than "expected" (based on their performance throughout the competition), since, given the importance of the match, the teams usually choose to play in a more studied and less risky way. Spain had 13 shots in the match, while England had 8. Conclusion During the analysis, we can see that there is a certain duality between the teams. Spain, being an example of a young and dynamic team, successfully imposed their style of play during the tournament, being aggressive with and without the ball. On the other side, England play in a more methodical way, not daring to use high blocks of pressure and constantly keeping possession with their defenders. Both ways of playing soccer were examples of success during the competition, but in the end the Spanish style prevailed. Despite finishing second in the most important international competition, England are the current champions of the Women's EURO (having knocked out Spain themselves during the tournament). So everything indicates that the duel that decided the world title in 2023 will continue to be very relevant and fierce in the future. That was our first post analyzing the 2023 Women's World Cup. Our next post will focus on the young players who stood out in the tournament and are expected to be even more prominent in the 2027 World Cup, which will be hosted in Brazil.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">An Optimization Model for Personalized Itineraries: Insights from our Olympics Planner 2024</title><link href="https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2024/post_olympics_planner_2024/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="An Optimization Model for Personalized Itineraries: Insights from our Olympics Planner 2024"/><published>2024-07-15T10:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-07-15T10:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2024/post_olympics_planner_2024</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2024/post_olympics_planner_2024/"><![CDATA[<h2 id="introduction">Introduction</h2> <p align="justify"> As the Paris 2024 Olympic Games draw near, we are pleased to introduce the Olympics Planner 2024. This tool is engineered to provide personalized itineraries that cater to individual preferences, using advanced algorithms to help attendees fully engage with the events, attractions, and venues. In this post, we will explore the methodologies and technologies behind the development of the Olympics Planner 2024.<br/><br/> </p> <h2 id="data-collection">Data Collection</h2> <p align="justify"> We sourced our dataset from the official publications of<a href="https://tickets.paris2024.org/en/"> the Paris Olympic Committee</a>, which provided details about event schedules, ticket pricing, and venue information. We gathered data on event timings, costs of tickets, and the exact locations of venues, documented with both addresses and geographic coordinates.<br/><br/> Scripts were crafted to extract this information from the official Olympic website, a process that presented challenges due to the complex presentation of the site's data and issues with data accessibility. These obstacles underscore the complexities of employing this methodology with historical Olympic data, which may be even harder to access.<br/><br/> Additionally, we incorporated financial considerations into our model by including both the average travel costs between events and the ticket prices. To ensure total expenses remained within the allocated budget, we introduced a budget constraint. Travel costs were estimated by calculating the travel time between venues and multiplying it by the average cost per minute, providing a more realistic assessment of the financial implications of attending multiple events. </p> <h2 id="the-model">The Model</h2> <p align="justify"> We approached the task of crafting optimal viewing schedules for the Olympic Games by formulating it as a network flow optimization model. Our goal was to develop personalized schedules that prioritized spectator preferences while ensuring the feasibility of travel and maintaining a coherent schedule. <br/><br/> Consider a directed graph \( G = (V, A) \), where \( V \) represents the set of vertices denoting Olympic events, and \( A \) represents the arcs denoting transitions between events.<br/><br/> Each event \( i \in V \) is defined by its start time \( t^{\text{start}}_i \) and duration \( \text{duration}_i \), where \( t^{\text{end}}_i = t^{\text{start}}_i + \text{duration}_i \). The start time \( t^{\text{start}}_i \) denotes the minute within the total Olympic timeline when event \( i \) begins.<br/><br/> Each event \( i \in V \) has an associated ticket price \( c_i \). Additionally, there is an average travel cost per minute \( c_{ij} \) for each arc \( (i, j) \in A \). The total travel cost between events \( i \) and \( j \) is given by \( c_{ij} \times t_{ij} \), where \( t_{ij} \) represents the travel time in minutes between the two events. Spectators have a maximum budget \( B \), which serves as an upper limit on total costs, covering both ticket prices and travel expenses.<br/><br/> In addition to costs, each event \( i \in V \) is assigned a preference score \( p_i \), reflecting spectator interest in attending that event.<br/><br/> Let \( x_{ij} \) be a binary decision variable for arc \( (i, j) \in A \), where \( x_{ij} = 1 \) indicates a spectator travels from event \( i \) to event \( j \), and \( x_{ij} = 0 \) otherwise. Similarly, let \( w_i \) be a binary decision variable for vertex \( i \in V \), where \( w_i = 1 \) indicates attendance at event \( i \), and \( w_i = 0 \) otherwise.<br/><br/> The optimization problem is formulated as follows: $$ \begin{align} \text{Maximize} \quad &amp; Z = \sum_{i \in V} p_i w_i \label{eq:objective}\\ \text{subject to} \\ &amp; \sum_{j \in V \setminus \{i\}} x_{ij} = w_i, \quad \forall i \in V \setminus \{n+1\} \label{eq:sequence_1}\\ &amp; \sum_{i \in V \setminus \{j\}} x_{ij} = w_j, \quad \forall j \in V \setminus \{0\} \label{eq:sequence_2}\\ &amp; \sum_{i \in V} x_{0i} = 1 \label{eq:start}\\ &amp; \sum_{i \in V} x_{i(n+1)} = 1 \label{eq:end}\\ &amp; t^{\text{end}}i + t{ij} - M_{ij}(1 - x_{ij}) \leq t^{\text{start}}_j, \quad \forall i, j \in V, i \neq j \label{eq:travel_time}\\ &amp; \sum_{i \in V} c_i w_i + \sum_{j \in V} x_{ij}c_{ij}t_{ij} \leq B \label{eq:budget}\\ &amp; x_{ij} \in \{0, 1\}, \quad \forall (i, j) \in A \label{eq:binary_x}\\ &amp; w_i \in \{0, 1\}, \quad \forall i \in V \label{eq:binary_y} \end{align} $$ <p align="justify"> where, <br/><br/> </p> $$ \begin{align} M_{ij} = \max\{0, t^{\text{end}}i + t{ij} - t^{\text{start}}_j\} \end{align} $$ The objective function \( Z \) aims to maximize the total preference score, thereby prioritizing events that spectators are highly interested in attending. Constraints ensure logical sequencing of events (\( \ref{eq:sequence_1} \) and \( \ref{eq:sequence_2} \)), define the start (\( \ref{eq:start} \)) and end (\( \ref{eq:end} \)) of the viewing schedule, enforce feasible travel times (\( \ref{eq:travel_time} \)), and maintain budget constraints (\( \ref{eq:budget} \)). Variables \( x_{ij} \) and \( w_i \) are binary, ensuring the model's feasibility and practical application. </p> <p align="justify"> The model's implementation consisted of three key steps: constructing a directed graph, calculating travel times, and assigning preference scores and costs to each event.<br/><br/> Preference scores were allocated to each event based on spectator interest, categorized into five levels ranging from "Very Uninterested" to "Very Interested," each assigned a specific weight. Additionally, the cost of attending each event was incorporated into the model by including ticket prices. Travel times between venues for spectators attending in person were determined using Geographic Information System (GIS) tools. These tools accounted for actual travel routes and car travel durations to ensure feasible transitions between events within the planned schedule.<br/><br/> </p> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2024-07-15-olympics-planner/routejpg.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <h2 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2> <p align="justify"> This research introduces a novel approach to optimizing Olympic Game-Watching Schedules using network flow optimization. Set within a directed graph, the model seamlessly integrates spectator preferences, travel logistics, and budget considerations to craft personalized viewing schedules that enhance the overall experience. This innovative use of operations research in large-scale event management sets a new benchmark for complex scheduling solutions.<br/><br/> To make this tool available to the public, we developed a website where users can create their own itinerary for the 2024 Paris Olympic Games.<br/><br/> Explore your custom Olympic schedule here: <a href="https://olympicsplanner.ace.cos.ufrj.br/"> Olympics Planner 2024</a> </p>]]></content><author><name>Amanda Azevedo, Almir Júnior, Pedro Siqueira</name></author><category term="Olympics;"/><category term="Paris"/><category term="Olympics;"/><category term="Paris"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Discover how we developed the Olympics Planner 2024, an optimization model designed to create personalized itineraries for the Paris Olympic Games.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">In-Depth Analysis of Bayer Leverkusen - Key Players</title><link href="https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2024/post_leverkusen_3_en/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="In-Depth Analysis of Bayer Leverkusen - Key Players"/><published>2024-05-27T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-05-27T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2024/post_leverkusen_3_en</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2024/post_leverkusen_3_en/"><![CDATA[<hr/> <p align="justify"> Se quiser ler este texto em pt-br, <a href="https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2000/post_leverkusen_3_pt/"> clique aqui.</a> </p> <h2>Introduction</h2> <div style="text-align: justify"> As we covered in the first post in this series, Xabi Alonso's Bayer Leverkusen play in a very unique way by today's soccer standards, and this is no coincidence. The coach manages to get the most out of his players, and in the 23/24 season, almost all of them can be considered individual highlights in their respective roles. <br/><br/> In this post, we'll talk about the most important players for the Bundesliga champion's functioning. <br/><br/> <h3>The wingbacks, Grimaldo and Frimpong:</h3> One of the most interesting and unique features of this team is the presence of two extremely attacking wing-backs, who play a big part in the build-up play and are often in the final third of the pitch to complete plays. <br/><br/> The man in charge on the left side of the pitch is <b>Alejandro Grimaldo</b>. The 28-year-old Spaniard was bought from Benfica this season and has quickly become a key part of Xabi's style of play, and can even be considered, alongside Florian Wirtz, <b>the most important player in the team</b>. As well as being an excellent passer and playmaker, Grimaldo has two other attributes worth mentioning: his long-range shot and his free-kick. This season alone, the Spaniard <b>has scored 3 goals from outside the box, 2 of them from free-kicks</b>. <br/><br/> After such impressive performances during the season, Grimaldo was called up to play for his national team for the first time. <br/><br/> <div style="width: 100%; margin: 0 auto; text-align: center;"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2024-05-27-post_leverkusen_3/Alejandro_Grimaldo.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> In the Bundesliga, Grimaldo was <b>the 6th player with the most goals scored</b>, but above him, there are only the center forwards, such as Bayern Munich's Harry Kane and RB Leipzig's Loïs Openda. The Bayer Leverkusen wingback was also the competition's <b>leader in assists</b> and <b>second in chances created</b>. <br/><br/> On the right wingback is Dutchman <b>Jeremie Frimpong</b>. The 23-year-old was signed from Bayer Leverkusen in the 20/21 season, but only established himself as a first-team regular the following season. Since then, it's been possible to see a big improvement in Frimpong's performance, which has become even clearer with the arrival of Xabi Alonso at the helm. <br/><br/> <div style="width: 100%; margin: 0 auto; text-align: center;"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2024-05-27-post_leverkusen_3/Jeremie_Frimpong.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> The evolution in performance is clearly linked to <b>the change in the player's role, which became more attacking</b> with the arrival of the Spanish coach. We can see that, comparing Frimpong's first season as a starter at Leverkusen (the only one managed entirely by Gerardo Seoane) and the following two seasons, <b>the Dutchman's number of goal-scoring involvements has doubled.</b> <br/><br/> <div style="width: 100%; margin: 0 auto; text-align: center;"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2024-05-27-post_leverkusen_3/FrimpogGA.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> It's important to note that Seoane was in charge of Leverkusen until the 8th round of the 22/23 Bundesliga season. In those 8 games, Frimpong scored two goals (an average of 0.25 goals per game). From matchday 9 onwards, with Xabi Alonso taking over as coach, Frimpong's number of goals per game rose to 0.5, showing that the period with the new coach had a much greater impact on his total number of goals and assists that season.<br/><br/> Looking at Frimpong's numbers pre-Xabi and post-Xabi, it's clear how much <b>the coach was a determining factor in the development of the Dutchman's offensive potential</b>. To show this more clearly, we looked at the heatmaps of all Frimpong's games from the 21/22 season to the current one, and grouped them into time intervals with data from 7 to 9 different games. In this way, we can better visualize the process of the Dutchman moving away from the defensive sector and towards the offensive sector, especially after Xabi Alonso's debut as coach on October 8, 2022. It's interesting to see, in the 23/24 season, <b>an intense occupation of the right side of the opponent's penalty area</b>. <br/><br/> <figure> <video src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2024-05-27-post_leverkusen_3/gif_frimpong_time_final.mp4" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" autoplay="" controls=""/> </figure> Analyzing the statistics of these two players in the Bundesliga made it even clearer what we meant when we said that this team is marked by its extremely attacking wingbacks. <br/><br/> <h3>The midfielder, Xhaka:</h3> The silent highlights of Xabi Alonso's team are in the more defensive part of midfield. In this area of the pitch, there are players who, despite their great importance to the team's functioning, are little remembered because they don't have inflated offensive numbers. <br/><br/> In one of the positions, there is a kind of relay, as on several occasions Argentinian Exequiel Palacios gives way to German Robert Andrich and, more often than not, the two perform very well. <br/><br/> On the other hand, one midfielder is unquestionable in the line-up. Swiss midfielder <b>Granit Xhaka</b> has made 32 Bundesliga appearances as a starter (33 including the one game he came on from the bench), and averages 86 minutes per game, showing that on the rare occasions he is substituted, it is only at the end of matches. As a result, Xhaka is Bayer Leverkusen's <b>second most-used player in the Bundesliga</b>, only behind goalkeeper Lukáš Hrádecký. <br/><br/> As well as his regularity in terms of playing time, it's important to highlight the player's incredible regularity in passing. Xhaka is the Bundesliga's <b>leader in accurate passes</b>, and has made an impressive 15 appearances with more than 100 passes and 90% accuracy. <br/><br/> <div style="width: 100%; margin: 0 auto; text-align: center;"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2024-05-27-post_leverkusen_3/Granit_Xhaka.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> Next, we'll show the “sonar map” of Granit Xhaka's passes. The graph was created using data on the player's position, final position and the distance of the pass. From this, we were able to find out at which angle each pass comes from and, assuming 0º as the direction of the opponent's goal, group the passes by these angles. The number above each bar corresponds to the number of passes that occurred in that direction.<br/><br/> <div style="width: 100%; margin: 0 auto; text-align: center;"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2024-05-27-post_leverkusen_3/sonar_map.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <h3>The star, Florian Wirtz:</h3> You can't talk about Bayer Leverkusen without mentioning <b>Florian Wirtz</b>. Alongside Grimaldo, the 20-year-old German is considered the team's main player. The young attacking midfielder is almost impeccable in all offensive aspects: finishing, passing, dribbling, game vision, high pressing, etc. <br/><br/> Since his arrival at Bayer Leverkusen in 2020, Wirtz has been considered <b>one of the great promises of German soccer</b>, and every season he shows more of his potential. But, like many others in this team, it was Xabi Alonso who was responsible for getting the most out of Wirtz, who is having his best season in 23/24. <br/><br/> <div style="width: 100%; margin: 0 auto; text-align: center;"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2024-05-27-post_leverkusen_3/Florian_Wirtz.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> Looking at the league as a whole, Wirtz is a standout in several statistics. The German is <b>8th in the ranking of goals scored</b> (behind only center forwards, except for teammate Alejandro Grimaldo) and <b>4th in right dribbles per game</b>. <br/><br/> <h3>The striker, Boniface:</h3> Finally, let's talk about the team's center forward: 23-year-old Nigerian <b>Victor Okoh Boniface</b>. Unfortunately, Boniface was out from round 17 to round 27 due to a serious injury he suffered in January. Despite this factor reducing the sample size, it is important to talk about the striker, as he is essential to the model of play that has enchanted Europe since the start of the season. <br/><br/> Even though he is now seen as fundamental, Boniface's arrival at Leverkusen for 20 million euros seemed a risk, given that he came from the Belgian league and that, despite having had a good season, he wasn't that impressive. Fortunately for Xabi Alonso, the price quickly became too small for the excellent player he received. The Bayer Leverkusen striker's speed, physical strength, understanding of the game and repertoire have even led to him being <b>called up to the Nigerian national team for the first time</b>. <br/><br/> <div style="width: 100%; margin: 0 auto; text-align: center;"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2024-05-27-post_leverkusen_3/Victor_Boniface.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> It's also important to note <b>the difference felt by Bayer Leverkusen in the period without Boniface</b>. In the table below, we show the difference in the team's average goals per game in two different time intervals: the first 16 rounds, with Boniface available, and between rounds 17 and 27 (while Boniface was injured). We chose not to include the end of the championship in the comparison since, even if the player was available, his average minutes were much lower, a factor related to the period of greater caution with the player's health after injury. <br/><br/> <div style="width: 100%; margin: 0 auto; text-align: center;"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2024-05-27-post_leverkusen_3/BonifaceGoals.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> Despite almost 3 months out of the league, Boniface was <b>the 7th player with the most goal participations in Bundesliga 23/24</b>. <br/><br/> <h2>Conclusion</h2> In the last post in our series on Bayer Leverkusen, we analyzed the data relating to some of the most important players in the undefeated Bundesliga champions. The intention was to show the impact that the young but already winning coach Xabi Alonso has had on his players, especially during this very special season for the squad. It's safe to say that the Spaniard has been responsible for “revealing” several of the team's players to the world, including getting several of them, like Grimaldo and Boniface, called up to their national teams for the first time. We can also say that the world is looking forward to seeing more of Bayer Leverkusen next season, which will put the club to the test in the Champions League and in the defense of the national title. </div>]]></content><author><name>Ace Laboratory Football Team - Daniel Barros</name></author><category term="Football;"/><category term="Analysis"/><category term="Football;"/><category term="Bundesliga;"/><category term="Analysis"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">In-Depth Analysis of Bayer Leverkusen - Past Seasons and Current Campaign</title><link href="https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2024/post_leverkusen_2_en/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="In-Depth Analysis of Bayer Leverkusen - Past Seasons and Current Campaign"/><published>2024-05-23T10:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-05-23T10:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2024/post_leverkusen_2_en</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2024/post_leverkusen_2_en/"><![CDATA[<hr/> <p align="justify"> Se quiser ler este texto em pt-br, <a href="https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2000/post_leverkusen_2_pt/"> clique aqui.</a> </p> <h2>Introduction</h2> <div style="text-align: justify"> Many aspects of Leverkusen have changed under Xabi Alonso. Some of the main changes have been the players and the way the squad has been managed. Therefore, in order to understand the success Leverkusen have enjoyed this season, it's important to analyze what happened to the squad before and after Xabi Alonso's arrival.<br/><br/> <h2>Players in the Squad</h2> One of the main changes made after the arrival of Xabi Alonso was the management of the players in the squad. To make this clearer, we analyze the players in the team over the last 3 seasons.<br/><br/> <h3>Season 2021/2022</h3> In 21/22, the team had a vast squad, with a total of 35 players and an average age of close to 24.5 years. In addition, the average value per player was around 13 million euros. In that season, the most estimated sector of the field on the market was the attack, with a value of approximately 170.70 million euros.<br/><br/> In 2021, Leverkusen hired a new coach, Swiss Gerardo Seone, who played his first game on August 7, 2021. Under the Swiss, Leverkusen played mostly in a 4-2-3-1 formation, very different from what happens today with Xabi Alonso. It's worth remembering that <a href="https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2024/post_leverkusen_1_en/"> Xabi's style of play</a> has already been discussed here on our blog!<br/><br/> It was in the 2021 season that the current seventh most valuable player in the world gained more prominence, being a player used frequently by Gerardo. In addition to the Leverkusen revelation, other players began to gain more prominence in the team too, such as striker Shick, who was the team's top scorer that season.<br/><br/> <h3>Season 2022/2023</h3> In 22/23, the squad didn't change much; it remained substantially the same as in 21/22. However, it was during this season that Xabi Alonso took over the team. To be more precise, Xabi took charge of Leverkusen on matchday 9 of the Bundesliga and matchday 4 of the Champions League.<br/><br/> Despite the few changes to the squad in general, Leverkusen sold some defenders and signed more midfielders. As a result, the most valued sector in 2022 was the midfield, which was valued at more than 185 million euros at the time.<br/><br/> After these small changes, the squad still had 35 players in it, the same number as in the 21/22 season, with the average age dropping slightly to 24.2 years. The average value of each player remained similar compared to 21/22.<br/><br/> <div style="width: 100%; margin: 0 auto; text-align: center;"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2024-05-23-post_leverkusen_2/player_squad.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <h3>Season 2023/2024 (current season)</h3> After the end of Xabi's first season at Leverkusen, the coach appeared to have more autonomy in assembling the squad for 23/24. The number of players has dropped considerably compared to previous years, and Leverkusen now have just 27 players, a reduction of 22%. At the moment, Leverkusen's average age is 24.8 and the average value of each player is 22 million euros. In other words, the average age has changed very little, but the value per player has increased by almost 70% compared to the 22/23 season.<br/><br/> However, even with the considerable reduction in the squad, Leverkusen have moved much more on the market than in recent seasons. In addition, the total value of the current squad has increased by 31% compared to last season. It is therefore essential to analyze Leverkusen's signings this season and how the players have increased in value since Xabi Alonso's arrival.<br/><br/> <h2>Hiring</h2> The main signings made after the arrival of Xabi Alonso were the transfer of midfielder Xhaka, who played for Arsenal, for 25 million euros; the arrival of striker Boniface, who played for Union Saint-Gilloise in Belgium; the transfer of winger Grimaldo, who played for Benfica, who arrived for free; and the arrival of goalkeeper Kovar, who was at Manchester United, who cost around 5 million euros. The one-off signings were extremely important for the Leverkusen team, with the five main players in the German team being Wirtz, Palacios, Xhaka, Grimaldo, Kovar, and Boniface.<br/><br/> Despite the signings, the players who were already at the club have improved incredibly. To analyze the growth of players, their market value is a very interesting parameter. In the graph below, you can see the players who have risen the most in value since Xabi Alonso's arrival. It's important to note that Boniface, acquired this season by Leverkusen, already has a market value almost double what he was paid. Boniface and Grimaldo, the latter of whom was acquired for free, show how well the signings have been executed, making the most of the opportunities on the market.<br/><br/> <div style="width: 100%; margin: 0 auto; text-align: center;"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2024-05-23-post_leverkusen_2/player_market.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> In terms of player valuations alone, the balance was positive and exceeded 90 million euros. The estimated value of the total squad is almost 595 million euros, of which only 80 million were invested this year. It's worth remembering that in 2023 many players were sold, loaned, or released by Leverkusen, and the devaluation of the squad due to these losses totals 119 million. As such, in addition to the amount invested, Xabi Alonso's work has been fundamental in valuing the players. Xabi qualified the players already in the squad, and Leverkusen took advantage of the opportunities of a very competitive market.<br/><br/> <h2>Team Performance</h2> Finally, it's interesting to compare the development of the team over the three seasons mentioned above. In 2021/2022 before Xabi Alonso, in 2022/2023 before and after the arrival of the Spanish coach, and the 2023/2024 season when Xabi had more autonomy in the formation of the squad.<br/><br/> <h3>Season 2021/2022</h3> In the 21/22 season, Leverkusen performed well in terms of results. Despite an early exit from the Europa League, beaten by Atalanta in the last 16, they finished 3rd in the Bundesliga and therefore qualified for the Champions League the following season. One of the reasons for the squad remaining very similar in the 22/23 season is precisely the good performance in 21/22.<br/><br/> In 21/22, Leverkusen conceded 47 goals and scored 80, with a good offensive record, averaging 2.4 goals per game in the Bundesliga. In addition, the German team's main players this season were Wirtz, Shick, and Demirbay.<br/><br/> <h3>Season 2022/2023</h3> The start of the 22/23 season was very different from what was imagined. With the squad maintained and, therefore, the project continuing, it was expected that the team would at least achieve a performance similar to that of the 21/22 season. However, Leverkusen got off to a terrible start and by the 9th matchday of the Bundesliga were in 15th place, close to the relegation zone. At the same time, on Matchday 3 of the Champions League, they were bottom of their group, which included Club Brugge, Porto, and Atlético de Madrid.<br/><br/> After poor results, Xabi Alonso was invited to take over the team on October 8, 2022. After the arrival of the new coach, Leverkusen finished 3rd in the Champions League group stage and qualified for the Europa League, only to fall to Roma in the semi-finals. At the end of the season, Leverkusen finished 6th in the Bundesliga and secured a place in the 2023/2024 Europa League.<br/><br/> Leverkusen's main players after Xabi Alonso took over were Wirtz, Demirbay, and Palácios. In other words, Leverkusen's highlights remained similar to the 2021 season, but Palácios was able to develop much more after the Spanish coach's arrival.<br/><br/> <h3>Season 2023/2024</h3> This season, Leverkusen need no introduction. They've won their first Bundesliga title in history and without losing a single game. Still in the Bundesliga, they've scored a total of 89 goals and conceded just 24, an average of 2.6 goals per game. Leverkusen have also conquered an average of 62% of possession per match in the Bundesliga.<br/><br/> Apart from all the prominence the team had in the Bundesliga, Leverkusen is in the final of the Europa League and is considered by many to be the favorite to win the title. The final will be played between the German club and Atalanta.<br/><br/> As for Leverkusen's highlights this season, the best players were Grimaldo, Wirtz, Palacios, Xhaka, Kovar, Hofmann, and Boniface. What's important to note is that the players signed were highlights of the team during the season, which demonstrates a clear efficiency when it comes to using players.<br/><br/> <h2>Conclusion</h2> Xabi Alonso's management has transformed Leverkusen into a highly competitive team, reflected by the unprecedented Bundesliga title win and the Europa League final. The reduction and qualification of the squad, with strategic signings and the valorization of the players already in the squad, significantly increased the team's market value. With an efficient style of play, Leverkusen not only improved their performance on the pitch, but also highlighted the ability of their players, such as Wirtz, Palacios, and new signings Xhaka, Grimaldo, Kovar, and Boniface, consolidating themselves as one of the strongest teams of the season.<br/><br/> Stay tuned to our social networks, as next week we'll be posting our final analysis of Xabi Alonso's brilliant season.<br/><br/> </div>]]></content><author><name>Ace Laboratory Football Team - Hugo Antunes</name></author><category term="Football;"/><category term="Analysis"/><category term="Football;"/><category term="Bundesliga;"/><category term="Analysis"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Se quiser ler este texto em pt-br, clique aqui.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">In-Depth Analysis of Bayer Leverkusen - Xabi Alonso’s Playing Style</title><link href="https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2024/post_leverkusen_1_en/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="In-Depth Analysis of Bayer Leverkusen - Xabi Alonso’s Playing Style"/><published>2024-05-20T10:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-05-20T10:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2024/post_leverkusen_1_en</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2024/post_leverkusen_1_en/"><![CDATA[<hr/> <p align="justify"> Se quiser ler este texto em pt-br, <a href="https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2000/post_leverkusen_1_pt/"> clique aqui.</a> </p> <h2>Introduction</h2> <div style="text-align: justify"> <div style="width: 90%; margin: 0 auto; text-align: center;"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2024-05-20-post_leverkusen_1/last_minute.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> There’s been one unbeaten team in all competitions for exactly one year, since May 2023. Champions of their national league, finalists in their country’s cup and in the UEFA competition. In moments when it seems like this team is finally going to lose, they come back with an unshakeable determination, score goals in added time and maintain their unbeaten streak and sequence in championships. How did a team that hadn't attracted attention in soccer for a few years manage to become a top power in European soccer, with the longest unbeaten streak in history? In this series of posts, ACE Laboratory will analyze and identify the playing style of Bayer Leverkusen and their coach Xabi Alonso, aiming to uncover the reasons behind the magnificent run the team has done in 2024.<br/><br/> <h2>What is Xabi Alonso’s playing style?</h2> Xabi Alonso, a former player who has won every possible title and is known for being extremely technical and analytical, worked with gigantic teams and excellent coaches like Mourinho, Guardiola, and Ancelotti. Each with their different styles, Xabi managed to absorb the best qualities from each, becoming a great communicator, strategist, and football enthusiast. After completing the UEFA course, he started in Real Madrid's U-14 team and soon moved to Real Sociedad B. There, technical skills and ball control were the focus, and the club was promoted to the second division for the first time in 60 years. From there, Bayer Leverkusen saw in Xabi someone who could save the team from the critical situation of relegation, and history began to be made. But how does Bayer Leverkusen play now, having been led by Alonso for over a year?<br/><br/> <h3>Bayer Leverkusen without possession</h3> In the defensive sector, Alonso's team applies high pressure during the opponent's build-up in a mid-block, forcing errors to regain possession. Depending on the match, the German champion can adopt two different formations while defending: a 5-2-2-1, pressing the opponent's build-up with five players, crowding the midfield, and forcing plays to the sides of the field where the wing-backs press and win the ball; or a 4-2-3-1, which allows for an easier transition out of defense after stealing the ball.<br/><br/> Additionally, Leverkusen employs counter-pressing, commonly known as Gegenpressing. Xabi needed only a few months to shape and solidify this defensive tactic, establishing one of the most robust defenses in the league. By the end of the Bundesliga, they had achieved nearly 54 recoveries per match using this tactical approach.<br/><br/> <div style="width: 90%; margin: 0 auto; text-align: center;"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2024-05-20-post_leverkusen_1/recoveries.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> The team also conceded the fewest goals in the entire Bundesliga, allowing only 24 goals, proving the efficiency of their playing style.<br/><br/> <div style="width: 90%; margin: 0 auto; text-align: center;"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2024-05-20-post_leverkusen_1/Goals_Against.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <h3>Bayer Leverkusen with possession</h3> Classified as a middle ground between Pep Guardiola's positional play and the relational play seen in Fernando Diniz's Fluminense, Xabi Alonso trains the team for a build-up that depends on the current formation on the field. The playing style, which involves many passing exchanges, is evident in the team's passing network, where we can see the formation of "triangles" that allow multiple options for a player to work the ball.<br/><br/> <div style="width: 90%; margin: 0 auto; text-align: center;"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2024-05-20-post_leverkusen_1/passing_networks.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> Often, the wing-back Grimaldo operates defensively on the left, leaving two central defenders and a right-back to create space on the field and allow for "third man combinations." In these combinations, two players (usually Xhaka and Palacios) quickly pass the ball between themselves to draw defenders, creating space for a third player (usually Wirtz) to receive the ball. This tactic is characteristic of the relational play style.<br/><br/> In that way, the wing-backs have a much more significant role in the game, both offensively and defensively, switching sides of the field while attacking and defending. This can be observed in the passing network from the match against Augsburg, where wing-back Frimpong appeared more advanced than any other Bayer player.<br/><br/> By employing this tactic, Xabi Alonso has maximized the individual technical skills of his wide players, such as Frimpong and Grimaldo, who have contributed to 39 goals in the Bundesliga. In other words, nearly half of the team's goals have come through these two players.<br/><br/> <div style="width: 90%; margin: 0 auto; text-align: center;"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2024-05-20-post_leverkusen_1/augsburg.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> The use of this tactic is evidenced by the number of passes made by Bayer, the highest in the Bundesliga in the 2023-24 season. Additionally, the four advanced players move a lot, preventing the opposing defenders from pushing up their defensive line.<br/><br/> <div style="width: 90%; margin: 0 auto; text-align: center;"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2024-05-20-post_leverkusen_1/Passes_per_match.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> However, it is also common to see the team building up play with three defenders, utilizing the flanks with advanced wing-backs (usually Grimaldo and Frimpong), midfielders and forwards giving closer non-positional options, through midfield with quick transitions to attack generally architected by Wirtz or with direct passes from the defense to the attack into the empty spaces created by the team’s movementation. This is exemplified by the high number of progressive passes per game.<br/><br/> <div style="width: 90%; margin: 0 auto; text-align: center;"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2024-05-20-post_leverkusen_1/progressive_passes.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> If the opponents remain too rigid centrally, the team starts forming narrow diamond patterns, allowing Bayer to continue doing their short and dynamic passes to reach the final third of the field. Another possibility is that if the opponents press Leverkusen's short passing exchanges, the ball is moved to the opposite flank, which will have plenty of free space.<br/><br/> Moreover, the German team doesn't rely solely on movement and masterful passing to score goals this season, since approximately 10% of all goals scored by Xabi Alonso's team have come from set-pieces. Additionally, goals from counter-attacks are also common for the German side when necessary.<br/><br/> <div style="width: 90%; margin: 0 auto; text-align: center;"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2024-05-20-post_leverkusen_1/dead_balls.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <h3>Final third of the field</h3> The final third of the German team's attack is almost unpredictable. The advance of the wing-backs through the flanks mixed with midfielders infiltrating the box, along with a bit of accurate long-range shooting, create Xabi Alonso's magical formula for the team's incredible effectiveness. Thus, a statistic that demonstrates the unpredictability of the team led by the Spanish maestro is the percentage of attacks from each offensive third of the field, with the left, middle, and right accounting for 33%, 34%, and 33% respectively.<br/><br/> Such offensive prowess not only leads to a flurry of goals and chances created for the German team but also contributes to the team's unbeaten streak, which, when being behind on the scoreboard, always finds a way, often through the tactics taught by Xabi Alonso, combined with a bit of luck, to score goals and maintain their unbeaten record intact for all season.<br/><br/> <div style="width: 90%; margin: 0 auto; text-align: center;"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2024-05-20-post_leverkusen_1/Goal_Creating_Actions.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> A common tactic is as follows: when reaching the final third of the field, the wing-backs advance and the team's formation shifts to a 3-2-5, with the central players pushing up to receive the ball and create more options for playmaking, thus creating a numerical advantage that makes the team unpredictable and overwhelms the opposing defense. During this advancement, other players move up to occupy the midfield. The team is so efficient that it ranks in the top 3 in chances created from open play, but in comparison, has few chances from set-pieces.<br/><br/> <div style="width: 90%; margin: 0 auto; text-align: center;"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2024-05-20-post_leverkusen_1/live_dead_balls.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <h3>Weakness</h3> Due to the relational play, if the team loses the ball in the attacking side and fails apply quick pressure, the opponent has a lot of space on the flanks of the field (where the full-backs should be), since the players concentrate in a compressed manner for effective passing combinations and triangles. However, if the midfielders in transition cover the flanks, the central area becomes weakened and opportunities arise for the opponent. The system relies entirely on the players' perfection and minimizing errors. An example of this was observed in the away game against Qarabag in the UEFA Europa League, where both goals conceded were due to possession losses and effective counter-attacks by the Azerbaijani team.<br/><br/> <div style="width: 90%; margin: 0 auto; text-align: center;"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2024-05-20-post_leverkusen_1/possession_lost.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> But, as we can see by the team’s results in the season and their goal difference stats, the risk is worth taking. <br/><br/> <div style="width: 90%; margin: 0 auto; text-align: center;"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2024-05-20-post_leverkusen_1/Goal_Difference.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <h2>Conclusion</h2> It is evident that Xabi Alonso has blended various influences and added his own product to create a team capable of an unbeaten performance in the Bundesliga. However, one of the key aspects of this team is the individuality of each player, who has fit into the Spanish coach's system while incorporating their own unique playing styles. When facing Xabi Alonso in tactical chess, one doesn't see his pieces as knights, towers, or pawns, but rather as twenty-four players with different characteristics that change the German team's playing style. These players are the reason behind the team's immense success this season and the singularity of this squad that has captivated the world. In the next post, we will analyze the evolution of these players and the team, leading to what is now known as the first team to win the first unbeaten Bundesliga title. </div>]]></content><author><name>Ace Laboratory Football Team - Caio Santos e Lucas Calmon</name></author><category term="Football;"/><category term="Analysis"/><category term="Football;"/><category term="Bundesliga;"/><category term="Analysis"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Se quiser ler este texto em pt-br, clique aqui.]]></summary></entry></feed>