<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.4.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://ac3lab.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://ac3lab.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2025-07-04T01:04:34+00:00</updated><id>https://ac3lab.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">blank</title><subtitle>Marrying academic rigor with practical applications to benefit sports </subtitle><entry><title type="html">Palmeiras vs Botafogo: A Tactical Battle in the Club World Cup Round of 16</title><link href="https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2025/botafogo_palmeiras_en/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Palmeiras vs Botafogo: A Tactical Battle in the Club World Cup Round of 16"/><published>2025-07-02T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-07-02T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2025/botafogo_palmeiras_en</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2025/botafogo_palmeiras_en/"><![CDATA[<hr/> <p align="justify"> Se quiser ler este texto em português, <a href="https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2000/botafogo_palmeiras_pt/"> clique aqui.</a> </p> <h2> <b> Introduction </b></h2> <div style="text-align: justify"> The clash between Brazilian clubs Botafogo and Palmeiras extended their growing rivalry onto the international stage, as they met once again in the Round of 16 of the 2025 FIFA Club World Cup. The two sides previously faced off in the 2024 Copa Libertadores Round of 16 and battled for the title in the Brasileirão Série A — with Botafogo emerging victorious in both competitions. <br/><br/> In the Club World Cup group stage, Palmeiras topped Group A with one win and two draws. Botafogo finished second in Group B, recording two victories — including an impressive win over UEFA Champions League winners PSG — and one loss. <br/><br/> Despite Botafogo's recent dominance in the head-to-head record — three wins and two draws in their last five meetings — Palmeiras entered the knockout stage as slight favorites. According to Opta Analyst, Palmeiras had a 52.4% chance of winning in regular time, compared to 23.8% for Botafogo, with the probability of a draw also at 23.8%. The overall chances of advancing to the quarterfinals were more balanced: 55.6% for Palmeiras and 44.4% for Botafogo. <br/><br/> In the end, Palmeiras secured a 1–0 win in the Round of 16 match, with substitute Paulinho scoring the decisive goal in the first half of extra time. <br/><br/> Tactically, Botafogo stuck with the 4-3-3 formation that was used against PSG and Atlético de Madrid, with Danilo Barbosa stepping in for the suspended Gregore. Palmeiras deployed a 4-2-3-1 system and made several notable changes to their starting lineup. Academy product Allan started on the right wing, while rising star Estevão featured on the left. In defense, Bruno Fuchs replaced the injured Murilo, and Maurício took over for Veiga in midfield. <br/><br/> <h3> <b> Match Summary </b></h3> The first half ended with a clear offensive advantage for the São Paulo team. By the 30-minute mark, the Rio de Janeiro side had yet to attempt a single shot, while their opponents had already registered five. By halftime, the São Paulo club had taken seven shots with an expected goals (xG) value of 0.51, compared to just two shots and 0.07 xG for Botafogo. Despite this disparity, possession remained fairly balanced — 51% for Palmeiras and 49% for Botafogo. However, none of the nine total shots hit the target, highlighting the lack of efficiency from both sides in front of goal. <br/><br/> In the second half, possession remained nearly even — 52% for Botafogo and 48% for Palmeiras — but the São Paulo team continued to threaten more consistently. They registered nine shots to the opponent's two, including three on target versus just one. The xG numbers reflected this attacking edge: 0.64 to just 0.06. Goalkeeper John stood out in this period, making three crucial saves to keep Botafogo in the game. Another stat that underscored Palmeiras' dominance was corner kicks: they took 13 in regular time, compared to just two for Botafogo. <br/><br/> With the match still goalless after 90 minutes, extra time began at a high tempo. Substitutions brought new energy to the field — most notably Paulinho, who scored the decisive goal in the first half of extra time. During those 15 minutes, Palmeiras stayed on the front foot, producing two shots on target and converting one. <br/><br/> In the second half of extra time, already ahead, Palmeiras adopted a more defensive posture, particularly after replacing forward Paulinho with center-back Micael. They had only 26% possession in that stretch, focusing on protecting the lead. Meanwhile, Botafogo pushed forward aggressively. In those final 15 minutes alone, the Rio side recorded 10 shots — more than in the entire 90 minutes plus the first extra-time period combined. That final stretch generated 0.75 xG, accounting for 68.2% of their total expected goals for the entire match. <br/><br/> After 120 minutes, Palmeiras secured their place in the quarterfinals with a stronger overall performance: 19 total shots, five on target, 47% possession, and approximately 83% passing accuracy. <br/><br/> A standout performer for Palmeiras was Richard Ríos, who delivered a high-quality display over the full 120 minutes to help secure the win. He provided an assist and led his team in tackles (4), duels won (10), and distance covered (13,4 km). His performance was well-rounded, contributing both offensively and defensively, and he played a key role in the team's success. <br/><br/> The image below shows the attacking momentum of the match, highlighting Palmeiras' superiority, with most of the opportunities and greater attacking efficiency, despite the overall statistical balance in the game. It also shows Botafogo dominating the second half of extra time, with 10 attempts compared to none from the team from São Paulo. <br/><br/> <div class="row"> <div class="col-sm-10 offset-sm-1 mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2025-06-26-post_world_cup/oitavas/pressure_map.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" title="Attacking momentum of the match" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <center>Attacking momentum of the match between Palmeiras and Botafogo. <br/><br/></center> <h3> <b> Tactical Analysis </b></h3> In addition to repeating the same formation used against the European sides (PSG and Atlético de Madrid), Botafogo also stuck to the same strategy: applying pressure in their own defensive half and relying on counterattacks. <br/><br/> When in possession — and not attacking in transition — head coach Renato Paiva's approach was clear: the wingers, Artur and Savarino, moved into central areas to create space for overlapping full-backs Vitinho and Alex Telles, while Igor Jesus stayed as the central reference up front. This dynamic can be seen in the image below. <br/><br/> <div class="row"> <div class="col-sm-10 offset-sm-1 mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2025-06-26-post_world_cup/oitavas/formation1.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" title="Botafogo's tactical formation" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <center>Botafogo's tactical formation and movement patterns. <br/><br/></center> Although he had been performing well in the tournament, forward Savarino stood out for the wrong reasons in this match. He completed only 75% of his passes, lost all 5 duels he contested, and gave away possession 10 times out of 27 touches. <br/><br/> Additionally, Botafogo focused more of their attacks down the right flank. Vitinho and Artur were the players with the most passing offers, with 74 and 60 respectively. The team's passing map helps illustrate this scenario. <br/><br/> <div class="row"> <div class="col-sm-6 offset-sm-3 mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2025-06-26-post_world_cup/oitavas/passing_map_botafogo.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" title="Botafogo's passing network" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <center>Botafogo's passing network against Palmeiras. <br/><br/></center> Palmeiras set up in a 4-2-3-1 formation but employed an intelligent defensive tactic by shifting into a 5-4-1 variation, as shown in the image below. This adjustment proved highly effective against Botafogo's attack — particularly since, as mentioned earlier, the team focused heavily on attacking down the flanks. The compact defensive shape effectively neutralized those wide advances. <br/><br/> <div class="row"> <div class="col-sm-10 offset-sm-1 mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2025-06-26-post_world_cup/oitavas/formation2.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" title="Palmeiras' defensive formation" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <center>Palmeiras' defensive formation and tactical adjustments. <br/><br/></center> Palmeiras' exceptional defensive performance is evidenced by Igor Jesus' high offensive movement — 29 runs in behind — yet without any effective finishing. Palmeiras' PPDA (passes per defensive action) reflects a low-block defense, with lower values closer to the box, as shown in the image below: the more red, the lower the index (in other words, more pressure), and the more blue, the higher the index and lower the pressure. <br/><br/> <div class="row"> <div class="col-sm-10 offset-sm-1 mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2025-06-26-post_world_cup/oitavas/ppda_palmeiras.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" title="Palmeiras' PPDA by zone" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <center>Palmeiras' PPDA by zone against Botafogo. <br/><br/></center> One of the key positive defensive standouts was left-back Joaquín Piquerez, who played a vital role in executing this system. In addition to maintaining strong positioning and discipline on his side of the field, Piquerez led the team in defensive actions (10) and clearances (5), showing great awareness and composure throughout the match. His contribution was crucial in absorbing the pressure during Botafogo's most aggressive phases and helped Palmeiras maintain their structure even as the match became more intense. <br/><br/> <h2> <b> Conclusion </b></h2> The match between Palmeiras and Botafogo showcased not only the intensity of a growing rivalry but also the tactical maturity and adaptability of both teams. While Botafogo stayed true to its counterattacking identity and maintained structural consistency throughout the tournament, Palmeiras demonstrated greater flexibility — both in formation and in in-game adjustments — which ultimately made the difference. <br/><br/> Statistically and tactically, Palmeiras managed to control key areas of the pitch, especially in defense, where their shape and discipline effectively neutralized Botafogo's strengths. The transition from a 4-2-3-1 to a 5-4-1 in defensive phases proved decisive, as did individual performances like that of Joaquín Piquerez and Richard Ríos, who embodied the balance between defensive solidity and offensive support. <br/><br/> In a match defined by fine margins and intense strategic battles, Palmeiras' ability to adapt and capitalize on moments of opportunity, such as the goal in extra time, underlined the team's competitive edge — not just in terms of talent, but in execution and game management. The result was not only a deserved qualification but also a performance that reflects the evolution of Brazilian clubs on the international stage. <br/><br/> Having secured a spot in the quarterfinals, Palmeiras now faces a high-stakes encounter with Chelsea — the same opponent they battled in the 2022 Club World Cup final. The matchup not only revives recent history but also adds another chapter to Palmeiras' pursuit of the long-awaited dream of eternal glory on the world stage. <br/><br/> </div>]]></content><author><name>Ace Laboratory Team - Brenno Santos, Antonio Magalhães</name></author><category term="Football;"/><category term="Analysis"/><category term="Football;"/><category term="Analysis;"/><category term="Club"/><category term="World"/><category term="Cup"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A thrilling tactical showdown between Brazilian giants Palmeiras and Botafogo in the Club World Cup Round of 16, featuring intense extra-time drama and strategic masterclass]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Flamengo vs Bayern: An Analysis of Errors and Tactical Differences</title><link href="https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2025/flamengo_bayern_en/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Flamengo vs Bayern: An Analysis of Errors and Tactical Differences"/><published>2025-07-02T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-07-02T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2025/flamengo_bayern_en</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2025/flamengo_bayern_en/"><![CDATA[<hr/> <p align="justify"> Se quiser ler a versão em português, <a href="https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2000/flamengo_bayern_pt/"> clique aqui.</a> </p> <h2> <b> Introduction </b></h2> <div style="text-align: justify"> This past Sunday, 06/29, Flamengo and Bayern Munich faced off in a match between the cream of what South American football can offer (and possibly the best team on the continent) against a team from the highest tier of European football (which wasn't the best of the last season) in a game marked by several things, but mainly by the number of errors on the part of the Rio team that led to the Bavarian team's goals, which raises the question: were these failures just demerits of the red-and-black team? <br/><br/> <h3> <b> Match Summary </b></h3> Even before the ball rolled, there was already a debate about the lineup made by Filipe Luís, for including Arrascaeta, the team's top scorer of the season, but who doesn't usually impose as much physical vigor when marking pressure or when serving as a speed escape valve for the attack, roles that would be better performed by another athlete, such as Bruno Henrique, the striker who came on in place of the Uruguayan in the group stage match against Chelsea and changed the course of the match. However, whatever the Brazilian coach's thinking was, it was completely influenced by what happened in the early minutes of the game. <br/><br/> The pace of the game, the strategy, and the level of pressure that would be felt throughout the 90 minutes were severely influenced when at 3 minutes and 45 seconds, the Argentine goalkeeper Rossi kicked a ball at Pulgar, which ended up resulting in a corner kick (by the referee's understanding) that generated a second one, from which came the first goal of the match, an own goal. This change in the score so quickly would already be enough to change the entire match planning, but the blitz imposed by Bayern was still in full force when the French defender Upamecano came up from the German defensive line to contest a pass received by Arrascaeta, which succeeded in Harry Kane's fatal finish, extending the score. <br/><br/> After this disastrous sequence of events, the Rio team managed to have more possession and try to put their game idea into practice, leading to their first goal play, resulting from a deflected cross into the penalty area with a Gerson finish, which made the Bavarian imposition return with full force. <br/><br/> <div class="row"> <div class="col-sm-10 offset-sm-1 mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2025-06-26-post_world_cup/oitavas/fla_bayern.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" title="Momento ofensivo da partida" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <center>Offensive moment of the match between Flamengo and Bayern. <br/><br/></center> As we can observe in the attacking third actions chart, this pattern repeated itself in the interval between the third and fourth goals of the Europeans, giving the impression that the German team "took their foot off" after making the result more comfortable, leaving more possession and space for the Brazilian team to work the plays, which resulted in a second goal after the Uruguayan midfielder's cross hit Olise's open hand inside the area, generating a penalty converted with precision by Jorginho. This pattern repeated itself after this reduction in the score advantage, with the pace being imposed by Bayern and with pressure on a ball exit where Luiz Araújo tried to dribble near the defensive penalty area, turning into a precise shot from the English striker. <br/><br/> This norm in the game dynamics can help explain the fact that at the end of the match some data showed a Flamengo equivalent or superior to Bayern (such as a minimal advantage in possession, a greater number of shots, xG), although the Rio team was not very close to equalizing the score (the closest chance came from an Arrascaeta header at 6 minutes of play), the eye test points to the contrary, a Bayern that dictated the pace when the advantage decreased and that didn't take as many risks. <br/><br/> <h3> <b> Tactical Analysis </b></h3> Regarding the question of errors, forced or not, they can be contextualized, in part, by the difference in quality between the two teams in various aspects, but mainly in the effectiveness of pressure and efficiency in punishing the opposing team's errors, and one of the justifications for these issues can be, besides the quality of the players on the field, due to the history of German teams having this historical habit of pressing high, after all, gegenpressing comes from there. <br/><br/> The concept of marking by pressing in attack is not something that was created recently, but this style of football, especially in the context of German football, is attributed to German coach Ralf Rangnick, who influenced modern generations of German coaches, such as Jurgen Klopp, Thomas Tuchel, and Julian Nagelsmann. Additionally, the German league is known for the high level of athleticism imposed by the players, fundamental factors for teams like Klopp's Borussia or Hansi Flick's Bayern Munich to establish their game plans brutally, having vigor to move up the marking line, attack spaces quickly, etc. <br/><br/> This very high-pressure football, combined with the high marking line, has been in the club's DNA for a long time, and besides being very well refined by recent coaches, such as Nagelsmann and Hansi Flick, they are put into practice by Kompany, the current coach, while the ephemerality of Brazilian coaches' work combined with the lack of conviction in fixed game styles for clubs, makes it difficult for the work to be much refined here, and for there to be an exploited sequence even with coach changes. <br/><br/> <h2> <b> Conclusion </b></h2> In the end, the Brazilian team did what they could, especially given the circumstances, and lost in a dignified manner, and although they were far from making a head-to-head match, it doesn't mean that the defeat was a disgrace or something of the sort, and this defeat cannot shake the structures of both the squad and the entire football department because the season is only at its halfway point, with the most decisive matches for national competitions and the Copa Libertadores very close. <br/><br/> The match between Flamengo and Bayern demonstrated not only the technical difference between the teams, but also the importance of tactical consistency and efficient pressure in modern football. While Bayern showed its tradition of high pressure and finishing efficiency, Flamengo revealed fragilities that need to be worked on to compete at the highest international level. <br/><br/> The defeat, although heavy on the scoreboard, serves as valuable learning for the development of Brazilian football, showing that tactical evolution and methodological consistency are fundamental for success in the international scenario. <br/><br/> </div>]]></content><author><name>Ace Laboratory Team - João Victor Gadelha</name></author><category term="Football;"/><category term="Analysis"/><category term="Football;"/><category term="Analysis;"/><category term="Club"/><category term="World"/><category term="Cup"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[How Flamengo's errors and Bayern's pressure defined the result in the Club World Cup Round of 16]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Fluminense vs Inter: A Victory that Surprised Everyone</title><link href="https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2025/fluminense_inter_en/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Fluminense vs Inter: A Victory that Surprised Everyone"/><published>2025-07-02T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-07-02T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2025/fluminense_inter_en</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2025/fluminense_inter_en/"><![CDATA[<hr/> <p align="justify"> Se quiser ler este texto em português, <a href="https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2000/fluminense_inter_pt/"> clique aqui.</a> </p> <h2> <b> Introduction </b></h2> <div style="text-align: justify"> In our last post about Fluminense after the group stage, we stated: "the Flu had both defensive failures and wasted goal opportunities, which should be crucial points for improvement in the next game". In this knockout match against Inter Milan, it seems the tricolor understood the message. <br/><br/> Renato Gaúcho bet on a different formation, with a 3-5-2. In the first minute of the match, Fluminense's high pressing was already causing discomfort for goalkeeper Sommer, who shares a ball with Germán Cano. A few minutes later, after a series of passes, Fluminense overloaded Inter with four players inside the penalty area, setting up a cross for Cano, who, free, becomes lethal again and scores the first goal of the match, putting Fluminense in an excellent position. <br/><br/> <h3> <b> Match Summary </b></h3> After the goal, Fluminense didn't panic. The Italian team kept the ball at their feet, ending the first half with 66% possession, but without causing major problems for the tricolor, who intercepted their shots very well, both in defense and in goalkeeper Fábio's hands. Additionally, Renato's team was the one that came closest to the second goal still in the first half, with a wasted chance from Samuel Xavier after an impressive play by Arias. This play, along with Ignácio's disallowed goal, demonstrates that, despite having less possession, Fluminense definitely didn't back down from the game. <br/><br/> Accumulating only half the number of passes from Inter at the end of the first half (126 to 250), it was the Rio team that showed more sharpness, ending the first half with 5 shots against Inter's 5. Dimarco, who wears number 32, was responsible for three of them. See the possession from Inter's passing network: <br/><br/> <div class="row"> <div class="col-sm-6 offset-sm-3 mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2025-06-26-post_world_cup/oitavas/rede_inter.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" title="Inter's passing network" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <center>Inter Milan's passing network against Fluminense. <br/><br/></center> In the second half, Fluminense continued in this style — Renato, in fact, ended the game with a substitution to spare. Inter, however, showed they wanted the game, making changes that had an effect: from the 60th minute onwards, the team brought much danger to Fluminense, shooting an incredible 10 times. The tricolor fan certainly held their breath seeing the three great chances created by Inter, one wasted by de Vrij, another from Lautaro that stopped in Fábio, and one more from Lautaro in the same minute that hit the post. These three shots alone add up to 0.52 xG. <br/><br/> Who closed the tricolor's house was the match's star, Ignácio, who won 10 of the 15 duels he contested. This pressure suffered can be observed from Fluminense's PPDA (Passes per Defensive Action) chart: <br/><br/> <div class="row"> <div class="col-sm-10 offset-sm-1 mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2025-06-26-post_world_cup/oitavas/ppda_flu.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" title="Fluminense's PPDA" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <center>Fluminense's PPDA by zone against Inter. <br/><br/></center> <h3> <b> Tactical Analysis </b></h3> Renato Gaúcho's tactical change to 3-5-2 was fundamental for Fluminense's success. This formation allowed greater control of the midfield and better defensive coverage, especially against Inter's technical quality. <br/><br/> Fluminense's defensive system worked exceptionally well, with the three defenders providing extra security and the full-backs offering offensive width when necessary. The high pressing at the beginning of the match caught Inter by surprise and resulted in Cano's early goal. <br/><br/> Ignácio's performance was particularly notable. The player not only won most of the duels but was also crucial in defensive organization and offensive transition. His versatility allowed Fluminense to maintain tactical structure even under intense pressure from Inter in the second half. <br/><br/> <h2> <b> Conclusion </b></h2> However, qualification was destined for the Warriors team, who killed the game at Hércules' feet in stoppage time, to confirm an extremely conscious and deserved victory. <br/><br/> Fluminense demonstrated significant tactical evolution compared to previous games. The change to 3-5-2, combined with a more aggressive approach at the beginning of the match, was fundamental to neutralizing Inter's quality. The team showed maturity in managing the result, even under intense pressure in the second half. <br/><br/> After this victory, fans may have been excited about the possibility of revenge against Manchester City. However, the Club World Cup has shown that it never tires of surprising, and Fluminense now has a match scheduled against Al-Hilal for Friday, which will very likely be their biggest challenge so far. <br/><br/> The performance against Inter demonstrates that Fluminense is growing in the tournament and could be a surprise in the next phases. The combination of defensive solidity, offensive efficiency, and tactical adaptability makes the tricolor a fearsome opponent for any team. <br/><br/> </div>]]></content><author><name>Ace Laboratory Team</name></author><category term="Football;"/><category term="Analysis"/><category term="Football;"/><category term="Analysis;"/><category term="Club"/><category term="World"/><category term="Cup"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[How Renato Gaúcho surprised Inter with tactical change and Fluminense secured qualification in the Round of 16]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Botafogo’s Surprising Club World Cup Group Stage Performance</title><link href="https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2025/botafogo_grupos_en/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Botafogo’s Surprising Club World Cup Group Stage Performance"/><published>2025-06-26T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-06-26T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2025/botafogo_grupos_en</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2025/botafogo_grupos_en/"><![CDATA[<hr/> <p align="justify"> Se quiser ler este texto em pt-br, <a href="https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2000/botafogo_grupos_pt/"> clique aqui.</a> </p> <h2> <b> Introduction </b></h2> <div style="text-align: justify"> Botafogo, current Copa Libertadores champion and eighth in the Brazilian league, came into the tournament on a three-game winning streak and kept most of the continental title-winning squad, despite the departures of Luiz Henrique, Thiago Almada, and soon, Igor Jesus. To strengthen the roster, the club signed forwards Arthur Cabral, Joaquín Correa, and the young Argentine prospect Álvaro Montoro. <br/><br/> The Rio de Janeiro's club ended up in the group considered one of the toughest, with two European giants, including the Champions League winner, Paris Saint-Germain — the Spanish powerhouse Atlético Madrid, and a strong American side, the Seattle Sounders, and still managed to finish in second place, with two wins and one loss. <br/><br/> <h3> <b> Game 1: Botafogo vs Seattle Sounders </b></h3> Botafogo defeated Seattle Sounders 2–1 in the opening round of the Club World Cup, in a match characterized by two very different halves: a dominant first half from the Brazilian side, and a second half largely controlled by the Americans. <br/><br/> Botafogo started in a 4-4-2 formation, with Igor Jesus and Mastriani up front. Savarino and Barboza returned to the starting lineup after missing the previous match. <br/><br/> Despite having 55% possession in the first half, Seattle failed to register a single shot on target. Botafogo, playing more directly, had seven shots — four on target — and scored twice, both from aerial plays. The first came from a Jair header after a free-kick delivered by Alex Telles; the second was a headed goal by Igor Jesus following a cross from right-back Vitinho. The Sounders struggled defensively in the air, winning only 36% of their aerial duels in the opening half. <br/><br/> In the second half, Seattle couldn't make it count: they had 19 shots but only 5 on target — a 26% accuracy rate. The team exchanged more passes, occupied the attacking third, and applied pressure, but were undone by poor finishing and John's saves. <br/><br/> The shift in Botafogo's defensive strategy between the two halves can be illustrated using PPDA (Passes Allowed per Defensive Action) charts. This metric is calculated by dividing the number of passes the opponent makes by the number of defensive actions (interceptions, tackles, duels, and fouls) by the analyzing team. Lower PPDA values indicate higher pressing intensity. The image below shows Botafogo's PPDA by zone in the first half. <br/><br/> <div class="row"> <div class="col-sm-6 offset-sm-3 mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2025-06-26-post_world_cup/fase_de_grupos/PPDA_Firsthalf_BOTvsSEA.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" title="Botafogo's PPDA by zone in the first half against Seattle Sounders" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <center>Botafogo's PPDA by zone in the first half against Seattle Sounders. <br/><br/></center> In the first half, Botafogo mainly pressed in the zone just beyond midfield, without applying intense high pressing near the opponent's goal but showing reasonable pressure in advanced areas. <br/><br/> In the second half, as the PPDA zone chart shows, the team clearly dropped deeper, defending mostly in their own half. This strategic shift aimed to draw Seattle forward and explore counterattacking opportunities. The image below shows Botafogo's PPDA by zone in the second half. <br/><br/> <div class="row"> <div class="col-sm-6 offset-sm-3 mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2025-06-26-post_world_cup/fase_de_grupos/PPDA_SecondHalf_BOTvsSEA.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" title="Botafogo's PPDA by zone in the second half against Seattle Sounders" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <center>Botafogo's PPDA by zone in the second half against Seattle Sounders. <br/><br/></center> Offensively, Botafogo relied heavily on full-backs Alex Telles and Vitinho, who played a key role in creating chances. Both displayed strong technical ability and were involved in most of the team's attacks — 9 of the 12 Botafogo shots featured contributions from one of them. <br/><br/> <div class="row"> <div class="col-sm-6 offset-sm-3 mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2025-06-26-post_world_cup/fase_de_grupos/Rededepasses_BOTvsSEA.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" title="Botafogo's PPDA by zone in the second half against Seattle Sounders" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <center>Botafogo's pass network against Seattle Sounders. <br/><br/></center> <h3> <b> Game 2: Botafogo vs Paris Saint-Germain </b></h3> Botafogo, despite having less than a 15% chance of winning according to Opta Analyst, defeated the reigning Champions League champions 1-0 in a thrilling match. <br/><br/> The Rio club only made one change to the starting eleven that faced the Sounders in the tournament opener. Striker Mastriani was replaced by midfielder Allan. Coach Renato Paiva opted to strengthen the midfield, given that they were up against a very strong opponent in that area. Paiva chose a 4-3-3 formation instead of the 4-4-2 used in the opening game. <br/><br/> PSG's dominance of possession was evident from the very first minutes. By the 14th minute, the French side had already completed an impressive 146 passes compared to Botafogo's 17. That pattern continued for virtually the entire match — PSG controlled the ball while Botafogo relied on a reactive strategy focused on defensive organization and quick transitions. By the end of the game, the numbers reflected this imbalance — PSG finished with 68% possession, Botafogo with 24%, and 8% of the time with the ball in contention. Overall, PSG completed 706 of their 766 passes, while Botafogo completed 215 of their 278. The offensive disparity was also clear: the French team received 256 passes in the final third, compared to just 32 for the Rio side. <br/><br/> Despite having less possession and fewer attacking opportunities, Botafogo was decisive in its actions. The team's most effective attacks came down the right flank, the origin of all four of their crosses — all of which occurred before the 55th minute, when Portuguese left-back Nuno Mendes came on. His introduction shored up PSG's defense, as has been highlighted throughout the season for his strong performances. <br/><br/> One aspect that really stood out was the finishing accuracy. PSG attempted 16 shots during the game, but only two were on target. In contrast, Botafogo was extremely efficient: they took four shots and hit the target with everyone, demonstrating remarkable finishing. Offensively, striker Igor Jesus was decisive once again — with his only shot of the game, he scored the winning goal. <br/><br/> Botafogo adopted a more defensive posture, similar to the second half against the Seattle Sounders. However, this time their lines were much more compact and close together, allowing PSG very little space to penetrate. The image below shows Botafogo's defensive actions — on the left, forced turnovers and on the right, possession recoveries. <br/><br/> <div class="row"> <div class="col-sm-6 offset-sm-3 mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2025-06-26-post_world_cup/fase_de_grupos/Forced_turnovers_BOTvsPSG.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" title="Botafogo's defensive actions against PSG" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <center>Botafogo's defensive actions against PSG: forced turnovers (left) and possession recoveries (right). <br/><br/></center> It shows how Botafogo defended with a low block, recovering the ball predominantly in their own defensive half. <br/><br/> <h3> <b> Game 3: Botafogo vs Atletico Madrid </b></h3> Needing just a draw to take the lead in Group B, Botafogo put in an excellent defensive performance, which was absolutely necessary since Atlético Madrid went into the match knowing they had to win — especially given that if PSG also won, Atlético would have to do so by more than one goal to qualify. <br/><br/> Atlético Madrid had most of the possession, with 61% compared to Botafogo's 39%, completing 508 passes versus the Brazilian team's 303, with Botafogo making only 93 passes in the second half. Atlético's shot volume was also notable — they had 23 attempts but only 5 on target, a poor conversion rate that reflects Botafogo's incredibly solid defense. Even with Atlético's lack of finishing efficiency, they produced an impressive expected goals (xG) total of 3.03 but managed only one goal, underlining Madrid's attacking shortcomings. <br/><br/> Botafogo repeated the setup they had used against PSG — a 4-3-3 with very compact lines, relying on quick attacking transitions. It was also noticeable that Botafogo pressed mostly from their own half, with little high pressing; this is evident in the team's PPDA by zone. <br/><br/> <div class="row"> <div class="col-sm-6 offset-sm-3 mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2025-06-26-post_world_cup/fase_de_grupos/PPDA_BOTvsATL.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" title="Botafogo's PPDA by zone against Atlético Madrid" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <center>Botafogo's PPDA by zone against Atlético Madrid. <br/><br/></center> The image shows Botafogo's PPDA (passes per defensive action) across different areas of the pitch. The redder the zone, the lower the PPDA — in other words, the more intense the pressing. The bluer the zone, the less pressure the team applied. By analyzing the image, we can see that Botafogo's pressing was mostly concentrated in their own half, especially in the first quarter of the field. <br/><br/> <h2> <b> Conclusion </b></h2> To sum up Botafogo's group stage in one word, it would be <b>SURPRISING</b>. Botafogo ended up in one of the toughest groups at the Club World Cup and still managed to qualify, in second place, ahead of two of Europe's top teams, even beating the reigning Champions League winner. According to Opta Analyst, before the start of the Club World Cup, Botafogo had about a 70% chance of being eliminated in the group stage, which underlines the impressive tournament the team is having by securing this qualification. <br/><br/> Overall, Botafogo delivered an outstanding performance, both offensively and defensively. Going forward, the standout was Igor Jesus, who scored two of the team's three goals in the tournament so far. He made the most of the chances that came his way and was crucial to the Rio club's qualification. The player took only 6 shots in the competition, posting a conversion rate of around 33% — one of the highest in the tournament to date. <br/><br/> It's also important to highlight the team's defensive performance. Barboza and Jair played at an extremely high level, forcing opposing teams into very poor shot conversion rates. The three teams that faced Botafogo — Seattle (21.7%), Paris Saint-Germain (12.5%), and Atlético Madrid (20.8%) — all had low shooting accuracy, which speaks volumes about Botafogo's defensive solidity. <br/><br/> <div class="row"> <div class="col-sm-6 offset-sm-3 mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2025-06-26-post_world_cup/fase_de_grupos/Shot_accuracy.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" title="Botafogo's PPDA by zone against Atlético Madrid" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <center>Shot accuracy comparison between Botafogo and their opponents. <br/><br/></center> Botafogo had an outstanding group stage, with every player demonstrating exactly why they were crowned Libertadores champions in 2024 and showcasing the power and resilience of Brazilian football against Europe's elite. <br/><br/> The standout player for Botafogo in this group stage was Alexander Barboza. He was one of the key pillars behind their qualification, with only 2 dribbles completed against him across 3 matches, leading the team in tackles, interceptions, and clearances per game. <br/><br/> <div class="row"> <div class="col-sm-6 offset-sm-3 mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2025-06-26-post_world_cup/fase_de_grupos/Probabilities_GroupB.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" title="Botafogo's PPDA by zone against Atlético Madrid" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <center>Group B qualification probabilities before the tournament. <br/><br/></center> </div>]]></content><author><name>Ace Laboratory Football Team - Brenno Santos, Antonio Magalhães</name></author><category term="Football;"/><category term="Analysis"/><category term="Football;"/><category term="Analysis;"/><category term="Club"/><category term="World"/><category term="Cup"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Botafogo's Surprising Club World Cup Group Stage Performance]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Flamengo’s Dominant Group Stage Performance at the Club World Cup</title><link href="https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2025/flamengo_grupos_en/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Flamengo’s Dominant Group Stage Performance at the Club World Cup"/><published>2025-06-26T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-06-26T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2025/flamengo_grupos_en</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2025/flamengo_grupos_en/"><![CDATA[<hr/> <p align="justify"> Se quiser ler este texto em pt-br, <a href="https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2000/flamengo_grupos_pt/"> clique aqui.</a> </p> <h2> <b> Introduction </b></h2> <div style="text-align: justify"> Flamengo concluded the group stage in first place in Group D, with 7 points, securing early qualification already in the second round. Despite facing different scenarios and opponent strategies, Filipe Luís's team remained faithful to their dominant and pressing game model, even against a high-level opponent like Chelsea. Occasionally, the team had some variations, such as a 3-1-6 / 3-3-4, with one of the defensive midfielders dropping back to the defensive line, freeing both full-backs for attack. <br/><br/> Throughout the campaign, the red and black team not only remained unbeaten but was superior to all their opponents in crucial metrics: ball possession, completed passes, shots, tackles, and xG (Expected Goals). Even with player rotations, the offensive organization demonstrated a consistent pattern. To attack low blocks, the team transitioned from their 4-2-3-1 to a 3-2-5, with the left-back dropping back to form a line of three and the right-back advancing to provide width, supported by a double pivot in midfield. <br/><br/> <div class="row"> <div class="col-sm-6 offset-sm-3 mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2025-06-26-post_world_cup/fase_de_grupos/campinho.gif" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" title="example image" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> Flamengo's tactical changes. <br/><br/> </div> <h3> <b> Game 1: Flamengo 2-0 Espérance </b></h3> In their debut match at the Club World Cup, Flamengo defeated Espérance 2-0. The game was characterized by the tactical control and ball possession management of the Brazilian team, which knew how to impose their game model and neutralize the Tunisian opponent's strategy. <br/><br/> From the initial minutes, Flamengo's pressure forced the Tunisian team to abandon short build-up, opting for long balls. Defensively, Espérance congested the central corridor in a 4-3-3, but conceded the flanks. It was precisely through there that Flamengo dismantled the opponent's defense, with both goals in the match originating from crosses. The dominance translated into 69% ball possession and was quantified by pass network metrics: Flamengo showed higher density (0.4750 vs 0.4542), average degree of connections (14.25 vs 13.62), and clustering coefficient (0.1090 vs 0.0969). These numbers indicate a more connected team with a greater tendency for triangulations, which allowed for safe result management with a controlled number of 11 shots. <br/><br/> The analysis of this match's pass network established the importance of defenders and defensive midfielders as connectors. Léo Pereira (Defender) was the leader in pass volume (Weighted Degree: 206) and the main bridge between sectors, confirmed by the team's highest Betweenness Centrality (0.3857). Jorginho (Defensive Midfielder), second in volume (Weighted Degree: 179), was the key piece for triangulations, leading the team with the highest Clustering Coefficient (0.2200). Completing the axis, Erick Pulgar (Defensive Midfielder) acted as an efficient connector (Weighted Degree: 177; high Closeness Centrality: 0.7686), and Léo Ortiz (Defender) was a vital secondary link for defensive triangulations (Weighted Degree: 135; Clustering Coefficient: 0.1861). <br/><br/> <div class="row"> <div class="col-sm-7 offset-sm-3 mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2025-06-26-post_world_cup/fase_de_grupos/fla-esp.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" title="example image" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> Statistics of the Flamengo x Espérance match. <br/><br/> </div> <h3> <b> Game 2: Flamengo 3-1 Chelsea </b></h3> In their second game, Flamengo, with some changes in the lineup, defeated the English team 3-1, with direct participation of substitutions in the comeback goals. <br/><br/> The match had two distinct phases. In the first half, after conceding a goal in the 13th minute, Chelsea retreated. Flamengo dominated possession (63%) and passes (277 vs 162), but with difficulty creating clear chances, resulting in only 5 shots. The scenario changed in the second half. The red and black pressure became more effective, and with Bruno Henrique's entry, the team scored two goals in five minutes. After scoring the third goal in the 82nd minute, Flamengo inverted the strategy, conceded the ball to Chelsea, and began managing the score (61% possession and 244 passes for the English in the second half). The final statistics (possession 51% x 49%, passes 437 x 410) suggest a misleading balance that masks the distinct dominance phases. A clearer indicator of red and black superiority was the number of actions in the opponent's area: 27 vs 17. <br/><br/> The network analysis reinforced the importance of the defensive axis. Jorginho (Defensive Midfielder) was the most participative player (Weighted Degree: 113) and the key piece for triangulations, with the highest Clustering Coefficient (0.2236). Léo Pereira (Defender), with similar volume (Weighted Degree: 112), was the main authority in the network (highest PageRank: 0.1384). Defender Danilo (Weighted Degree: 100) quickly connected the sectors (highest Closeness Centrality: 0.7686), while Erick Pulgar (Weighted Degree: 91) acted as a bridge between defense and midfield (second highest Betweenness Centrality: 0.1298). For Chelsea, defender Trevoh Chalobah was the pillar, leading his team in volume (Weighted Degree: 105), closeness (0.8750), and betweenness (0.3434). <br/><br/> <div class="row"> <div class="col-sm-7 offset-sm-3 mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2025-06-26-post_world_cup/fase_de_grupos/fla-chel.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" title="example image" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> Statistics of the Flamengo x Chelsea match. <br/><br/> </div> <h3> <b> Game 3: Flamengo 1-1 LAFC </b></h3> In their third game, Flamengo, already qualified, drew 1-1 with LAFC in a more protocol match. Despite the heavily modified team, they demonstrated dominance against an LAFC parked in a 5-2-3. <br/><br/> The superiority was constant, reflected in overwhelming statistics: 66% ball possession, 19 to 5 in shots, 659 to 344 in passes, and 27 to 5 in actions in the opponent's area. Despite the volume, Flamengo was not effective, while LAFC converted their only great chance. The result was also strongly influenced by bad luck: there were five balls hitting the woodwork in the game (four from Flamengo). Modeling the group stage data (48 matches), the probability of such an event is only 0.12% (approximately 1 in 835), a rare case that evidences the exceptionality of what occurred. <br/><br/> The game model remained consistent even with an alternative team, with defenders and defensive midfielders being the team's hubs again. Jorginho (Defensive Midfielder) and Léo Pereira (Defender) repeated the previous game's performance, leading in pass volume with Weighted Degrees of 113 and 112, respectively, proving the system's strength. Danilo (Defender) also maintained high volume, with 100 passes. On LAFC's side, full-back Sergi Palencia was the main connector, leading his team in betweenness (0.5852), closeness (0.8750), and network authority (PageRank: 0.1427). <br/><br/> <div class="row"> <div class="col-sm-7 offset-sm-3 mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2025-06-26-post_world_cup/fase_de_grupos/fla-lafc.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" title="example image" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> Statistics of the Flamengo x Los Angeles FC match. <br/><br/> </div> <h2> <b> Conclusion </b></h2> Flamengo demonstrated a dominant and consistent performance throughout the entire group stage, maintaining their characteristic game model even in the face of different opponent strategies. The red and black team not only remained unbeaten but was also superior in all important metrics, consolidating their position as one of the tournament's main forces. <br/><br/> </div>]]></content><author><name>Ace Laboratory Football Team - Murilo Jorge</name></author><category term="Football;"/><category term="Analysis"/><category term="Football;"/><category term="Analysis;"/><category term="Club"/><category term="World"/><category term="Cup"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Flamengo's Dominant Group Stage Performance at the Club World Cup]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Fluminense’s Solid Group Stage Performance at the Club World Cup</title><link href="https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2025/fluminense_grupos_en/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Fluminense’s Solid Group Stage Performance at the Club World Cup"/><published>2025-06-26T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-06-26T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2025/fluminense_grupos_en</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2025/fluminense_grupos_en/"><![CDATA[<hr/> <p align="justify"> Se quiser ler este texto em pt-br, <a href="https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2000/fluminense_grupos_pt/"> clique aqui.</a> </p> <h2> <b> Introduction </b></h2> <div style="text-align: justify"> Fluminense, the Rio de Janeiro club managed by Renato Gaúcho, arrives at the World Cup at a very good moment for the club. A sequence of 6 unbeaten games for the Tricolor, which was put at risk in a group containing 3 giants from 3 different continents: Borussia Dortmund (Germany), Mamelodi Sundowns (South Africa), and Ulsan HD (South Korea). <br/><br/> <h3> <b> Game 1: Fluminense 0-0 Borussia Dortmund </b></h3> Fluminense's debut at the Club World Cup was marked by a surprising match against Borussia Dortmund. Against the main opponent in the group, Renato Gaúcho's team managed to impose their ideals for much of the game, coming dangerously close numerous times. So much so that Kobel, the German team's goalkeeper, was the best player of the match, with a rating of 8.2 (Sofascore). Despite the goalless draw and inferiority in ball possession, many considered the Brazilian team superior in the game. <br/><br/> Despite Borussia's superiority in ball possession in both parts of the game, few were the times they brought concrete danger to Fábio's goal. With the high volume of play through the wings, Fluminense managed to impose themselves through the flanks and propose play in the middle of the field, winning 67% of duels. The German team couldn't be efficient, despite managing to control the ball more (54% possession) and make more accurate passes (263). <br/><br/> In the second half, the intensity of both teams dropped, but Borussia managed to explore their ideal game a bit more. Their possession increased by 1% and the team began to win their offensive duels (55% duels won) and defensive duels (71% duels won), and this led goalkeeper Fábio to make 3 saves, the only ones of the game. Given the greater volume, this exposed the team to counterattacks — Fluminense's main chance came from a counterattack after a long pass from Hércules to Everaldo. <br/><br/> The game ended in a 0-0 draw, with 14 shots (5 on target) for Fluminense and 7 (3 on target) for Borussia. Despite inferior possession, the Tricolor demonstrated maturity to execute their offensive plays and overcome the German team's defense with their fast style of play and their speed transitions through the wings. <br/><br/> <h3> <b> Game 2: Fluminense 4-2 Ulsan HD </b></h3> Fluminense delivered a great performance against the current three-time South Korean champion, Ulsan HD. The 4-2 victory, despite some defensive lapses, was convincing. The Tricolor's game was characterized by the high positioning of players, exchanging relatively short passes in the midfield and opponent's area, resulting in an impressive 70% possession and 92% accurate passes by the end of the match. The game, however, was not without scares for Fluminense, who suffered a comeback at the end of the first half, leading Renato Gaúcho to make a bet on an even more offensive game with the exit of Ganso and the entry of Everaldo. The risk paid off, as the superiority of actions in the final third of the field yielded 3 goals and sealed Fluminense's victory. The great highlight of the match was Jhon Arias, who showed himself extremely present on both sides of the field, scoring a beautiful free-kick goal and providing an assist to Keno at the end of the game. <br/><br/> <div class="row"> <div class="col-sm-6 offset-sm-3 mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2025-06-26-post_world_cup/fase_de_grupos/network_passes_flu_ulsan.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" title="example image" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> Fluminense's pass network against Ulsan HD. <br/><br/> </div> <h3> <b> Game 3: Mamelodi Sundowns 0-0 Fluminense </b></h3> In the final round, the group was wide open. Any of the teams had a chance, even if small, to qualify. In a game where Fluminense only needed a draw and Mamelodi Sundowns needed a victory, the game demonstrated the importance it was for each team — the South African team managed to neutralize various offensive weapons of the Tricolor and was superior almost throughout the entire game (67% possession in the first half and 69% in the second). This 0-0 draw is largely due to the outstanding defensive performance of Fluminense's team, with about 67% of tackles won and 42 ball recoveries. It's also important to recognize the maturity and defensive organization of the South African team, as they managed to neutralize the main player of the Rio team: Jhon Arias. He had the lowest number of actions on the ball among the 3 games (57) and couldn't shoot on goal. Renato Gaúcho knew how to play with a tactic that invited the opponent forward and managed to extract the draw, securing qualification in second place in the group. <br/><br/> <h2> <b> Conclusion </b></h2> Fluminense's group stage was not easy. They played a surprising debut match, made big mistakes despite the convincing victory in the second match, and played an extremely dull final game. The predictions showed Fluminense as the third force in this group: 39.4% chance of advancing to the round of 16, behind Mamelodi Sundowns (47.1%) and Borussia Dortmund (74.9%) (Opta). Despite this, the team managed to qualify in a difficult group. The Flu had both defensive lapses and wasted goal opportunities, which should be crucial points for improvement in the next game. <br/><br/> Offensively, the lack of rhythm due to Germán Cano's recovery is notable, as the Argentine had 5 shots on goal and missed 3 chances. The striker was gaining rhythm throughout the 3 games, but it wasn't enough to see him at his best form, which is crucial for Fluminense. Still, Cano had only fewer shots than Jhon Arias (9), who was twice elected as the best player of the match by FIFA and obtained the best Sofascore rating in all group stage games. Defensively, the Rio team had lapses against Ulsan HD, but overall, had a good performance, with clean sheets in the other two games. The good performance of the Tricolor defense — with highlights for Freytes and Renê — resulted in few shots against Fluminense, especially in the game against Mamelodi Sundowns and Borussia Dortmund; in comparison, only Ulsan HD had fewer shots in the match against the German team. With a match scheduled against Inter Milan, it wouldn't be controversial to say that Fluminense has every chance to maintain the sequence of Brazilian team qualifications in this Club World Cup. <br/><br/> </div>]]></content><author><name>Ace Laboratory Football Team - Miguel Angelo e Pedro Lopes</name></author><category term="Football;"/><category term="Analysis"/><category term="Football;"/><category term="Analysis;"/><category term="Club"/><category term="World"/><category term="Cup"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Fluminense's Solid Group Stage Performance at the Club World Cup]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Palmeiras’ Group Stage Performance at the Club World Cup</title><link href="https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2025/palmeiras_grupos_en/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Palmeiras’ Group Stage Performance at the Club World Cup"/><published>2025-06-26T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-06-26T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2025/palmeiras_grupos_en</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2025/palmeiras_grupos_en/"><![CDATA[<hr/> <p align="justify"> Se quiser ler este texto em pt-br, <a href="https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2000/palmeiras_grupos_pt/"> clique aqui.</a> </p> <h2> <b> Introduction </b></h2> <div style="text-align: justify"> Palmeiras advances to the next phase, but doesn't convince. In 3 matches full of ups and downs, the green and white team that remains unbeaten in the Club World Cup achieved 2 draws and 1 victory that led them to first place in Group B. In the next phase, their opponent will be Botafogo, which, despite qualifying in second place in their group, promises to give the São Paulo team a hard time. <br/><br/> <h3> <b> Analysis of the Three Matches </b></h3> The analysis of the first three matches points to a team very comfortable playing reactively, trying to take advantage of opponent's mistakes to activate their attackers at speed and take advantage of a likely disorganized defensive sector to create their main goal-scoring opportunities, which was also reflected in a lower number of passes exchanged by the team compared to opponents in the second and third games. Not by chance, most of Abel Ferreira's team's converted chances have as their starting point a counterattack or a ball recovered still in the offensive sector. <br/><br/> Another well-known strength of the green and white team is aerial play, with good headers like Flaco Lopez, Murilo, and Gustavo Gómez (who won 100% of aerial duels attempted in this first phase), crosses and set-piece situations usually bring danger to the opposing team. As an example of this, we have the two goals against Al Ahly; the first was the result of an offensive set-piece crossed into the area, which forced the Egyptian team to take a more offensive stance and offer more gaps for the reactive game plan so well worked by Palmeiras' team, while the second had its play initiated with a victory in an aerial duel in Palmeiras' defensive area, which triggered a devastating counterattack leaving Flaco Lopez with a clear path to attack from the midfield line. <br/><br/> <h3> <b> Negative Points </b></h3> Despite these unquestionably strong points, not everything is going well for the São Paulo team. The group stage games (especially the last one) exposed two flaws of the green team in this World Cup. The first and most notable is the lack of creativity during the offensive phase, the poor form experienced by Raphael Veiga (the team's main playmaker) compromises the entire play creation process, thus most attacks result in an attempt to cross into the center of the area, almost 90 in total across the three games, and although they were so numerous, they generally have little effectiveness (especially when Flaco Lopez is not on the field); as an alternative to the poor form of number 23, the coach has been betting on another midfielder, the young Maurício, who started the competition as a starter and came on in the other two games at halftime, in those minutes on the field, he accumulated more offensive actions, including an assist in the game against Al Ahly, and the equalizing goal against Inter Miami. <br/><br/> The second negative point of Palmeiras' team is the lack of aggressiveness of the team without their starting defensive midfield duo. The absence of Aníbal Moreno in the game against Inter Miami was greatly felt by Abel Ferreira's team, which, when positioned in the defensive sector, did not show the necessary intensity to recover the ball. Another consequence of this also notable in this last game was the performance of Richard Rios, who, finding himself without his usual partner, participated in 50% more plays with the ball compared to the other two matches and doubled his number of passes compared to his average, in addition to having his positioning affected, performing more functions in midfield. <br/><br/> <h2> <b> Conclusion </b></h2> Finally, Palmeiras' next opponent promises to be a great challenge. Both teams have fast attacks and abuse quick transitions, which indicates a dynamic and high-intensity game. Another highlight is the absence of midfielder Gregore in the black and white team, a fundamental piece in Botafogo's midfield. It remains to be seen whether Abel Ferreira's team will have the necessary intensity and competence to advance to the next phase. <br/><br/> </div>]]></content><author><name>Ace Laboratory Football Team - Gabriel Madruga e João Victor</name></author><category term="Football;"/><category term="Analysis"/><category term="Football;"/><category term="Analysis;"/><category term="Club"/><category term="World"/><category term="Cup"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Palmeiras' Group Stage Performance at the Club World Cup]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">NBA Playoffs : The MVPs Duel</title><link href="https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2025/nba-playoffs_en/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="NBA Playoffs : The MVPs Duel"/><published>2025-06-09T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-06-09T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2025/nba-playoffs_en</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2025/nba-playoffs_en/"><![CDATA[<hr/> <style>body{text-align:justify}</style> <p>Se quiser ler este texto em pt-br, <a href="https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2000/nba-playoffs_pt"> clique aqui.</a></p> <h2> <b> Introduction </b></h2> <p>The NBA, the world’s premier basketball league, is split into two conferences: the Eastern and Western. Each season begins with a regular schedule, when every team faces one another, and concludes with the playoffs, in which teams compete only against opponents from their own conference, until the NBA Finals, in which the winner of each conference plays for the league’s championship.</p> <p>This year’s Western Conference playoffs delivered one of the most thrilling seven-game series imaginable, as the top‐seeded Oklahoma City Thunder—fresh off a historic 68–14 regular season—took on the fourth‐seeded Denver Nuggets, who finished a strong 50–32. Despite their differing records, both clubs feature one of the sport’s brightest stars.</p> <p>Oklahoma City’s Shai Gilgeous-Alexander and Denver’s Nikola Jokić, both leading MVP contenders, put up spectacular numbers. Shai led the league in scoring, averaging 32.7 points per game, while Nikola ranked among the top three in points, rebounds, assists, and steals, producing one of the greatest individual seasons in NBA history. After each advanced through the first round, they squared off in a historic playoff showdown</p> <h3> <b> Game 1 (DEN 121 – 119 OKC) </b> </h3> <p>Denver faced a steep disadvantage heading into Game 1: they’d had just one day to rest after a grueling seven-game series against the Clippers, while Oklahoma City enjoyed an eight-day layoff. Most observers expected Denver to be overmatched.</p> <p>But Nikola Jokić—one of the season’s MVP frontrunners—put on a masterclass. He poured in 42 points on 51.7 percent shooting and hauled in 22 rebounds, spearheading a vital upset over the Thunder.</p> <p>Oklahoma City still got big nights from their stars: Shai Gilgeous-Alexander scored 33 points, and reserve guard Alex Caruso chipped in 20 points and five steals, helping force Denver into 18 turnovers.</p> <p>ESPN Analytics gave OKC a 98 percent chance to win with six minutes left in the fourth quarter (trailers down 95–108), but Denver stormed back. Jokić alone scored 18 of his points in that final period, rallying the Nuggets to a dramatic victory.</p> <div class="row"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2025-06-09-post-nba-playoffs/Game_1.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" title="Game1" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <h3> <b> Game 2 (DEN 106 – 149 OKC) </b> </h3> <p>In Game 2, the Thunder overwhelmed the Nuggets from the opening tip. Shai Gilgeous-Alexander was nothing short of sensational, pouring in 34 points by the end of the third quarter on an almost surreal 11-for-13 shooting (84.6%). He toyed with Denver’s defense, attacking off the dribble, pulling up from midrange, and finishing through contact at the rim.</p> <p>Oklahoma City wasted no time stamping its authority. By the end of the first quarter, the home club had built a 24-point cushion, igniting the crowd and forcing Denver into its first lineup adjustments. The thunder kept rolling in the second period, and in the third, they outscored the Nuggets by an additional 17 points. With a 41-point lead as the fourth quarter began, victory was all but assured before the final buzzer.</p> <div class="row"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2025-06-09-post-nba-playoffs/Game_2.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" title="Game2" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <h3> <b> Game 3 (DEN 113 – 104 OKC) </b> </h3> <p>In a nail-biter that stretched into overtime, the Denver Nuggets ultimately prevailed thanks to Jamal Murray’s all-around mastery. Murray poured in 27 points, dished out 8 assists and came up with 4 steals, asserting himself as the game’s defining force on both ends of the floor. His relentless pressure—both as a creator in the half-court and as a disruptor on defense—kept Denver’s momentum alive when it mattered most.</p> <p>Oklahoma City’s young wing Jalen Williams likewise turned in a spectacular performance, tallying a career-high 32 points on a blend of smooth pull-ups and aggressive drives. Yet his heroics weren’t quite enough: Shai Gilgeous-Alexander, typically the Thunder’s engine, managed just 18 points on 7-for-22 shooting (31.8%), a rare off night compared to his torrid regular-season pace. And although Nikola Jokić logged heavy minutes, he never found his usual rhythm—finishing with 20 points but also losing the ball eight times, well below the MVP-level production fans have come to expect. Ultimately, Murray’s late-game poise in overtime tipped the scales in Denver’s favor.</p> <div class="row"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2025-06-09-post-nba-playoffs/Game_3.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" title="Game3" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <h3> <b> Game 4 (DEN 87 – 92 OKC) </b> </h3> <p>Game 4 proved the roughest outing of the series. Both clubs looked out of sync, with Oklahoma City managing just a 35.6 percent field-goal rate and Denver an even lower 31.3 percent—their worst shooting marks all series.</p> <p>That offensive slump stemmed largely from fatigue. The Nuggets arrived on virtually no rest after a grueling seven-game battle with the Clippers, while the Thunder’s long layoff couldn’t fully compensate for rusty legs. With little recovery time, neither team could find its usual rhythm.</p> <p>Hall-of-Famer Charles Barkley called the scheduling “unfair” to Denver, noting it’s tough to play Friday night and then turn around for Sunday afternoon with almost no break.</p> <div class="row"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2025-06-09-post-nba-playoffs/Game_4.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" title="Game4" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <h3> <b> Game 5 (DEN 105 – 112 OKC) </b> </h3> <p>Nikola Jokić delivered a masterclass—44 points on 68 percent shooting—but his teammates never caught fire. Michael Porter Jr., for example, logged 29 minutes yet scored just two points, connecting on only 14.3 percent of his shots.</p> <p>By contrast, Oklahoma City boasted a balanced attack, converting 50 percent of its field goals and featuring six players in double figures. That collective efficiency carried the Thunder to victory and underscored their status as the game’s best team.</p> <div class="row"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2025-06-09-post-nba-playoffs/Game_5.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" title="Game5" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <h3> <b> Game 6 (DEN 119 – 107 OKC) </b> </h3> <p>Sick? You wouldn’t know it. Jamal Murray’s availability for Game 6 was in serious doubt after the flu laid him low—interim coach David Adelman even admitted he was “definitely sick”—and he wasn’t cleared to play until just 45 minutes before tip-off. Yet in this “flu game,” Murray still poured in 25 points, lifting Denver to victory and forcing a winner-takes-all Game 7.</p> <p>And he wasn’t alone. Julian Strawther provided a key spark off the bench: in just three minutes of third-quarter action, he rattled off eight points that shifted the momentum. When Strawther checked in, the score was 80–78 in Denver’s favor; by the time he sat back down, the Nuggets had extended their lead to 90–81—an impact performance in the biggest moments.</p> <div class="row"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2025-06-09-post-nba-playoffs/Game_6.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" title="Game6" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <h3> <b> Game 7 (DEN 93 – 125 OKC) </b> </h3> <p>In Game 7, OKC won the series and advanced to the Western Conference Finals. Despite holding a five-point lead after the first quarter, the Denver Nuggets couldn’t maintain the pace—especially in the second quarter, in which they committed eight turnovers compared with the Thunder’s two. OKC outscored Denver 39–20 in that period, and the lead only grew in the second half. In addition to the turnovers, the Nuggets shot under 23 percent from three-point range.</p> <p>On Denver’s side, key role players Jamal Murray, Michael Porter Jr., and Aaron Gordon combined for just 27 points on 39 percent shooting. By contrast, OKC’s supporting duo, Jalen Williams and Chet Holmgren, combined for 37 points on 53 percent shooting.</p> <p>Finally, MVP candidate Shai Gilgeous-Alexander delivered an outstanding performance, scoring 35 points on 12 of 19 shooting and knocking down 75 percent of his three-point attempts.</p> <div class="row"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2025-06-09-post-nba-playoffs/Game_7.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" title="Game7" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <h2> <b> Conclusion </b> </h2> <p>Though the Thunder finished the regular season with one of the greatest records in NBA history (68–14), they struggled mightily against the Denver Nuggets—Denver accounted for 29 percent of Oklahoma City’s defeats until the western conference finals, handing them five of their 17 total losses on the year (including two regular-season setbacks and three in the playoffs). The championship series itself became a war of attrition: MVP candidates on both sides raised their games, while the Thunder’s tenacious defense forced an astonishing 124 turnovers over seven hard-fought contests.</p> <p>In the end, Shai Gilgeous-Alexander captured MVP honors, leading all scorers with a blistering 52.9 percent field-goal rate and averaging 29,7 points per game in the series to cement his reputation as a franchise cornerstone. Nikola Jokić was hardly far behind—he posted a series-long double-double, averaging 28.4 points and 13.9 rebounds per contest—underscoring just how razor-thin the margin was between these two superstars.</p>]]></content><author><name>Ace Laboratory Team - Brenno Santos, Antonio Magalhães</name></author><category term="Basketball;"/><category term="Analysis"/><category term="Basketball;"/><category term="Analysis"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Predicting Match Results in Football - Part 3</title><link href="https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2025/post_poisson_3_en/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Predicting Match Results in Football - Part 3"/><published>2025-05-16T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-05-16T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2025/post_poisson_3_en</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2025/post_poisson_3_en/"><![CDATA[<hr/> <p align="justify"> Se quiser ler este texto em pt-br, <a href="https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2000/post_poisson_3_pt/"> clique aqui.</a> </p> <h2> <b> Introduction </b></h2> <div style="text-align: justify"> In this final post of the Results Prediction series, we’ll introduce the Poisson Distribution. This time, we’ll do something a bit different: we’ll explain what the Poisson Distribution is and walk through the step-by-step process of predicting the final score of a match. <br/><br/> <h3> <b> The Poisson Distribution </b> </h3> The Poisson distribution is a discrete probability distribution that expresses the probability of a given number of events occurring in a fixed interval of time or space. It assumes these events occur with a known average rate and independently of the time since the last event. <br/><br/> <div style="width: 100%; margin: 0 auto; text-align: center;"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2025-05-16-post_poisson_3/image1.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <center>The Poisson distribution formula. <br/><br/></center> The left side of the Poisson distribution formula, P(X = k), represents the probability of exactly k events occurring in a fixed interval. Here, X is the number of events, and k is the specific number we’re interested in. <br/><br/> The numerator on the right-hand side, e<sup>-λ</sup> λ<sup>k</sup>, has two components. λ<sup>k</sup> reflects the likelihood of k events happening based on the average rate λ. The e<sup>-λ</sup> accounts for the randomness of the events, ensuring that the probability decreases as the number of events deviates from the expected rate. <br/><br/> The denominator on the right-hand side, k!, adjusts for the number of ways the k events can occur. The factorial notation calculates the number of possible arrangements, ensuring that the probability accounts for the fact that the order of events doesn’t matter. <br/><br/> <h3> <b> How to Use It in Football </b> </h3> First of all, we need to clarify something: there are several goal prediction models using the Poisson distribution, but we’re going to use the simplest one, which considers only the historical match data of the two teams. More complex models can account for other variables such as pitch quality, head-to-head records, and more. <br/><br/> To begin, we need to decide which matches we want to predict. For this post, we’ll try to predict the number of goals in a Fla-Flu derby (with Fluminense as the home team) in 2023, using data from both teams from the 2022 Brasileirão season. <br/><br/> <h3> <b> Preparing the Table </b> </h3> We used the results of all matches from the 2022 Brasileirão, sourced from the FBREF website. The data includes various pieces of information, but we only used the match results. For the next steps, we had to split the data into “Home Team,” “Away Team,” “Home Goals,” and “Away Goals.” <br/><br/> <h3> <b> Calculating Offensive and Defensive Strength </b> </h3> To predict the number of goals for a team, we first need to calculate the Offensive Strength and Defensive Strength of the teams in the Brasileirão, based on last season. <br/><br/> The Offensive Strength is the average number of goals scored by each team, both at home and away. The formula is: <br/><br/> <ul> <li>Total goals scored at home / number of games</li> <li>Total goals scored away / number of games</li> </ul> <br/><br/> In the 2022 Brasileirão season, there were 534 home goals and 371 away goals. Divided by the number of games (380), we get the average goals scored at home as 1.405, and the average goals scored away as 0.976.<br/><br/> The Defensive Strength is the average number of goals conceded by each team — which is essentially the inverse of Offensive Strength, since the number of goals scored by the home team equals the number of goals conceded by the away team. Thus, the average goals conceded at home is 0.976, and the average goals conceded away is 1.405. <br/><br/> Now we can use these league averages to calculate the strengths of the specific teams we want to analyze. <br/><br/> <h3> <b> Predicting Fluminense’s Goals </b> </h3> To calculate Fluminense’s Offensive Strength, we take the number of home goals scored by Fluminense in the 2022 season (39) and divide it by the number of home games (19) = 2.052. Then we divide this value by the league’s average home goals (1.405), giving us an Offensive Strength of 1.460.<br/><br/> Next, we calculate Flamengo’s Defensive Strength to predict how many goals Fluminense might score. We take the number of away goals conceded by Flamengo (24) and divide it by their number of away games (19) = 1.263. Then divide this by the average away goals conceded in the league (1.405), yielding a Defensive Strength of 0.898.<br/><br/> Now we can compute the expected number of goals for Fluminense by multiplying: Fluminense’s Offensive Strength (1.460) × Flamengo’s Defensive Strength (0.898) × Average Home Goals (1.405)<br/><br/> <b>1.460 × 0.898 × 1.405 = 1.845 </b> <br/><br/> <h3> <b> Predicting Flamengo’s Goals </b> </h3> To calculate the number of goals Flamengo might score, we use the same formulas, but replace the average home goals with average away goals.<br/><br/> <ul> <li>Flamengo’s Offensive Strength: (23/19) / 0.976 = 1.239</li> <li>Fluminense’s Defensive Strength: (20/19) / 0.976 = 1.078</li> </ul> <br/><br/> Now, multiply these values with the average away goals: <br/><br/> <b>1.239 × 1.078 × 0.976 = 1.305 </b> <h3> <b> Using the Poisson Distribution </b> </h3> Since no match ends in a score of 1.845 to 1.305, we use these values with the Poisson Distribution to spread 100% of the probability across possible goal outcomes for each team. We want to estimate the chance of each team scoring a specific number of goals (in our case, 0 to 5) — the number of occurrences of the event — using the expected goals (1.845 for Flu, 1.305 for Fla) - the expected occurencies. <br/><br/> We can do this easily in Python using the command:<br/><br/> <figure class="highlight"><pre><code class="language-python" data-lang="python"><table class="rouge-table"><tbody><tr><td class="gutter gl"><pre class="lineno">1
</pre></td><td class="code"><pre><span class="n">poisson</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">pmf</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">NumberOfOccurrences</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">ExpectedOccurrences</span><span class="p">)</span>
</pre></td></tr></tbody></table></code></pre></figure> <br/><br/> Calculating this 6 times for each team, we get the following vectors: <table> <thead> <tr> <th style="color: white;">Goals</th> <th style="color: white;">Fluminense</th> <th style="color: white;">Flamengo</th> </tr> </thead> <tbody> <tr> <td style="color: white;">0 goals</td> <td style="color: white;">15.80%</td> <td style="color: white;">27.11%</td> </tr> <tr> <td style="color: white;">1 goal</td> <td style="color: white;">29.15%</td> <td style="color: white;">35.39%</td> </tr> <tr> <td style="color: white;">2 goals</td> <td style="color: white;">26.90%</td> <td style="color: white;">23.09%</td> </tr> <tr> <td style="color: white;">3 goals</td> <td style="color: white;">16.54%</td> <td style="color: white;">10.05%</td> </tr> <tr> <td style="color: white;">4 goals</td> <td style="color: white;">7.63%</td> <td style="color: white;">3.28%</td> </tr> <tr> <td style="color: white;">5 goals</td> <td style="color: white;">2.82%</td> <td style="color: white;">0.86%</td> </tr> </tbody> </table> Since these results are independent, the most likely result of the match is 1-1, as both teams are most likely to score 1 goal. Multiplying the probabilities of each team scoring 1 goal gives the probability of a 1-1 draw: <br/><br/> <b>0.2915 × 0.3539 = 0.1031</b><br/><br/> Using the np.outer command with these two vectors, we can generate the full probability matrix of all possible score combinations.<br/><br/> <div style="width: 100%; margin: 0 auto; text-align: center;"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2025-05-16-post_poisson_3/image2.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <center>By summing the probabilities: Above the diagonal (Fluminense wins): 48.96% <br/> On the diagonal (Draw): 22.75% <br/> Below the diagonal (Flamengo wins): 26.91% <br/><br/></center> <h2> <b> Conclusion </b> </h2> <div style="width: 100%; margin: 0 auto; text-align: center;"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2025-05-16-post_poisson_3/image3.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <center>In total, we had 3 draws, 2 wins for Flamengo, and 1 win for Fluminense. When Fluminense played at home, there were two draws and one win for Fluminense. <br/><br/></center> From this result, we can compare it with the first encounter between the teams in 2023, which took place in the final round of the Taça Guanabara and ended in a 2-1 win for Fluminense. That result was the second most likely according to our model, indicating that the match followed the expected trend based on the teams’ offensive and defensive performance from the previous season. <br/><br/> Moreover, we didn’t use data from earlier 2023 Campeonato Carioca matches, which could provide more up-to-date offensive and defensive strength values — and thus a different probability distribution. <br/><br/> With this analysis, we wrap up our series of posts, where we’ve explored some predictive models applied to football and how we can use them to better understand the sport. <div> </div></div>]]></content><author><name>Ace Laboratory Football Team - Lucas Calmon, Pedro Carvalho</name></author><category term="Football;"/><category term="Analysis"/><category term="Football;"/><category term="Analysis"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Predicting Match Results in Football - Part 2</title><link href="https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2025/post-value-market_2_ing/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Predicting Match Results in Football - Part 2"/><published>2025-04-15T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-04-15T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2025/post-value-market_2_ing</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2025/post-value-market_2_ing/"><![CDATA[<p align="justify"> Se quiser ler este texto em pt-br, <a href="https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2025/post-value_market_2_pt/"> clique aqui.</a> <h2> <b> Introduction </b> </h2> <div style="text-align: justify"> In this post, we will present another method for predicting victory. This time, we will use the market value of the teams as the main variable, which corresponds to the sum of the individual market values of all players on the team. We will explore how this metric can influence the performance of clubs and their chances of winning a match. </div> <h3> <b> Context </b> </h3> <div style="text-align: justify"> Money plays a significant role in modern football. With the transfer market becoming increasingly inflated, it is necessary to spend more money in the transfer windows to maintain competitiveness in the top leagues. The professionalization of the sport has also had a great influence on increasing the cost of maintaining a team, as more expenses are now needed for infrastructure and creating a quality environment to stay ahead of the competition. In fact, studies in the Premier League and Championship (2011-2020) have shown a correlation between a team's payroll and the position the team achieves in the table (Soccernomics, Simon Kuper and Stefan Szymanski). Money drives football. Therefore, we will use the market value of the clubs in the Brazilian league to try to predict the final result of the matches. <div style="width: 100%; margin: 0 auto; text-align: center;"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2025-04-15-post-value-market-2/img1.jpeg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <h3> <b> Method </b> </h3> <h4><b>Data</b></h4> <div style="text-align: justify"> We will use data from the 2023 season. <b></b> The dataset has two main parts: <ul> <br/> <li>The match data: information such as the home team, away team, result, match date, and odds for victory (home, draw, away), extracted from the <a href="https://football-data.co.uk/">Football-data</a> website and the Pinnacle betting house.</li> <li>The market value of the teams in the Brazilian league 2023, sourced from <a href="https://www.transfermarkt.com.br">Transfermarkt</a>.</li> </ul> Let’s take a look at our match dataset. It has about 19 fields, but only the following are relevant to us: <div style="width: 80%; margin: 0 auto; text-align: center;"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2025-04-15-post-value-market-2/img2.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <b>Legend:</b> home: Home team; away: Away team; res: Match result; oddHome: Home team's chance of victory; oddDraw: Chance of a draw; oddAway: Away team's chance of victory. <br/><br/> We will transform the odds into probabilities. To do this, we don't simply use the formula (1/odds), because the sum of the probabilities would exceed 1. This excess represents the bookmaker's margin, so we normalize the probabilities to correct it. <div style="width: 80%; margin: 0 auto; text-align: center;"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2025-04-15-post-value-market-2/img3.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> Now let's take a look at the market value data: <div style="width: 50%; margin: 0 auto; text-align: center;"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2025-04-15-post-value-market-2/img4.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <div style="text-align: justify"> The column <code>TFM_Value</code> contains the market value in millions of euros. For example, Palmeiras' market value is 138.4 million euros. These values represent the market values of the clubs as of July 20, 2024. <b></b> We have merged the two datasets, adding the market value columns for the home team (<code>tmH</code>) and the away team (<code>tmA</code>). <div style="width: 100%; margin: 0 auto; text-align: center;"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2025-04-15-post-value-market-2/img5.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> The variable we will use to predict the results is the ratio between <code>tmH</code> (home team's market value) and <code>tmA</code> (away team's market value). More specifically, the <b>logarithm</b> of this ratio. The reason we use the log is that the distribution of the ratio between <code>tmH</code> and <code>tmA</code> is skewed to the right. Applying the log function makes the distribution symmetrical, which improves performance. The image below helps to visualize this. <div style="width: 80%; margin: 0 auto; text-align: center;"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2025-04-15-post-value-market-2/img6.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div style="width: 80%; margin: 0 auto; text-align: center;"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2025-04-15-post-value-market-2/img7.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> So, the <code>logTmRatio</code> will be the variable we will use to predict the results. In other words, our independent variable. <div style="text-align: justify"> We encoded the <code>res</code> column as: <ul> <li>0: Home team victory</li> <li>1: Draw</li> <li>2: Away team victory</li> </ul> This new column will be called <code>winValue</code>. <div style="width: 80%; margin: 0 auto; text-align: center;"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2025-04-15-post-value-market-2/img8.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <h3><b>Model</b></h3> <div style="text-align: justify"> We will use an <b>Ordinal Logistic Regression</b> model, which is a technique used to model the relationship between an ordinal response variable (i.e., categories with order) and one or more predictor variables. In our case, the ordinal response variable is <code>winValue</code> and the predictor variable will be <code>logTmRatio</code>. The model involves determining the \( \alpha_1 \), which is the point that separates the home team victory from the draw or away team victory. In other words, if a point falls before \( \alpha_1 \), the model will predict a home team victory, and if it falls after \( \alpha_1 \), it will predict a draw or away team victory. The \( \alpha_2 \) is the point that separates the draw from the away team victory. The \( \beta \) indicates how the predictor variable, in our case the market value ratio, influences the result. For better visualization of this explanation, observe the graph below, where \( \alpha_1 \) is represented by \( \theta_1 \): <div style="width: 80%; margin: 0 auto; text-align: center;"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2025-04-15-post-value-market-2/img9.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> We used an Ordinal Logistic Regression model, which relates an ordinal response variable (<code>winValue</code>) to a continuous predictor (<code>logTmRatio</code>). The model finds two cutoff points: <ul> <li><b>\( \alpha_1 \)</b>: separates home team victory from draw or away team victory</li> <li><b>\( \alpha_2 \)</b>: separates draw from away team victory</li> <li><b>\( \beta \)</b>: tells us how this ratio influences the result of The coefficient of <code>logTmRatio</code></li> </ul> Now that we understand the model, let's prepare its training. The training dataset consists of the first 200 games of the season, and the remaining 180 games will be used as the test dataset. <div style="width: 80%; margin: 0 auto; text-align: center;"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2025-04-15-post-value-market-2/img10.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <b>Model coefficients:</b><br/> \(\beta \): -0.6309<br/> \( \alpha_1 \): -0.1519<br/> \( \alpha_2 \): 0.0533 </div> <h4><b>Probability Calculation</b></h4> <div style="text-align: justify"> From these coefficients, we calculate: <ul> <li><b>Ph (home team victory)</b>: \( \frac{1}{1 + e^{-( \alpha_1 - βx)}} \)</li> <li><b>Pd (draw)</b>: \( \frac{1}{1 + e^{-( \alpha_2 - βx)}} - Ph \)</li> <li><b>Pv (away team victory)</b>: \( 1 - Ph - Pd \)</li> </ul> <div style="width: 100%; margin: 0 auto; text-align: center;"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2025-04-15-post-value-market-2/img11.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> Let's add columns to compare the prediction results from Pinnacle and what we found. <div style="width: 100%; margin: 0 auto; text-align: center;"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2025-04-15-post-value-market-2/img12.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <h3> <b> Evaluation </b> </h3> <div style="text-align: justify"> Remember that we used the first 200 games to train our model, so we will compare the prediction results from our test set. <div style="width: 100%; margin: 0 auto; text-align: center;"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2025-04-15-post-value-market-2/img13.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> The most important value for us is highlighted: the average accuracy of results from both the bookmaker and our model. Notice that they are close, and even the bookmaker had less than 50% accuracy. One important thing to consider when analyzing these data is the size of the training set, which only had 200 matches, and we achieved a result of a 0.03 difference from the bookmaker. Let’s create two cross tables to better understand in which types of games our model is most likely to make errors and succeed. <div style="width: 40%; margin: 0 auto; text-align: center;"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2025-04-15-post-value-market-2/img14.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> Notice that in the draw column, our model did not predict draws, which is due to the fact that the market value ratio between two teams has a very low probability of resulting in a draw, since it is expected that the market values of the teams would need to be close to each other. <div style="width: 40%; margin: 0 auto; text-align: center;"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2025-04-15-post-value-market-2/img15.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> The numbers are quite scattered, but we can see that our model performs better than Pinnacle in predicting away team victories, while Pinnacle has most of its correct predictions in home team victories. </div> <h2> <b> Conclusion </b> </h2> <div style="text-align: justify"> In the next post, we will discuss the prediction of results based on the Poisson distribution, a well-known distribution used to predict rare events. Stay tuned to our social media to not miss any updates from the blog! </div> </p>]]></content><author><name>Ace Laboratory Football Team - Lucas Calmon, Pedro Carvalho</name></author><category term="Football;"/><category term="Analysis"/><category term="Football;"/><category term="Analysis"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary></entry></feed>