<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.4.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://ac3lab.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://ac3lab.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2025-07-08T02:21:38+00:00</updated><id>https://ac3lab.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">blank</title><subtitle>Marrying academic rigor with practical applications to benefit sports </subtitle><entry><title type="html">Fluminense vs Al Hilal: Brazilian Resilience Meets Saudi Power in Quarterfinal Showdown</title><link href="https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2025/alhilal_flu_en/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Fluminense vs Al Hilal: Brazilian Resilience Meets Saudi Power in Quarterfinal Showdown"/><published>2025-07-07T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-07-07T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2025/alhilal_flu_en</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2025/alhilal_flu_en/"><![CDATA[<hr/> <p align="justify"> Se quiser ler este texto em português, <a href="https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2000/alhilal_flu_pt/"> clique aqui.</a> </p> <h2> <b> Introduction </b></h2> <div style="text-align: justify"> Fluminense and Al Hilal faced off in the quarterfinals of the FIFA Club World Cup in a highly anticipated matchup. Both teams reached this stage by overcoming heavyweight opponents in the Round of 16 — defying expectations. The Brazilian side pulled off a major upset by eliminating Inter Milan, runners-up of the 2024/25 UEFA Champions League, while the Saudi club knocked out the mighty Manchester City. <br/><br/> Still, according to Opta Analyst projections, Al Hilal were the favorites to reach the semifinals, with a 59.8% chance of advancing. <br/><br/> The starting lineups reflected each team's strategic intentions. Fluminense lined up in a 3-5-2, with Cano and Jhon Arias forming the attacking duo. The only change from the side that beat Inter was the inclusion of left-back Fuentes, replacing the suspended Renê. Meanwhile, Al Hilal fielded the same XI that started against City, but this time arranged in a 5-3-2 formation — reminiscent of the tactical setup Simone Inzaghi used at Inter Milan, his previous club. <br/><br/> <h3> <b> Match Summary </b></h3> The first half was tightly contested and offered few clear chances. Al Hilal had 52% possession compared to Fluminense's 48%, and both sides registered three shots each, with only one on target for either team. The Brazilian side opened the scoring through a beautiful strike from Martinelli, capitalizing on a poorly cleared ball by João Cancelo. Al Hilal's best chance came from a set piece, as Koulibaly's header forced an excellent save from Fábio, preserving the 1-0 lead. <br/><br/> The game was heavily concentrated in midfield, with 56% of all passes occurring in the central third. Al Hilal had the edge in duels, winning 61% of them. On the negative side, Arias had a quiet first half — losing 11 of his 12 duels and giving the ball away 11 times in 29 possessions. The strikers were largely uninvolved: Marcos Leonardo and Cano had only 12 and 10 touches, respectively — only slightly more than goalkeeper Fábio, who had 8. <br/><br/> Defensively, left wing-back Al-Harbi stood out for Al Hilal, leading the first half in tackles and interceptions. <br/><br/> In the second half, Al Hilal pressed higher up the pitch and found the equalizer early. After another set piece and a Koulibaly header, the ball fell to Marcos Leonardo, who slotted it home. Despite the goal, the Saudi team continued pushing forward but struggled to break down Fluminense's compact defense. Al Hilal took 12 shots in the second half — four times more than in the first — but only three hit the target. <br/><br/> They finished the half with 65% possession and earned 10 corner kicks, compared to just one for Fluminense. Still, the Brazilian side proved more dangerous. One of their two shots on target in the second half found the back of the net — Hércules scored to restore the lead. Fluminense had another golden opportunity after a poor pass by Renan Lodi left Cano one-on-one with goalkeeper Bounou, but the Al Hilal keeper came out on top. <br/><br/> In the closing minutes, Al Hilal pushed for an equalizer, bringing on striker Hamdallah in place of midfielder Kanno. However, they couldn't find the breakthrough, and Fluminense secured a spot in the semifinals. <br/><br/> Defensively, Fluminense put in a rock-solid performance. Center-back Ignácio was the standout, leading the game in defensive actions (16), clearances (9), and blocked shots (3). Right-back Samuel Xavier also impressed — he led the match in interceptions (3) and assisted the game-winning goal. <br/><br/> Despite the loss, Koulibaly had an excellent game for Al Hilal. The defender won 10 of his 11 duels, provided the assist for their goal, and led the match in tackles with 5. <br/><br/> <h3> <b> Tactical Analysis </b></h3> When Fluminense had possession, their buildup started with the three center-backs, while wing-backs Samuel Xavier and Fuentes pushed high to align with the forward pair in the central channel. Meanwhile, Al Hilal, in their defensive phase, avoided high pressing and maintained five players in their back line, with their wing-backs closely marking Fluminense's wide players. The image below helps illustrate this tactical structure. <br/><br/> <div class="row"> <div class="col-sm-10 offset-sm-1 mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2025-06-26-post_world_cup/quartas/alhilalflu1.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" title="Fluminense's attacking formation" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <center>Fluminense's attacking formation and movement patterns. <br/><br/></center> Similarly, when Al Hilal had the ball, they also relied on a back three for their buildup, pushing their wing-backs high up the pitch — a strategy quite similar to Fluminense's. However, the Brazilian side defended differently. Left midfielder Nonato joined Cano and Arias to form a front line of three, while Bernal and Martinelli (replaced by Hércules in the second half) sat deeper in midfield. Additionally, Fluminense's wing-backs were tasked with marking their Saudi counterparts, and the three center-backs tracked the attacking duo of Marcos Leonardo and Malcom. The following image illustrates this defensive setup. <br/><br/> <div class="row"> <div class="col-sm-10 offset-sm-1 mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2025-06-26-post_world_cup/quartas/alhilalflu2.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" title="Al Hilal's attacking formation" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <center>Al Hilal's attacking formation and Fluminense's defensive setup. <br/><br/></center> Regarding Al Hilal's buildup play, it's important to highlight Rúben Neves (marked in blue in the image), who is originally a midfielder but has been deployed as a center-back since the Round of 16 match against Manchester City. He was the team's primary distributor, leading the game in passes with 71 (92% accuracy) and topping the chart for line-breaking passes with 25 successful out of 36 attempts. <br/><br/> Neither team opted for high pressing. Instead, both chose to defend in mid-to-low blocks, aiming to reduce space and limit counterattacking opportunities. This is reflected in the PPDA (Passes Allowed per Defensive Action) zone maps for each team, which show that most of the pressing occurred in their own defensive thirds. On the map, red zones indicate higher pressing intensity, while blue zones indicate lower pressure. <br/><br/> <div class="row"> <div class="col-sm-10 offset-sm-1 mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2025-06-26-post_world_cup/quartas/alhilalflu3.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" title="PPDA comparison between teams" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <center>PPDA comparison showing defensive pressure zones for both teams. <br/><br/></center> <h2> <b> Conclusion </b></h2> Fluminense defeated Al Hilal in the first-ever meeting between the two sides, securing a place in the FIFA Club World Cup semifinals. Once again, the Brazilian team showed defensive resilience and attacking efficiency, earning another win against a favored opponent. <br/><br/> It was their second consecutive victory as underdogs — first against Inter Milan, now against Al Hilal — underscoring the strength of their collective play, tactical discipline, and competitive maturity under coach Renato Gaúcho. <br/><br/> In the semifinals, Fluminense will face Chelsea, who have already eliminated Benfica and Palmeiras. It will be another major challenge against top European competition, but based on their campaign so far, Fluminense have proven they are ready to compete with the best in the world. <br/><br/> </div>]]></content><author><name>Ace Laboratory Team - Antonio Magalhães</name></author><category term="Football;"/><category term="Analysis"/><category term="Football;"/><category term="Analysis;"/><category term="Club"/><category term="World"/><category term="Cup"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A tactical analysis of the FIFA Club World Cup quarterfinal clash between Fluminense and Al Hilal, featuring defensive masterclass and strategic battles]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Heartbreak and Heroics: Palmeiras Faces Chelsea in a Quarterfinal Thriller</title><link href="https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2025/chelsea_palmeiras_en/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Heartbreak and Heroics: Palmeiras Faces Chelsea in a Quarterfinal Thriller"/><published>2025-07-07T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-07-07T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2025/chelsea_palmeiras_en</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2025/chelsea_palmeiras_en/"><![CDATA[<hr/> <p align="justify"> Se quiser ler este texto em português, <a href="https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2000/chelsea_palmeiras_pt/"> clique aqui.</a> </p> <h2> <b> Introduction </b></h2> <div style="text-align: justify"> In the FIFA Club World Cup quarterfinals, Palmeiras and Chelsea face off to continue in the tournament. Their last meeting was in the 2021 Club World Cup final, where Chelsea won 2–1 in extra time. <br/><br/> According to Opta Analyst, Palmeiras had a low chance of winning, with a 15.4% probability of victory, 20.1% chance of a draw, and a 64.5% chance of defeat. Among the 8 teams qualified so far, Palmeiras had the lowest probability of reaching the semifinals, at just 25.50%. <br/><br/> Palmeiras lined up in a 4-2-3-1 formation, similar to the setup used in their match against Botafogo. However, in this clash against the English side, the team had two crucial absences due to suspensions: Piquerez and Gustavo Gómez, both key players who had been instrumental in Palmeiras' Club World Cup campaign. They were replaced by Vanderlan and Micael. <br/><br/> Chelsea also had a major absence in their squad — Ecuadorian midfielder Moisés Caicedo was suspended for the quarterfinals. As a result, the team started with Andrey Santos in his place. Chelsea also used a 4-2-3-1 formation, similar to the one used in their round of 16 match against Benfica, but with some changes, including fullback Reece James and midfielder Lavia. <br/><br/> <h3> <b> Match Summary </b></h3> The first half was marked by greater offensive threat from Chelsea. With 68% possession, 9 shots, and 1 goal, the English side clearly dominated the first 45 minutes. Until the 40th minute, the Brazilian team had no shots at all, highlighting their lack of offensive efficiency during that period. By halftime, Palmeiras had only two shots, with just one on target. During this half, English player Cole Palmer — who scored the goal — had more shots than the entire Palmeiras team, being a key offensive pillar for Chelsea in that stretch. <br/><br/> Palmeiras began to improve after the 30-minute mark, gradually attempting to enhance their attacking performance, which was reflected in the attacking momentum graph — previously showing near-total dominance by Chelsea. <br/><br/> In the second half, at the 53rd minute, 18-year-old Estevão scored the equalizer for Palmeiras. The second half began much more balanced, with Palmeiras having 46% possession in the first 15 minutes and two shots — equaling their total from the entire first half. <br/><br/> The final 45 minutes saw both teams score again, each adding one more goal. Possession in the second half was more balanced, with Palmeiras at 44% versus Chelsea's 56%, and a high number of total shots — 15 combined, with 5 from Palmeiras and 10 from Chelsea. <br/><br/> Despite Palmeiras managing to create a few more chances as the match went on, Chelsea had the overall better performance, securing the victory. In total, Chelsea had 19 shots, 6 of which were on target, achieving a slightly higher shot conversion rate than Palmeiras — 31.6% compared to Palmeiras' 28.6%. <br/><br/> A negative highlight for Palmeiras was Vanderlan, who, possibly feeling the pressure of replacing first-choice left-back Piquerez, had a poor performance. He completed only 63% of his passes, won just 2 out of 7 duels (28.6%), and lost possession 15 times out of 44 touches — clearly showing how much the suspended starter was missed. The image below, which shows Palmeiras' crosses, highlights the poor performance on the left flank, with none of the left-side crosses being completed. <br/><br/> <div class="row"> <div class="col-sm-10 offset-sm-1 mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2025-06-26-post_world_cup/quartas/CrossPalmeirasChelsea.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" title="Palmeiras' crosses against Chelsea" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <center>Palmeiras' crosses against Chelsea, showing poor performance on the left flank. <br/><br/></center> To compensate for the two suspended Palmeiras players, Bruno Fuchs — who had already performed well against Botafogo — played a crucial role in keeping the team in the game. He led all players in defensive actions with 18, far ahead of second-place Marc Cucurella with 8. Bruno was also the leader in clearances, interceptions, and tackles, and did not suffer a single successful dribble against him. <br/><br/> In this impressive Chelsea victory, one of the most important players was the outstanding Marc Cucurella. He had a pass accuracy of 96% and delivered an exceptional defensive performance. Notably, he was responsible for blocking all three of Palmeiras' blocked shots — showing that he excels at his duties both offensively and defensively. <br/><br/> <h3> <b> Tactical Analysis </b></h3> Chelsea's tactical approach was characterized by their ability to control possession and create attacking opportunities through structured build-up play. The English side's 4-2-3-1 formation allowed them to maintain numerical superiority in midfield while providing width through their full-backs. <br/><br/> The absence of Moisés Caicedo was well-managed by Chelsea's coaching staff, with Andrey Santos stepping in seamlessly to maintain the team's defensive balance. This adaptability showcased Chelsea's squad depth and tactical flexibility. <br/><br/> Palmeiras, despite missing key defensive players, attempted to maintain their attacking identity while adapting to Chelsea's superior technical quality. The Brazilian side's 4-2-3-1 formation was designed to provide defensive solidity while creating opportunities through quick transitions. <br/><br/> However, the absence of Piquerez and Gustavo Gómez proved crucial, particularly in defensive transitions and attacking support from the flanks. Vanderlan's struggles on the left side significantly impacted Palmeiras' ability to create width and maintain attacking momentum. <br/><br/> <h2> <b> Conclusion </b></h2> In a high-level clash marked by tactical contrasts and individual performances, Chelsea ultimately proved superior to Palmeiras, securing a deserved victory in the FIFA Club World Cup quarterfinals. Despite Palmeiras' effort to adjust and respond in the second half — particularly through the brilliance of young Estevão and the defensive leadership of Bruno Fuchs — the absence of key players like Piquerez and Gustavo Gómez left noticeable gaps in both defensive stability and offensive support. <br/><br/> Chelsea dominated the first half with possession, precision, and an organized attacking structure, driven largely by Cole Palmer and Marc Cucurella. The English side's ability to control the game through positioning, pressing, and fluid movement exposed Palmeiras' struggles to build and progress the ball. <br/><br/> While Palmeiras improved in the second half, showing more offensive intent and better balance, their overall inefficiency in the final third and individual underperformances — especially from Vanderlan — hindered a full comeback. Chelsea's depth, tactical consistency, and high execution level across all phases of play ensured their progression to the semifinals. <br/><br/> Chelsea came out on top in this match, as predicted by Opta's probabilities, and now moves forward in the tournament with a 36.25% chance of winning the championship. Their next challenge will be against Fluminense, who arrive in great form after impressive victories over Internazionale — last season's Champions League runners-up — and Al-Hilal, the undefeated champions of the 2023/2024 Saudi Pro League. <br/><br/> In summary, it was a match that showcased the importance of tactical discipline, squad depth, and composure under pressure — areas where Chelsea held the advantage and converted it into a hard-fought, yet clear, win. <br/><br/> </div>]]></content><author><name>Ace Laboratory Team - Brenno Santos</name></author><category term="Football;"/><category term="Analysis"/><category term="Football;"/><category term="Analysis;"/><category term="Club"/><category term="World"/><category term="Cup"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A tactical analysis of the FIFA Club World Cup quarterfinal clash between Palmeiras and Chelsea, featuring strategic battles and individual performances]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Real Madrid vs Borussia Dortmund: A Champions League Rematch on the World Stage</title><link href="https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2025/real_borussia_en/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Real Madrid vs Borussia Dortmund: A Champions League Rematch on the World Stage"/><published>2025-07-07T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-07-07T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2025/real_borussia_en</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2025/real_borussia_en/"><![CDATA[<hr/> <p align="justify"> If you want to read this text in Portuguese, <a href="https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2000/real_borussia_pt/"> click here.</a> </p> <h2> <b> Introduction </b></h2> <div style="text-align: justify"> The clash between Real Madrid and Borussia Dortmund marked the end of the quarterfinal stage of the FIFA Club World Cup, with the Spanish giants emerging victorious. This highly anticipated match drew extra attention, as it was a rematch of the 2023/24 UEFA Champions League final — a game Real Madrid won. Dortmund came into this fixture eager for revenge and with much to prove. <br/><br/> Real Madrid lined up in a 4-3-1-2 formation, despite missing key players such as Eduardo Camavinga and Ferland Mendy due to injury. Still, the squad showcased its impressive depth, featuring rising talents like Gonzalo, who had already made a mark in earlier Club World Cup matches, and the promising Arda Güler, a creative force steadily earning his place in Madrid's setup. <br/><br/> Borussia Dortmund, on the other hand, opted for a 3-4-1-2 formation. One of the emotional subplots was Jobe Bellingham taking the field without his brother Jude, who was suspended due to yellow card accumulation. Jobe had been performing well throughout the tournament. Up front, Serhou Guirassy, one of the competition's top scorers with three goals in four matches, carried Dortmund's hopes. Aware of the challenge, even he admitted before the game: "It's going to be a tough match." <br/><br/> According to Opta Analyst, Real Madrid entered the match with a 59.7% chance of advancing to the semifinals, while Borussia Dortmund had a 40.3% chance. These odds reflected Madrid's status as one of the tournament favorites to lift the trophy. <br/><br/> <h3> <b> Match Summary </b></h3> Before the 35-minute mark in the first half, Real Madrid's probability of advancing to the semifinals skyrocketed from 59.7% to 91.9%, thanks to two early goals from their rising stars — Gonzalo in the 10th minute and Fran García in the 20th. <br/><br/> Despite Borussia Dortmund having the edge in possession (58%) compared to Madrid's 42% in the first half, the Spanish side delivered a much more efficient and dangerous performance. They registered 8 total shots, with 4 on target, resulting in a 50% shot accuracy. After the second goal, Madrid pulled back slightly, allowing Dortmund to regain more control of the ball, but without creating significant danger. <br/><br/> In the second half, Madrid reasserted dominance, holding 57% of possession and recording 7 shots, 4 of which were on target. Despite the continued pressure, no goals came until stoppage time. Then, the game took a dramatic turn. <br/><br/> At 92 minutes, Borussia Dortmund capitalized on a defensive lapse and scored their first goal, narrowing the gap to 2–1. But Madrid responded almost immediately, with a third goal at the 94th minute, restoring their two-goal cushion. Dortmund, needing two more goals to equalize and force extra time, surged forward in desperation and won a penalty. Guirassy converted from the spot, making it 3–2 in the 98th minute — despite only 5 minutes of stoppage time being initially added. <br/><br/> The game continued for one final, dramatic opportunity. In the dying seconds, midfielder Marcel Sabitzer unleashed a powerful strike that was brilliantly saved by the Madrid goalkeeper. The shot had an xGOT (Expected Goals on Target) value of 0.70, indicating a high probability of scoring based on shot placement and trajectory — a near-equalizer denied only by a moment of goalkeeping brilliance. <br/><br/> In the end, despite Real Madrid's victory, the match was highly competitive. Madrid held 49% possession to Dortmund's 51%, and both teams produced a high volume of chances — 15 shots for Madrid, 12 for Dortmund. Madrid, however, showed superior finishing efficiency, with a 53.3% shot accuracy (8 out of 15), underlining their clinical edge in front of goal. <br/><br/> Another crucial factor in Madrid's win was their strong defensive performance. The back four combined for 16 tackles and 22 defensive actions, a testament to their resilience and discipline under pressure. <br/><br/> The undisputed standout of the match was Arda Güler, Real Madrid's brilliant 20-year-old prospect, who once again showcased why he is considered one of the most promising young talents in world football. Güler delivered a masterclass performance, registering two assists and playing a key role in orchestrating Madrid's attacking transitions. <br/><br/> Operating primarily as an advanced playmaker behind the two forwards, Arda Güler demonstrated exceptional vision, composure, and technical ability. He maintained an outstanding pass accuracy of 96%, completing nearly every pass he attempted — a remarkable feat in such a high-stakes, fast-paced match. Over the course of the game, he recorded 78 touches, a clear sign of his influence and involvement in Real Madrid's build-up play. <br/><br/> Just as impressive was his ball security. Güler lost possession only four times throughout the entire match, a testament to his intelligence on the ball and ability to navigate through pressure from the Dortmund midfield. Whether finding space between the lines, delivering sharp through balls, or contributing defensively when needed, he played with a maturity far beyond his age. <br/><br/> This performance adds to a growing list of impressive displays by Güler in the Club World Cup, further strengthening his case to become a regular starter in Carlo Ancelotti's squad. With key injuries in the team, Güler seized his opportunity and turned the spotlight onto himself — not just as a future star, but as a player ready to make a difference in the present. <br/><br/> <h3> <b> Tactical Analysis </b></h3> Real Madrid's tactical approach was characterized by their ability to adapt to the absence of key players while maintaining their attacking identity. The 4-3-1-2 formation allowed them to create numerical superiority in midfield while providing multiple attacking options through the central areas. <br/><br/> The absence of Camavinga and Mendy was well-managed through tactical adjustments and the impressive performances of their replacements. This adaptability showcased Madrid's squad depth and the quality of their youth development system. <br/><br/> Borussia Dortmund's 3-4-1-2 formation was designed to provide defensive solidity while creating attacking opportunities through the flanks and central areas. However, their inability to convert possession into clear-cut chances in the first half proved costly, despite their numerical advantage in midfield. <br/><br/> The dramatic finish highlighted both teams' fighting spirit and tactical flexibility. Dortmund's late surge demonstrated their ability to adapt under pressure, while Madrid's resilience showed their experience in managing high-stakes situations. <br/><br/> <h2> <b> Conclusion </b></h2> Real Madrid emerged victorious in a thrilling, high-scoring quarterfinal, a match that not only highlighted their resilience but also showcased the depth and brilliance of their rising stars. Despite missing key players due to injuries, the Spanish giants delivered a confident and commanding performance, proving once again why they are one of the most successful clubs in world football. <br/><br/> With that win, Real Madrid now advances to the semifinals, where they will face their most challenging opponent yet — Paris Saint-Germain, the reigning UEFA Champions League titleholders. It's a clash worthy of a final, featuring two European powerhouses filled with elite talent and global stars. <br/><br/> However, according to Opta Analyst, PSG enters the match as the favorite, with a 58.1% probability of reaching the final of the inaugural FIFA Club World Cup in its new format. Real Madrid, while not the statistical favorite in this semifinal, still carries the weight of experience, tradition, and individual brilliance — factors that often defy the odds. <br/><br/> Despite being the underdog in this particular matchup, Real Madrid holds a 24.67% chance of winning the entire tournament, according to Opta projections. This figure places them among the top contenders and reflects the competitive nature of the remaining teams. Given their form, mentality, and historical pedigree, it would be unwise to count Madrid out. <br/><br/> As they prepare for a blockbuster semifinal, Real Madrid will be banking on the momentum gained in the quarterfinals, the growth of their young stars, and the leadership of their seasoned veterans. The road ahead is difficult — but if there's one team that knows how to navigate elite competitions, it's Real Madrid! <br/><br/> </div>]]></content><author><name>Ace Laboratory Team - Brenno Santos</name></author><category term="Football;"/><category term="Analysis"/><category term="Football;"/><category term="Analysis;"/><category term="Club"/><category term="World"/><category term="Cup"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A tactical analysis of the FIFA Club World Cup quarterfinal clash between Real Madrid and Borussia Dortmund, featuring a dramatic Champions League rematch]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Palmeiras vs Botafogo: A Tactical Battle in the Club World Cup Round of 16</title><link href="https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2025/botafogo_palmeiras_en/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Palmeiras vs Botafogo: A Tactical Battle in the Club World Cup Round of 16"/><published>2025-07-02T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-07-02T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2025/botafogo_palmeiras_en</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2025/botafogo_palmeiras_en/"><![CDATA[<hr/> <p align="justify"> Se quiser ler este texto em português, <a href="https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2000/botafogo_palmeiras_pt/"> clique aqui.</a> </p> <h2> <b> Introduction </b></h2> <div style="text-align: justify"> The clash between Brazilian clubs Botafogo and Palmeiras extended their growing rivalry onto the international stage, as they met once again in the Round of 16 of the 2025 FIFA Club World Cup. The two sides previously faced off in the 2024 Copa Libertadores Round of 16 and battled for the title in the Brasileirão Série A — with Botafogo emerging victorious in both competitions. <br/><br/> In the Club World Cup group stage, Palmeiras topped Group A with one win and two draws. Botafogo finished second in Group B, recording two victories — including an impressive win over UEFA Champions League winners PSG — and one loss. <br/><br/> Despite Botafogo's recent dominance in the head-to-head record — three wins and two draws in their last five meetings — Palmeiras entered the knockout stage as slight favorites. According to Opta Analyst, Palmeiras had a 52.4% chance of winning in regular time, compared to 23.8% for Botafogo, with the probability of a draw also at 23.8%. The overall chances of advancing to the quarterfinals were more balanced: 55.6% for Palmeiras and 44.4% for Botafogo. <br/><br/> In the end, Palmeiras secured a 1–0 win in the Round of 16 match, with substitute Paulinho scoring the decisive goal in the first half of extra time. <br/><br/> Tactically, Botafogo stuck with the 4-3-3 formation that was used against PSG and Atlético de Madrid, with Danilo Barbosa stepping in for the suspended Gregore. Palmeiras deployed a 4-2-3-1 system and made several notable changes to their starting lineup. Academy product Allan started on the right wing, while rising star Estevão featured on the left. In defense, Bruno Fuchs replaced the injured Murilo, and Maurício took over for Veiga in midfield. <br/><br/> <h3> <b> Match Summary </b></h3> The first half ended with a clear offensive advantage for the São Paulo team. By the 30-minute mark, the Rio de Janeiro side had yet to attempt a single shot, while their opponents had already registered five. By halftime, the São Paulo club had taken seven shots with an expected goals (xG) value of 0.51, compared to just two shots and 0.07 xG for Botafogo. Despite this disparity, possession remained fairly balanced — 51% for Palmeiras and 49% for Botafogo. However, none of the nine total shots hit the target, highlighting the lack of efficiency from both sides in front of goal. <br/><br/> In the second half, possession remained nearly even — 52% for Botafogo and 48% for Palmeiras — but the São Paulo team continued to threaten more consistently. They registered nine shots to the opponent's two, including three on target versus just one. The xG numbers reflected this attacking edge: 0.64 to just 0.06. Goalkeeper John stood out in this period, making three crucial saves to keep Botafogo in the game. Another stat that underscored Palmeiras' dominance was corner kicks: they took 13 in regular time, compared to just two for Botafogo. <br/><br/> With the match still goalless after 90 minutes, extra time began at a high tempo. Substitutions brought new energy to the field — most notably Paulinho, who scored the decisive goal in the first half of extra time. During those 15 minutes, Palmeiras stayed on the front foot, producing two shots on target and converting one. <br/><br/> In the second half of extra time, already ahead, Palmeiras adopted a more defensive posture, particularly after replacing forward Paulinho with center-back Micael. They had only 26% possession in that stretch, focusing on protecting the lead. Meanwhile, Botafogo pushed forward aggressively. In those final 15 minutes alone, the Rio side recorded 10 shots — more than in the entire 90 minutes plus the first extra-time period combined. That final stretch generated 0.75 xG, accounting for 68.2% of their total expected goals for the entire match. <br/><br/> After 120 minutes, Palmeiras secured their place in the quarterfinals with a stronger overall performance: 19 total shots, five on target, 47% possession, and approximately 83% passing accuracy. <br/><br/> A standout performer for Palmeiras was Richard Ríos, who delivered a high-quality display over the full 120 minutes to help secure the win. He provided an assist and led his team in tackles (4), duels won (10), and distance covered (13,4 km). His performance was well-rounded, contributing both offensively and defensively, and he played a key role in the team's success. <br/><br/> The image below shows the attacking momentum of the match, highlighting Palmeiras' superiority, with most of the opportunities and greater attacking efficiency, despite the overall statistical balance in the game. It also shows Botafogo dominating the second half of extra time, with 10 attempts compared to none from the team from São Paulo. <br/><br/> <div class="row"> <div class="col-sm-10 offset-sm-1 mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2025-06-26-post_world_cup/oitavas/pressure_map.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" title="Attacking momentum of the match" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <center>Attacking momentum of the match between Palmeiras and Botafogo. <br/><br/></center> <h3> <b> Tactical Analysis </b></h3> In addition to repeating the same formation used against the European sides (PSG and Atlético de Madrid), Botafogo also stuck to the same strategy: applying pressure in their own defensive half and relying on counterattacks. <br/><br/> When in possession — and not attacking in transition — head coach Renato Paiva's approach was clear: the wingers, Artur and Savarino, moved into central areas to create space for overlapping full-backs Vitinho and Alex Telles, while Igor Jesus stayed as the central reference up front. This dynamic can be seen in the image below. <br/><br/> <div class="row"> <div class="col-sm-10 offset-sm-1 mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2025-06-26-post_world_cup/oitavas/formation2.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" title="Botafogo's tactical formation" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <center>Botafogo's tactical formation and movement patterns. <br/><br/></center> Although he had been performing well in the tournament, forward Savarino stood out for the wrong reasons in this match. He completed only 75% of his passes, lost all 5 duels he contested, and gave away possession 10 times out of 27 touches. <br/><br/> Additionally, Botafogo focused more of their attacks down the right flank. Vitinho and Artur were the players with the most passing offers, with 74 and 60 respectively. The team's passing map helps illustrate this scenario. <br/><br/> <div class="row"> <div class="col-sm-6 offset-sm-3 mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2025-06-26-post_world_cup/oitavas/passing_map_botafogo.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" title="Botafogo's passing network" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <center>Botafogo's passing network against Palmeiras. <br/><br/></center> Palmeiras set up in a 4-2-3-1 formation but employed an intelligent defensive tactic by shifting into a 5-4-1 variation, as shown in the image below. This adjustment proved highly effective against Botafogo's attack — particularly since, as mentioned earlier, the team focused heavily on attacking down the flanks. The compact defensive shape effectively neutralized those wide advances. <br/><br/> <div class="row"> <div class="col-sm-10 offset-sm-1 mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2025-06-26-post_world_cup/oitavas/formation1.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" title="Palmeiras' defensive formation" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <center>Palmeiras' defensive formation and tactical adjustments. <br/><br/></center> Palmeiras' exceptional defensive performance is evidenced by Igor Jesus' high offensive movement — 29 runs in behind — yet without any effective finishing. Palmeiras' PPDA (passes per defensive action) reflects a low-block defense, with lower values closer to the box, as shown in the image below: the more red, the lower the index (in other words, more pressure), and the more blue, the higher the index and lower the pressure. <br/><br/> <div class="row"> <div class="col-sm-10 offset-sm-1 mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2025-06-26-post_world_cup/oitavas/ppda_palmeiras.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" title="Palmeiras' PPDA by zone" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <center>Palmeiras' PPDA by zone against Botafogo. <br/><br/></center> One of the key positive defensive standouts was left-back Joaquín Piquerez, who played a vital role in executing this system. In addition to maintaining strong positioning and discipline on his side of the field, Piquerez led the team in defensive actions (10) and clearances (5), showing great awareness and composure throughout the match. His contribution was crucial in absorbing the pressure during Botafogo's most aggressive phases and helped Palmeiras maintain their structure even as the match became more intense. <br/><br/> <h2> <b> Conclusion </b></h2> The match between Palmeiras and Botafogo showcased not only the intensity of a growing rivalry but also the tactical maturity and adaptability of both teams. While Botafogo stayed true to its counterattacking identity and maintained structural consistency throughout the tournament, Palmeiras demonstrated greater flexibility — both in formation and in in-game adjustments — which ultimately made the difference. <br/><br/> Statistically and tactically, Palmeiras managed to control key areas of the pitch, especially in defense, where their shape and discipline effectively neutralized Botafogo's strengths. The transition from a 4-2-3-1 to a 5-4-1 in defensive phases proved decisive, as did individual performances like that of Joaquín Piquerez and Richard Ríos, who embodied the balance between defensive solidity and offensive support. <br/><br/> In a match defined by fine margins and intense strategic battles, Palmeiras' ability to adapt and capitalize on moments of opportunity, such as the goal in extra time, underlined the team's competitive edge — not just in terms of talent, but in execution and game management. The result was not only a deserved qualification but also a performance that reflects the evolution of Brazilian clubs on the international stage. <br/><br/> Having secured a spot in the quarterfinals, Palmeiras now faces a high-stakes encounter with Chelsea — the same opponent they battled in the 2022 Club World Cup final. The matchup not only revives recent history but also adds another chapter to Palmeiras' pursuit of the long-awaited dream of eternal glory on the world stage. <br/><br/> </div>]]></content><author><name>Ace Laboratory Team - Brenno Santos, Antonio Magalhães</name></author><category term="Football;"/><category term="Analysis"/><category term="Football;"/><category term="Analysis;"/><category term="Club"/><category term="World"/><category term="Cup"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A thrilling tactical showdown between Brazilian giants Palmeiras and Botafogo in the Club World Cup Round of 16, featuring intense extra-time drama and strategic masterclass]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Flamengo vs Bayern: An Analysis of Errors and Tactical Differences</title><link href="https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2025/flamengo_bayern_en/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Flamengo vs Bayern: An Analysis of Errors and Tactical Differences"/><published>2025-07-02T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-07-02T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2025/flamengo_bayern_en</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2025/flamengo_bayern_en/"><![CDATA[<hr/> <p align="justify"> Se quiser ler a versão em português, <a href="https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2000/flamengo_bayern_pt/"> clique aqui.</a> </p> <h2> <b> Introduction </b></h2> <div style="text-align: justify"> This past Sunday, 06/29, Flamengo and Bayern Munich faced off in a match between the cream of what South American football can offer (and possibly the best team on the continent) against a team from the highest tier of European football (which wasn't the best of the last season) in a game marked by several things, but mainly by the number of errors on the part of the Rio team that led to the Bavarian team's goals, which raises the question: were these failures just demerits of the red-and-black team? <br/><br/> <h3> <b> Match Summary </b></h3> Even before the ball rolled, there was already a debate about the lineup made by Filipe Luís, for including Arrascaeta, the team's top scorer of the season, but who doesn't usually impose as much physical vigor when marking pressure or when serving as a speed escape valve for the attack, roles that would be better performed by another athlete, such as Bruno Henrique, the striker who came on in place of the Uruguayan in the group stage match against Chelsea and changed the course of the match. However, whatever the Brazilian coach's thinking was, it was completely influenced by what happened in the early minutes of the game. <br/><br/> The pace of the game, the strategy, and the level of pressure that would be felt throughout the 90 minutes were severely influenced when at 3 minutes and 45 seconds, the Argentine goalkeeper Rossi kicked a ball at Pulgar, which ended up resulting in a corner kick (by the referee's understanding) that generated a second one, from which came the first goal of the match, an own goal. This change in the score so quickly would already be enough to change the entire match planning, but the blitz imposed by Bayern was still in full force when the French defender Upamecano came up from the German defensive line to contest a pass received by Arrascaeta, which succeeded in Harry Kane's fatal finish, extending the score. <br/><br/> After this disastrous sequence of events, the Rio team managed to have more possession and try to put their game idea into practice, leading to their first goal play, resulting from a deflected cross into the penalty area with a Gerson finish, which made the Bavarian imposition return with full force. <br/><br/> <div class="row"> <div class="col-sm-10 offset-sm-1 mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2025-06-26-post_world_cup/oitavas/fla_bayern.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" title="Momento ofensivo da partida" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <center>Offensive moment of the match between Flamengo and Bayern. <br/><br/></center> As we can observe in the attacking third actions chart, this pattern repeated itself in the interval between the third and fourth goals of the Europeans, giving the impression that the German team "took their foot off" after making the result more comfortable, leaving more possession and space for the Brazilian team to work the plays, which resulted in a second goal after the Uruguayan midfielder's cross hit Olise's open hand inside the area, generating a penalty converted with precision by Jorginho. This pattern repeated itself after this reduction in the score advantage, with the pace being imposed by Bayern and with pressure on a ball exit where Luiz Araújo tried to dribble near the defensive penalty area, turning into a precise shot from the English striker. <br/><br/> This norm in the game dynamics can help explain the fact that at the end of the match some data showed a Flamengo equivalent or superior to Bayern (such as a minimal advantage in possession, a greater number of shots, xG), although the Rio team was not very close to equalizing the score (the closest chance came from an Arrascaeta header at 6 minutes of play), the eye test points to the contrary, a Bayern that dictated the pace when the advantage decreased and that didn't take as many risks. <br/><br/> <h3> <b> Tactical Analysis </b></h3> Regarding the question of errors, forced or not, they can be contextualized, in part, by the difference in quality between the two teams in various aspects, but mainly in the effectiveness of pressure and efficiency in punishing the opposing team's errors, and one of the justifications for these issues can be, besides the quality of the players on the field, due to the history of German teams having this historical habit of pressing high, after all, gegenpressing comes from there. <br/><br/> The concept of marking by pressing in attack is not something that was created recently, but this style of football, especially in the context of German football, is attributed to German coach Ralf Rangnick, who influenced modern generations of German coaches, such as Jurgen Klopp, Thomas Tuchel, and Julian Nagelsmann. Additionally, the German league is known for the high level of athleticism imposed by the players, fundamental factors for teams like Klopp's Borussia or Hansi Flick's Bayern Munich to establish their game plans brutally, having vigor to move up the marking line, attack spaces quickly, etc. <br/><br/> This very high-pressure football, combined with the high marking line, has been in the club's DNA for a long time, and besides being very well refined by recent coaches, such as Nagelsmann and Hansi Flick, they are put into practice by Kompany, the current coach, while the ephemerality of Brazilian coaches' work combined with the lack of conviction in fixed game styles for clubs, makes it difficult for the work to be much refined here, and for there to be an exploited sequence even with coach changes. <br/><br/> <h2> <b> Conclusion </b></h2> In the end, the Brazilian team did what they could, especially given the circumstances, and lost in a dignified manner, and although they were far from making a head-to-head match, it doesn't mean that the defeat was a disgrace or something of the sort, and this defeat cannot shake the structures of both the squad and the entire football department because the season is only at its halfway point, with the most decisive matches for national competitions and the Copa Libertadores very close. <br/><br/> The match between Flamengo and Bayern demonstrated not only the technical difference between the teams, but also the importance of tactical consistency and efficient pressure in modern football. While Bayern showed its tradition of high pressure and finishing efficiency, Flamengo revealed fragilities that need to be worked on to compete at the highest international level. <br/><br/> The defeat, although heavy on the scoreboard, serves as valuable learning for the development of Brazilian football, showing that tactical evolution and methodological consistency are fundamental for success in the international scenario. <br/><br/> </div>]]></content><author><name>Ace Laboratory Team - João Victor Gadelha</name></author><category term="Football;"/><category term="Analysis"/><category term="Football;"/><category term="Analysis;"/><category term="Club"/><category term="World"/><category term="Cup"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[How Flamengo's errors and Bayern's pressure defined the result in the Club World Cup Round of 16]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Fluminense vs Inter: A Victory that Surprised Everyone</title><link href="https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2025/fluminense_inter_en/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Fluminense vs Inter: A Victory that Surprised Everyone"/><published>2025-07-02T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-07-02T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2025/fluminense_inter_en</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2025/fluminense_inter_en/"><![CDATA[<hr/> <p align="justify"> Se quiser ler este texto em português, <a href="https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2000/fluminense_inter_pt/"> clique aqui.</a> </p> <h2> <b> Introduction </b></h2> <div style="text-align: justify"> In our last post about Fluminense after the group stage, we stated: "the Flu had both defensive failures and wasted goal opportunities, which should be crucial points for improvement in the next game". In this knockout match against Inter Milan, it seems the tricolor understood the message. <br/><br/> Renato Gaúcho bet on a different formation, with a 3-5-2. In the first minute of the match, Fluminense's high pressing was already causing discomfort for goalkeeper Sommer, who shares a ball with Germán Cano. A few minutes later, after a series of passes, Fluminense overloaded Inter with four players inside the penalty area, setting up a cross for Cano, who, free, becomes lethal again and scores the first goal of the match, putting Fluminense in an excellent position. <br/><br/> <h3> <b> Match Summary </b></h3> After the goal, Fluminense didn't panic. The Italian team kept the ball at their feet, ending the first half with 66% possession, but without causing major problems for the tricolor, who intercepted their shots very well, both in defense and in goalkeeper Fábio's hands. Additionally, Renato's team was the one that came closest to the second goal still in the first half, with a wasted chance from Samuel Xavier after an impressive play by Arias. This play, along with Ignácio's disallowed goal, demonstrates that, despite having less possession, Fluminense definitely didn't back down from the game. <br/><br/> Accumulating only half the number of passes from Inter at the end of the first half (126 to 250), it was the Rio team that showed more sharpness, ending the first half with 5 shots against Inter's 5. Dimarco, who wears number 32, was responsible for three of them. See the possession from Inter's passing network: <br/><br/> <div class="row"> <div class="col-sm-6 offset-sm-3 mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2025-06-26-post_world_cup/oitavas/rede_inter.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" title="Inter's passing network" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <center>Inter Milan's passing network against Fluminense. <br/><br/></center> In the second half, Fluminense continued in this style — Renato, in fact, ended the game with a substitution to spare. Inter, however, showed they wanted the game, making changes that had an effect: from the 60th minute onwards, the team brought much danger to Fluminense, shooting an incredible 10 times. The tricolor fan certainly held their breath seeing the three great chances created by Inter, one wasted by de Vrij, another from Lautaro that stopped in Fábio, and one more from Lautaro in the same minute that hit the post. These three shots alone add up to 0.52 xG. <br/><br/> Who closed the tricolor's house was the match's star, Ignácio, who won 10 of the 15 duels he contested. This pressure suffered can be observed from Fluminense's PPDA (Passes per Defensive Action) chart: <br/><br/> <div class="row"> <div class="col-sm-10 offset-sm-1 mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2025-06-26-post_world_cup/oitavas/ppda_flu.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" title="Fluminense's PPDA" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <center>Fluminense's PPDA by zone against Inter. <br/><br/></center> <h3> <b> Tactical Analysis </b></h3> Renato Gaúcho's tactical change to 3-5-2 was fundamental for Fluminense's success. This formation allowed greater control of the midfield and better defensive coverage, especially against Inter's technical quality. <br/><br/> Fluminense's defensive system worked exceptionally well, with the three defenders providing extra security and the full-backs offering offensive width when necessary. The high pressing at the beginning of the match caught Inter by surprise and resulted in Cano's early goal. <br/><br/> Ignácio's performance was particularly notable. The player not only won most of the duels but was also crucial in defensive organization and offensive transition. His versatility allowed Fluminense to maintain tactical structure even under intense pressure from Inter in the second half. <br/><br/> <h2> <b> Conclusion </b></h2> However, qualification was destined for the Warriors team, who killed the game at Hércules' feet in stoppage time, to confirm an extremely conscious and deserved victory. <br/><br/> Fluminense demonstrated significant tactical evolution compared to previous games. The change to 3-5-2, combined with a more aggressive approach at the beginning of the match, was fundamental to neutralizing Inter's quality. The team showed maturity in managing the result, even under intense pressure in the second half. <br/><br/> After this victory, fans may have been excited about the possibility of revenge against Manchester City. However, the Club World Cup has shown that it never tires of surprising, and Fluminense now has a match scheduled against Al-Hilal for Friday, which will very likely be their biggest challenge so far. <br/><br/> The performance against Inter demonstrates that Fluminense is growing in the tournament and could be a surprise in the next phases. The combination of defensive solidity, offensive efficiency, and tactical adaptability makes the tricolor a fearsome opponent for any team. <br/><br/> </div>]]></content><author><name>Ace Laboratory Team</name></author><category term="Football;"/><category term="Analysis"/><category term="Football;"/><category term="Analysis;"/><category term="Club"/><category term="World"/><category term="Cup"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[How Renato Gaúcho surprised Inter with tactical change and Fluminense secured qualification in the Round of 16]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Botafogo’s Surprising Club World Cup Group Stage Performance</title><link href="https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2025/botafogo_grupos_en/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Botafogo’s Surprising Club World Cup Group Stage Performance"/><published>2025-06-26T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-06-26T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2025/botafogo_grupos_en</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2025/botafogo_grupos_en/"><![CDATA[<hr/> <p align="justify"> Se quiser ler este texto em pt-br, <a href="https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2000/botafogo_grupos_pt/"> clique aqui.</a> </p> <h2> <b> Introduction </b></h2> <div style="text-align: justify"> Botafogo, current Copa Libertadores champion and eighth in the Brazilian league, came into the tournament on a three-game winning streak and kept most of the continental title-winning squad, despite the departures of Luiz Henrique, Thiago Almada, and soon, Igor Jesus. To strengthen the roster, the club signed forwards Arthur Cabral, Joaquín Correa, and the young Argentine prospect Álvaro Montoro. <br/><br/> The Rio de Janeiro's club ended up in the group considered one of the toughest, with two European giants, including the Champions League winner, Paris Saint-Germain — the Spanish powerhouse Atlético Madrid, and a strong American side, the Seattle Sounders, and still managed to finish in second place, with two wins and one loss. <br/><br/> <h3> <b> Game 1: Botafogo vs Seattle Sounders </b></h3> Botafogo defeated Seattle Sounders 2–1 in the opening round of the Club World Cup, in a match characterized by two very different halves: a dominant first half from the Brazilian side, and a second half largely controlled by the Americans. <br/><br/> Botafogo started in a 4-4-2 formation, with Igor Jesus and Mastriani up front. Savarino and Barboza returned to the starting lineup after missing the previous match. <br/><br/> Despite having 55% possession in the first half, Seattle failed to register a single shot on target. Botafogo, playing more directly, had seven shots — four on target — and scored twice, both from aerial plays. The first came from a Jair header after a free-kick delivered by Alex Telles; the second was a headed goal by Igor Jesus following a cross from right-back Vitinho. The Sounders struggled defensively in the air, winning only 36% of their aerial duels in the opening half. <br/><br/> In the second half, Seattle couldn't make it count: they had 19 shots but only 5 on target — a 26% accuracy rate. The team exchanged more passes, occupied the attacking third, and applied pressure, but were undone by poor finishing and John's saves. <br/><br/> The shift in Botafogo's defensive strategy between the two halves can be illustrated using PPDA (Passes Allowed per Defensive Action) charts. This metric is calculated by dividing the number of passes the opponent makes by the number of defensive actions (interceptions, tackles, duels, and fouls) by the analyzing team. Lower PPDA values indicate higher pressing intensity. The image below shows Botafogo's PPDA by zone in the first half. <br/><br/> <div class="row"> <div class="col-sm-6 offset-sm-3 mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2025-06-26-post_world_cup/fase_de_grupos/PPDA_Firsthalf_BOTvsSEA.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" title="Botafogo's PPDA by zone in the first half against Seattle Sounders" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <center>Botafogo's PPDA by zone in the first half against Seattle Sounders. <br/><br/></center> In the first half, Botafogo mainly pressed in the zone just beyond midfield, without applying intense high pressing near the opponent's goal but showing reasonable pressure in advanced areas. <br/><br/> In the second half, as the PPDA zone chart shows, the team clearly dropped deeper, defending mostly in their own half. This strategic shift aimed to draw Seattle forward and explore counterattacking opportunities. The image below shows Botafogo's PPDA by zone in the second half. <br/><br/> <div class="row"> <div class="col-sm-6 offset-sm-3 mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2025-06-26-post_world_cup/fase_de_grupos/PPDA_SecondHalf_BOTvsSEA.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" title="Botafogo's PPDA by zone in the second half against Seattle Sounders" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <center>Botafogo's PPDA by zone in the second half against Seattle Sounders. <br/><br/></center> Offensively, Botafogo relied heavily on full-backs Alex Telles and Vitinho, who played a key role in creating chances. Both displayed strong technical ability and were involved in most of the team's attacks — 9 of the 12 Botafogo shots featured contributions from one of them. <br/><br/> <div class="row"> <div class="col-sm-6 offset-sm-3 mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2025-06-26-post_world_cup/fase_de_grupos/Rededepasses_BOTvsSEA.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" title="Botafogo's PPDA by zone in the second half against Seattle Sounders" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <center>Botafogo's pass network against Seattle Sounders. <br/><br/></center> <h3> <b> Game 2: Botafogo vs Paris Saint-Germain </b></h3> Botafogo, despite having less than a 15% chance of winning according to Opta Analyst, defeated the reigning Champions League champions 1-0 in a thrilling match. <br/><br/> The Rio club only made one change to the starting eleven that faced the Sounders in the tournament opener. Striker Mastriani was replaced by midfielder Allan. Coach Renato Paiva opted to strengthen the midfield, given that they were up against a very strong opponent in that area. Paiva chose a 4-3-3 formation instead of the 4-4-2 used in the opening game. <br/><br/> PSG's dominance of possession was evident from the very first minutes. By the 14th minute, the French side had already completed an impressive 146 passes compared to Botafogo's 17. That pattern continued for virtually the entire match — PSG controlled the ball while Botafogo relied on a reactive strategy focused on defensive organization and quick transitions. By the end of the game, the numbers reflected this imbalance — PSG finished with 68% possession, Botafogo with 24%, and 8% of the time with the ball in contention. Overall, PSG completed 706 of their 766 passes, while Botafogo completed 215 of their 278. The offensive disparity was also clear: the French team received 256 passes in the final third, compared to just 32 for the Rio side. <br/><br/> Despite having less possession and fewer attacking opportunities, Botafogo was decisive in its actions. The team's most effective attacks came down the right flank, the origin of all four of their crosses — all of which occurred before the 55th minute, when Portuguese left-back Nuno Mendes came on. His introduction shored up PSG's defense, as has been highlighted throughout the season for his strong performances. <br/><br/> One aspect that really stood out was the finishing accuracy. PSG attempted 16 shots during the game, but only two were on target. In contrast, Botafogo was extremely efficient: they took four shots and hit the target with everyone, demonstrating remarkable finishing. Offensively, striker Igor Jesus was decisive once again — with his only shot of the game, he scored the winning goal. <br/><br/> Botafogo adopted a more defensive posture, similar to the second half against the Seattle Sounders. However, this time their lines were much more compact and close together, allowing PSG very little space to penetrate. The image below shows Botafogo's defensive actions — on the left, forced turnovers and on the right, possession recoveries. <br/><br/> <div class="row"> <div class="col-sm-6 offset-sm-3 mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2025-06-26-post_world_cup/fase_de_grupos/Forced_turnovers_BOTvsPSG.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" title="Botafogo's defensive actions against PSG" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <center>Botafogo's defensive actions against PSG: forced turnovers (left) and possession recoveries (right). <br/><br/></center> It shows how Botafogo defended with a low block, recovering the ball predominantly in their own defensive half. <br/><br/> <h3> <b> Game 3: Botafogo vs Atletico Madrid </b></h3> Needing just a draw to take the lead in Group B, Botafogo put in an excellent defensive performance, which was absolutely necessary since Atlético Madrid went into the match knowing they had to win — especially given that if PSG also won, Atlético would have to do so by more than one goal to qualify. <br/><br/> Atlético Madrid had most of the possession, with 61% compared to Botafogo's 39%, completing 508 passes versus the Brazilian team's 303, with Botafogo making only 93 passes in the second half. Atlético's shot volume was also notable — they had 23 attempts but only 5 on target, a poor conversion rate that reflects Botafogo's incredibly solid defense. Even with Atlético's lack of finishing efficiency, they produced an impressive expected goals (xG) total of 3.03 but managed only one goal, underlining Madrid's attacking shortcomings. <br/><br/> Botafogo repeated the setup they had used against PSG — a 4-3-3 with very compact lines, relying on quick attacking transitions. It was also noticeable that Botafogo pressed mostly from their own half, with little high pressing; this is evident in the team's PPDA by zone. <br/><br/> <div class="row"> <div class="col-sm-6 offset-sm-3 mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2025-06-26-post_world_cup/fase_de_grupos/PPDA_BOTvsATL.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" title="Botafogo's PPDA by zone against Atlético Madrid" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <center>Botafogo's PPDA by zone against Atlético Madrid. <br/><br/></center> The image shows Botafogo's PPDA (passes per defensive action) across different areas of the pitch. The redder the zone, the lower the PPDA — in other words, the more intense the pressing. The bluer the zone, the less pressure the team applied. By analyzing the image, we can see that Botafogo's pressing was mostly concentrated in their own half, especially in the first quarter of the field. <br/><br/> <h2> <b> Conclusion </b></h2> To sum up Botafogo's group stage in one word, it would be <b>SURPRISING</b>. Botafogo ended up in one of the toughest groups at the Club World Cup and still managed to qualify, in second place, ahead of two of Europe's top teams, even beating the reigning Champions League winner. According to Opta Analyst, before the start of the Club World Cup, Botafogo had about a 70% chance of being eliminated in the group stage, which underlines the impressive tournament the team is having by securing this qualification. <br/><br/> Overall, Botafogo delivered an outstanding performance, both offensively and defensively. Going forward, the standout was Igor Jesus, who scored two of the team's three goals in the tournament so far. He made the most of the chances that came his way and was crucial to the Rio club's qualification. The player took only 6 shots in the competition, posting a conversion rate of around 33% — one of the highest in the tournament to date. <br/><br/> It's also important to highlight the team's defensive performance. Barboza and Jair played at an extremely high level, forcing opposing teams into very poor shot conversion rates. The three teams that faced Botafogo — Seattle (21.7%), Paris Saint-Germain (12.5%), and Atlético Madrid (20.8%) — all had low shooting accuracy, which speaks volumes about Botafogo's defensive solidity. <br/><br/> <div class="row"> <div class="col-sm-6 offset-sm-3 mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2025-06-26-post_world_cup/fase_de_grupos/Shot_accuracy.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" title="Botafogo's PPDA by zone against Atlético Madrid" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <center>Shot accuracy comparison between Botafogo and their opponents. <br/><br/></center> Botafogo had an outstanding group stage, with every player demonstrating exactly why they were crowned Libertadores champions in 2024 and showcasing the power and resilience of Brazilian football against Europe's elite. <br/><br/> The standout player for Botafogo in this group stage was Alexander Barboza. He was one of the key pillars behind their qualification, with only 2 dribbles completed against him across 3 matches, leading the team in tackles, interceptions, and clearances per game. <br/><br/> <div class="row"> <div class="col-sm-6 offset-sm-3 mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2025-06-26-post_world_cup/fase_de_grupos/Probabilities_GroupB.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" title="Botafogo's PPDA by zone against Atlético Madrid" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <center>Group B qualification probabilities before the tournament. <br/><br/></center> </div>]]></content><author><name>Ace Laboratory Football Team - Brenno Santos, Antonio Magalhães</name></author><category term="Football;"/><category term="Analysis"/><category term="Football;"/><category term="Analysis;"/><category term="Club"/><category term="World"/><category term="Cup"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Botafogo's Surprising Club World Cup Group Stage Performance]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Flamengo’s Dominant Group Stage Performance at the Club World Cup</title><link href="https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2025/flamengo_grupos_en/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Flamengo’s Dominant Group Stage Performance at the Club World Cup"/><published>2025-06-26T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-06-26T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2025/flamengo_grupos_en</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2025/flamengo_grupos_en/"><![CDATA[<hr/> <p align="justify"> Se quiser ler este texto em pt-br, <a href="https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2000/flamengo_grupos_pt/"> clique aqui.</a> </p> <h2> <b> Introduction </b></h2> <div style="text-align: justify"> Flamengo concluded the group stage in first place in Group D, with 7 points, securing early qualification already in the second round. Despite facing different scenarios and opponent strategies, Filipe Luís's team remained faithful to their dominant and pressing game model, even against a high-level opponent like Chelsea. Occasionally, the team had some variations, such as a 3-1-6 / 3-3-4, with one of the defensive midfielders dropping back to the defensive line, freeing both full-backs for attack. <br/><br/> Throughout the campaign, the red and black team not only remained unbeaten but was superior to all their opponents in crucial metrics: ball possession, completed passes, shots, tackles, and xG (Expected Goals). Even with player rotations, the offensive organization demonstrated a consistent pattern. To attack low blocks, the team transitioned from their 4-2-3-1 to a 3-2-5, with the left-back dropping back to form a line of three and the right-back advancing to provide width, supported by a double pivot in midfield. <br/><br/> <div class="row"> <div class="col-sm-6 offset-sm-3 mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2025-06-26-post_world_cup/fase_de_grupos/campinho.gif" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" title="example image" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> Flamengo's tactical changes. <br/><br/> </div> <h3> <b> Game 1: Flamengo 2-0 Espérance </b></h3> In their debut match at the Club World Cup, Flamengo defeated Espérance 2-0. The game was characterized by the tactical control and ball possession management of the Brazilian team, which knew how to impose their game model and neutralize the Tunisian opponent's strategy. <br/><br/> From the initial minutes, Flamengo's pressure forced the Tunisian team to abandon short build-up, opting for long balls. Defensively, Espérance congested the central corridor in a 4-3-3, but conceded the flanks. It was precisely through there that Flamengo dismantled the opponent's defense, with both goals in the match originating from crosses. The dominance translated into 69% ball possession and was quantified by pass network metrics: Flamengo showed higher density (0.4750 vs 0.4542), average degree of connections (14.25 vs 13.62), and clustering coefficient (0.1090 vs 0.0969). These numbers indicate a more connected team with a greater tendency for triangulations, which allowed for safe result management with a controlled number of 11 shots. <br/><br/> The analysis of this match's pass network established the importance of defenders and defensive midfielders as connectors. Léo Pereira (Defender) was the leader in pass volume (Weighted Degree: 206) and the main bridge between sectors, confirmed by the team's highest Betweenness Centrality (0.3857). Jorginho (Defensive Midfielder), second in volume (Weighted Degree: 179), was the key piece for triangulations, leading the team with the highest Clustering Coefficient (0.2200). Completing the axis, Erick Pulgar (Defensive Midfielder) acted as an efficient connector (Weighted Degree: 177; high Closeness Centrality: 0.7686), and Léo Ortiz (Defender) was a vital secondary link for defensive triangulations (Weighted Degree: 135; Clustering Coefficient: 0.1861). <br/><br/> <div class="row"> <div class="col-sm-7 offset-sm-3 mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2025-06-26-post_world_cup/fase_de_grupos/fla-esp.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" title="example image" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> Statistics of the Flamengo x Espérance match. <br/><br/> </div> <h3> <b> Game 2: Flamengo 3-1 Chelsea </b></h3> In their second game, Flamengo, with some changes in the lineup, defeated the English team 3-1, with direct participation of substitutions in the comeback goals. <br/><br/> The match had two distinct phases. In the first half, after conceding a goal in the 13th minute, Chelsea retreated. Flamengo dominated possession (63%) and passes (277 vs 162), but with difficulty creating clear chances, resulting in only 5 shots. The scenario changed in the second half. The red and black pressure became more effective, and with Bruno Henrique's entry, the team scored two goals in five minutes. After scoring the third goal in the 82nd minute, Flamengo inverted the strategy, conceded the ball to Chelsea, and began managing the score (61% possession and 244 passes for the English in the second half). The final statistics (possession 51% x 49%, passes 437 x 410) suggest a misleading balance that masks the distinct dominance phases. A clearer indicator of red and black superiority was the number of actions in the opponent's area: 27 vs 17. <br/><br/> The network analysis reinforced the importance of the defensive axis. Jorginho (Defensive Midfielder) was the most participative player (Weighted Degree: 113) and the key piece for triangulations, with the highest Clustering Coefficient (0.2236). Léo Pereira (Defender), with similar volume (Weighted Degree: 112), was the main authority in the network (highest PageRank: 0.1384). Defender Danilo (Weighted Degree: 100) quickly connected the sectors (highest Closeness Centrality: 0.7686), while Erick Pulgar (Weighted Degree: 91) acted as a bridge between defense and midfield (second highest Betweenness Centrality: 0.1298). For Chelsea, defender Trevoh Chalobah was the pillar, leading his team in volume (Weighted Degree: 105), closeness (0.8750), and betweenness (0.3434). <br/><br/> <div class="row"> <div class="col-sm-7 offset-sm-3 mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2025-06-26-post_world_cup/fase_de_grupos/fla-chel.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" title="example image" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> Statistics of the Flamengo x Chelsea match. <br/><br/> </div> <h3> <b> Game 3: Flamengo 1-1 LAFC </b></h3> In their third game, Flamengo, already qualified, drew 1-1 with LAFC in a more protocol match. Despite the heavily modified team, they demonstrated dominance against an LAFC parked in a 5-2-3. <br/><br/> The superiority was constant, reflected in overwhelming statistics: 66% ball possession, 19 to 5 in shots, 659 to 344 in passes, and 27 to 5 in actions in the opponent's area. Despite the volume, Flamengo was not effective, while LAFC converted their only great chance. The result was also strongly influenced by bad luck: there were five balls hitting the woodwork in the game (four from Flamengo). Modeling the group stage data (48 matches), the probability of such an event is only 0.12% (approximately 1 in 835), a rare case that evidences the exceptionality of what occurred. <br/><br/> The game model remained consistent even with an alternative team, with defenders and defensive midfielders being the team's hubs again. Jorginho (Defensive Midfielder) and Léo Pereira (Defender) repeated the previous game's performance, leading in pass volume with Weighted Degrees of 113 and 112, respectively, proving the system's strength. Danilo (Defender) also maintained high volume, with 100 passes. On LAFC's side, full-back Sergi Palencia was the main connector, leading his team in betweenness (0.5852), closeness (0.8750), and network authority (PageRank: 0.1427). <br/><br/> <div class="row"> <div class="col-sm-7 offset-sm-3 mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2025-06-26-post_world_cup/fase_de_grupos/fla-lafc.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" title="example image" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> Statistics of the Flamengo x Los Angeles FC match. <br/><br/> </div> <h2> <b> Conclusion </b></h2> Flamengo demonstrated a dominant and consistent performance throughout the entire group stage, maintaining their characteristic game model even in the face of different opponent strategies. The red and black team not only remained unbeaten but was also superior in all important metrics, consolidating their position as one of the tournament's main forces. <br/><br/> </div>]]></content><author><name>Ace Laboratory Football Team - Murilo Jorge</name></author><category term="Football;"/><category term="Analysis"/><category term="Football;"/><category term="Analysis;"/><category term="Club"/><category term="World"/><category term="Cup"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Flamengo's Dominant Group Stage Performance at the Club World Cup]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Fluminense’s Solid Group Stage Performance at the Club World Cup</title><link href="https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2025/fluminense_grupos_en/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Fluminense’s Solid Group Stage Performance at the Club World Cup"/><published>2025-06-26T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-06-26T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2025/fluminense_grupos_en</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2025/fluminense_grupos_en/"><![CDATA[<hr/> <p align="justify"> Se quiser ler este texto em pt-br, <a href="https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2000/fluminense_grupos_pt/"> clique aqui.</a> </p> <h2> <b> Introduction </b></h2> <div style="text-align: justify"> Fluminense, the Rio de Janeiro club managed by Renato Gaúcho, arrives at the World Cup at a very good moment for the club. A sequence of 6 unbeaten games for the Tricolor, which was put at risk in a group containing 3 giants from 3 different continents: Borussia Dortmund (Germany), Mamelodi Sundowns (South Africa), and Ulsan HD (South Korea). <br/><br/> <h3> <b> Game 1: Fluminense 0-0 Borussia Dortmund </b></h3> Fluminense's debut at the Club World Cup was marked by a surprising match against Borussia Dortmund. Against the main opponent in the group, Renato Gaúcho's team managed to impose their ideals for much of the game, coming dangerously close numerous times. So much so that Kobel, the German team's goalkeeper, was the best player of the match, with a rating of 8.2 (Sofascore). Despite the goalless draw and inferiority in ball possession, many considered the Brazilian team superior in the game. <br/><br/> Despite Borussia's superiority in ball possession in both parts of the game, few were the times they brought concrete danger to Fábio's goal. With the high volume of play through the wings, Fluminense managed to impose themselves through the flanks and propose play in the middle of the field, winning 67% of duels. The German team couldn't be efficient, despite managing to control the ball more (54% possession) and make more accurate passes (263). <br/><br/> In the second half, the intensity of both teams dropped, but Borussia managed to explore their ideal game a bit more. Their possession increased by 1% and the team began to win their offensive duels (55% duels won) and defensive duels (71% duels won), and this led goalkeeper Fábio to make 3 saves, the only ones of the game. Given the greater volume, this exposed the team to counterattacks — Fluminense's main chance came from a counterattack after a long pass from Hércules to Everaldo. <br/><br/> The game ended in a 0-0 draw, with 14 shots (5 on target) for Fluminense and 7 (3 on target) for Borussia. Despite inferior possession, the Tricolor demonstrated maturity to execute their offensive plays and overcome the German team's defense with their fast style of play and their speed transitions through the wings. <br/><br/> <h3> <b> Game 2: Fluminense 4-2 Ulsan HD </b></h3> Fluminense delivered a great performance against the current three-time South Korean champion, Ulsan HD. The 4-2 victory, despite some defensive lapses, was convincing. The Tricolor's game was characterized by the high positioning of players, exchanging relatively short passes in the midfield and opponent's area, resulting in an impressive 70% possession and 92% accurate passes by the end of the match. The game, however, was not without scares for Fluminense, who suffered a comeback at the end of the first half, leading Renato Gaúcho to make a bet on an even more offensive game with the exit of Ganso and the entry of Everaldo. The risk paid off, as the superiority of actions in the final third of the field yielded 3 goals and sealed Fluminense's victory. The great highlight of the match was Jhon Arias, who showed himself extremely present on both sides of the field, scoring a beautiful free-kick goal and providing an assist to Keno at the end of the game. <br/><br/> <div class="row"> <div class="col-sm-6 offset-sm-3 mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/Posts_Images/2025-06-26-post_world_cup/fase_de_grupos/network_passes_flu_ulsan.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" title="example image" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> Fluminense's pass network against Ulsan HD. <br/><br/> </div> <h3> <b> Game 3: Mamelodi Sundowns 0-0 Fluminense </b></h3> In the final round, the group was wide open. Any of the teams had a chance, even if small, to qualify. In a game where Fluminense only needed a draw and Mamelodi Sundowns needed a victory, the game demonstrated the importance it was for each team — the South African team managed to neutralize various offensive weapons of the Tricolor and was superior almost throughout the entire game (67% possession in the first half and 69% in the second). This 0-0 draw is largely due to the outstanding defensive performance of Fluminense's team, with about 67% of tackles won and 42 ball recoveries. It's also important to recognize the maturity and defensive organization of the South African team, as they managed to neutralize the main player of the Rio team: Jhon Arias. He had the lowest number of actions on the ball among the 3 games (57) and couldn't shoot on goal. Renato Gaúcho knew how to play with a tactic that invited the opponent forward and managed to extract the draw, securing qualification in second place in the group. <br/><br/> <h2> <b> Conclusion </b></h2> Fluminense's group stage was not easy. They played a surprising debut match, made big mistakes despite the convincing victory in the second match, and played an extremely dull final game. The predictions showed Fluminense as the third force in this group: 39.4% chance of advancing to the round of 16, behind Mamelodi Sundowns (47.1%) and Borussia Dortmund (74.9%) (Opta). Despite this, the team managed to qualify in a difficult group. The Flu had both defensive lapses and wasted goal opportunities, which should be crucial points for improvement in the next game. <br/><br/> Offensively, the lack of rhythm due to Germán Cano's recovery is notable, as the Argentine had 5 shots on goal and missed 3 chances. The striker was gaining rhythm throughout the 3 games, but it wasn't enough to see him at his best form, which is crucial for Fluminense. Still, Cano had only fewer shots than Jhon Arias (9), who was twice elected as the best player of the match by FIFA and obtained the best Sofascore rating in all group stage games. Defensively, the Rio team had lapses against Ulsan HD, but overall, had a good performance, with clean sheets in the other two games. The good performance of the Tricolor defense — with highlights for Freytes and Renê — resulted in few shots against Fluminense, especially in the game against Mamelodi Sundowns and Borussia Dortmund; in comparison, only Ulsan HD had fewer shots in the match against the German team. With a match scheduled against Inter Milan, it wouldn't be controversial to say that Fluminense has every chance to maintain the sequence of Brazilian team qualifications in this Club World Cup. <br/><br/> </div>]]></content><author><name>Ace Laboratory Football Team - Miguel Angelo e Pedro Lopes</name></author><category term="Football;"/><category term="Analysis"/><category term="Football;"/><category term="Analysis;"/><category term="Club"/><category term="World"/><category term="Cup"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Fluminense's Solid Group Stage Performance at the Club World Cup]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Palmeiras’ Group Stage Performance at the Club World Cup</title><link href="https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2025/palmeiras_grupos_en/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Palmeiras’ Group Stage Performance at the Club World Cup"/><published>2025-06-26T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-06-26T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2025/palmeiras_grupos_en</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2025/palmeiras_grupos_en/"><![CDATA[<hr/> <p align="justify"> Se quiser ler este texto em pt-br, <a href="https://ac3lab.github.io/blog/2000/palmeiras_grupos_pt/"> clique aqui.</a> </p> <h2> <b> Introduction </b></h2> <div style="text-align: justify"> Palmeiras advances to the next phase, but doesn't convince. In 3 matches full of ups and downs, the green and white team that remains unbeaten in the Club World Cup achieved 2 draws and 1 victory that led them to first place in Group B. In the next phase, their opponent will be Botafogo, which, despite qualifying in second place in their group, promises to give the São Paulo team a hard time. <br/><br/> <h3> <b> Analysis of the Three Matches </b></h3> The analysis of the first three matches points to a team very comfortable playing reactively, trying to take advantage of opponent's mistakes to activate their attackers at speed and take advantage of a likely disorganized defensive sector to create their main goal-scoring opportunities, which was also reflected in a lower number of passes exchanged by the team compared to opponents in the second and third games. Not by chance, most of Abel Ferreira's team's converted chances have as their starting point a counterattack or a ball recovered still in the offensive sector. <br/><br/> Another well-known strength of the green and white team is aerial play, with good headers like Flaco Lopez, Murilo, and Gustavo Gómez (who won 100% of aerial duels attempted in this first phase), crosses and set-piece situations usually bring danger to the opposing team. As an example of this, we have the two goals against Al Ahly; the first was the result of an offensive set-piece crossed into the area, which forced the Egyptian team to take a more offensive stance and offer more gaps for the reactive game plan so well worked by Palmeiras' team, while the second had its play initiated with a victory in an aerial duel in Palmeiras' defensive area, which triggered a devastating counterattack leaving Flaco Lopez with a clear path to attack from the midfield line. <br/><br/> <h3> <b> Negative Points </b></h3> Despite these unquestionably strong points, not everything is going well for the São Paulo team. The group stage games (especially the last one) exposed two flaws of the green team in this World Cup. The first and most notable is the lack of creativity during the offensive phase, the poor form experienced by Raphael Veiga (the team's main playmaker) compromises the entire play creation process, thus most attacks result in an attempt to cross into the center of the area, almost 90 in total across the three games, and although they were so numerous, they generally have little effectiveness (especially when Flaco Lopez is not on the field); as an alternative to the poor form of number 23, the coach has been betting on another midfielder, the young Maurício, who started the competition as a starter and came on in the other two games at halftime, in those minutes on the field, he accumulated more offensive actions, including an assist in the game against Al Ahly, and the equalizing goal against Inter Miami. <br/><br/> The second negative point of Palmeiras' team is the lack of aggressiveness of the team without their starting defensive midfield duo. The absence of Aníbal Moreno in the game against Inter Miami was greatly felt by Abel Ferreira's team, which, when positioned in the defensive sector, did not show the necessary intensity to recover the ball. Another consequence of this also notable in this last game was the performance of Richard Rios, who, finding himself without his usual partner, participated in 50% more plays with the ball compared to the other two matches and doubled his number of passes compared to his average, in addition to having his positioning affected, performing more functions in midfield. <br/><br/> <h2> <b> Conclusion </b></h2> Finally, Palmeiras' next opponent promises to be a great challenge. Both teams have fast attacks and abuse quick transitions, which indicates a dynamic and high-intensity game. Another highlight is the absence of midfielder Gregore in the black and white team, a fundamental piece in Botafogo's midfield. It remains to be seen whether Abel Ferreira's team will have the necessary intensity and competence to advance to the next phase. <br/><br/> </div>]]></content><author><name>Ace Laboratory Football Team - Gabriel Madruga e João Victor</name></author><category term="Football;"/><category term="Analysis"/><category term="Football;"/><category term="Analysis;"/><category term="Club"/><category term="World"/><category term="Cup"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Palmeiras' Group Stage Performance at the Club World Cup]]></summary></entry></feed>